<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><atom:link href="https://danlebrero.com" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><title>Daniel Lebrero Berna Blog</title><link>https://danlebrero.com</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><description>Daniel Lebrero blog</description><generator>clj-rss</generator><item><title>Book notes: The Ascetic Programmer   </title><link>https://danlebrero.com/2024/05/29/the-ascetic-programmer-book-summary/</link><guid>https://danlebrero.com/2024/05/29/the-ascetic-programmer-book-summary/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><description><![CDATA[<p>These are my notes on <a href="https://amzn.to/3wO30sU">The Ascetic Programmer: How asceticism benefits programming, science, and the arts</a> by <a href="https://toot.community/@piccolbo">Antonio Piccolboni</a>.</p><p>A case to &ldquo;do more with less&rdquo; (conciseness) and &ldquo;less is more&rdquo; (frugality), without forgetting that is not that easy:</p>
<blockquote><p>I would have written a shorter letter, but I did not have the time <cite>Blaise Pascal</cite></p>
</blockquote><h1>Key Insights</h1>
<ul>
  <li><p>Lines of code are a valuable measure of program complexity.</p>
  <blockquote>If we wish to count lines of code, we should not regard them as &ldquo;lines produced&rdquo; but as &ldquo;lines spent&rdquo; <cite>Dijkstra</cite>
  </blockquote></li>
  <li>The difference between a compressed program and a concise one is that the latter is human-intelligible.</li>
  <li>I considered what was written eons ago sacred.</li>
  <li>More general functions create indirect dependencies between parts of a program and, thus, more of the entanglement.</li>
  <li>If keeping two programs completely independent is paramount, an option is duplicating.</li>
  <li>Often code can grow as an accumulation of special cases until we realize a general rule that can replace them and covers additional ones as a bonus.</li>
  <li>If a long variable name works as documentation, is having to read it every time you run into it a good idea?</li>
  <li>Any non-trivial program should define the concepts relevant to the task on hand and implement data structures and operations to represent and manipulate those concepts, and this extends the language.</li>
  <li>Languages are defined by what they allow and what they prevent.</li>
  <li>Languages that forbid many constructs preclude them from expressing valid computations, hence developers will have to use longer programs to define equivalent computations.</li>
  <li>A simpler language should also be less powerful and therefore require more code for the same tasks:
  <ul>
    <li>However, Lisp sidesteps this trade-off to some degree.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Code generation isn&rsquo;t a suitable replacement for abstraction.</li>
  <li>Making many more assumptions about what you&rsquo;re trying to do allows to be much more concise, at some cost of generality.</li>
  <li>Developers give up on reading source code beyond what is strictly necessary to add their contributions.</li>
  <li>Machine Learning: the complexity just morphed, but it is learned from data rather than hand-coded.</li>
  <li>Short programs are easier to test.</li>
  <li>Maintaining simplicity in the face of supporting new features requires a constant, organized, resourced effort.</li>
  <li>Working on reducing complexity is generally considered second-class work and not career-boosting.</li>
  <li>You can&rsquo;t become a superstar if you have to pick the next entry in a so-called backlog.</li>
  <li>Lawrence Kesteloot: Every line of code you write is a potential bug.</li>
  <li>Two approaches in API design:
  <ol>
    <li>Minimal.</li>
    <li>Humane: strives to support as many reasonable use cases as possible.</li>
  </ol>
  <ul>
    <li>A developer writing against a minimal API will have to write more code but learn less than against a humane one.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Bad code begets bad code.</li>
  <li>Let the rot spread a little and meet your deadline.</li>
  <li>Development these days is fragmented into long series of self-inflicted emergencies.</li>
  <li>Deep Learning: Sun and co-authors concluded that &ldquo;performance increases logarithmically based on volume of training data&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>The Parsimony Principle: plurality should not be posited without necessity.</li>
  <li>Shorter sentences are easier to read and understand.</li>
  <li>Everything that is not useful in the picture is, it follows, harmful.</li>
  <li>Not only can most things wait, most things should. You either can&rsquo;t stop thinking about them, or those thoughts fade away. Let time do some work for you.
  <ul>
    <li>Time acts as a filter.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1>TOC</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#ch-0">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#ch-1">Chapter 1 - Computing</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-1.1">1.1 - Metrics</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-1.2">1.2 - Concise Software</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-1.3">1.3 - Frugal Software</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-1.4">1.4 - Hardware</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-1.5">1.5 - Verbosity and Bloatware</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-1.6">1.6 - Code Considered Harmful</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#ch-2">Chapter 2 - Science and Engineering</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-2.1">2.1 - Epistemology, Statistics and Machine Learning</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-2.3">2.3 - Engineering and Design</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#ch-3">Chapter 3 - Literature, Visual Arts and More</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-3.1">3.1 - Speaking and Writing</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-3.2">3.2 - Visual Arts</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-3.4">3.4 - Management</a></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-0"></a>Introduction</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Asceticism in programming comes in two flavors, roughly described by the slogans &ldquo;do more with less&rdquo; (conciseness) and &ldquo;less is more&rdquo; (frugality).</li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t expect a grand theory, but rather a series of interconnected anecdotes and expert opinions, interspersed with the occasional theorem and research paper.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-1"></a>Chapter 1 - Computing</h1><h2><a name="ch-1.1"></a>1.1 - Metrics</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Lines of code are a valuable measure of program complexity.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>If we wish to count lines of code, we should not regard them as &ldquo;lines produced&rdquo; but as &ldquo;lines spent&rdquo; <cite>Dijkstra</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
  <li>Alternatives:
  <ul>
    <li>Counting tokens.</li>
    <li>Cyclomatic complexity:
    <ul>
      <li>Correlates well with program size.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Properties that predict program size:
  <ul>
    <li>Number of bugs (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capers_Jones">Capers Jones</a>).</li>
    <li>Probability of project failure.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-1.2"></a>1.2 - Concise Software</h2>
<ul>
  <li>There are entire methodologies aimed at creating arbitrary deadlines and fostering a fictional sense of emergency.
  <ul>
    <li>Limits on size are rarely, if ever, encountered.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Sometimes you have to write 500 unnecessary lines of code to get to the 50 absolutely necessary lines of code.</li>
  <li>The difference between a compressed program and a concise one is that the latter is human-intelligible.</li>
  <li>A line of code&rsquo;s further costs are in the future and harder to estimate.
  <ul>
    <li>We hardly ever tried to estimate those delayed costs. Therefore, the incentives to delete are weaker.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Nobody taught me how to delete code.
  <ul>
    <li>I considered what was written eons ago sacred.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Where does the quasi-repetition stop, and where does the &ldquo;vaguely related code&rdquo; start?</li>
  <li>Even when identification is easy, there may not be time to eliminate repetition because of the work required.
  <ul>
    <li>However, writing a ticket to mark some duplication we left unattended generally isn&rsquo;t a career boosting move, and those tickets never get taken care of regardless.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>More general functions create indirect dependencies between parts of a program and, thus, more of the entanglement.</li>
  <li>If keeping two programs completely independent is paramount, an option is duplicating.</li>
  <li>Conciseness and modularity are two sides of coping with size.</li>
  <li>Often code can grow as an accumulation of special cases until we realize a general rule that can replace them and covers additional ones as a bonus.</li>
  <li>More code often means less flexibility and functionality.</li>
  <li>Different abstraction techniques are touted for their potential to reduce coupling and not for any conciseness advantage.</li>
  <li>Bill Atkinson used to report a negative number of lines contributed, including a &ldquo;-2000&rdquo; in the week he had rewritten some routines in QuickDraw to be six times faster.</li>
  <li>If a long variable name works as documentation, is having to read it every time you run into it a good idea?</li>
  <li>Who enjoys reading documentation?</li>
  <li>Joshua Bloch: APIs should be self-documenting.</li>
  <li>Any non-trivial program should define the concepts relevant to the task on hand and implement data structures and operations to represent and manipulate those concepts, and this extends the language.</li>
  <li>Languages are defined by what they allow and what they prevent.</li>
  <li>Paul Graham: Macros can do two things that functions can&rsquo;t: hey can control (or prevent) the evaluation of their arguments, and they are expanded right into the calling context.</li>
  <li>Guy Steele: It&rsquo;s really hard to make a language that&rsquo;s great at everything, in part just because there are only so many concise notations to go around. There&rsquo;s this Huffman encoding problem.</li>
  <li>Languages that forbid many constructs preclude them from expressing valid computations, hence developers will have to use longer programs to define equivalent computations.</li>
  <li>A language with many ways to express the same computation will lead to more verbose programs.</li>
  <li>Defining more common computations with shorter programs and accepting some verbosity for less common ones could be a good compromise but implies different languages tailored for different domains.</li>
  <li>A simpler language should also be less powerful and therefore require more code for the same tasks:
  <ul>
    <li>However, Lisp sidesteps this trade-off to some degree.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Verbose code is something to skim in long, painful, lonely sessions.</li>
  <li>Users love these more concise forms, but having multiple evaluation rules makes programs harder to understand and hinders their parametrization and generalization.</li>
  <li>Code generation isn&rsquo;t a suitable replacement for abstraction.</li>
  <li>POJO-aggrieved Java programmers.</li>
  <li>No API designer can escape the compromise between the complexity of an API, its power, and the complexity of user code.</li>
  <li>Edward Tufte:
  <ul>
    <li>Data-ink ratio, the ratio of ink spent to display data vs the total amount used in a chart, and recommended maximizing it.</li>
    <li>Data density: the number of data points per unit of area.</li>
    <li>Display lots of data with just enough ink, minimize and de-emphasize everything that isn&rsquo;t data.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/3VdaYoN">Grammar of graphics</a> by Leland Wilkinson.
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://vega.github.io/vega/">Vega project</a>.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Making many more assumptions about what you&rsquo;re trying to do allows to be much more concise, at some cost of generality.</li>
  <li>This lack of modularity is sometimes positively spun as coming &ldquo;batteries included&rdquo;, meaning that any integration challenges are taken care of.</li>
  <li>Two orders of magnitude fewer lines of code mean a lot less attack surface.</li>
  <li>A much smaller codebase also means code that is more likely to work the way it is supposed to.</li>
  <li>Developers give up on reading source code beyond what is strictly necessary to add their contributions.</li>
  <li>If you need one KLOC to fix a bug and can produce it within the available time, so be it. The maintenance bill doesn&rsquo;t reach the original author.</li>
  <li>Machine Learning: the complexity just morphed, but it is learned from data rather than hand-coded.</li>
  <li>Short programs are easier to test.</li>
  <li>GolfScript: unlike most code blocks in this book, we will not try to understand this one.</li>
  <li>What is valid for programs continues to be so at the level of system architecture.</li>
  <li>Heroku: Only by concertedly building a minimal stack that is stable and nearly operable can we maximize our ability to push forward with new products and ideas.</li>
  <li>Maintaining simplicity in the face of supporting new features requires a constant, organized, resourced effort.</li>
  <li>Minimalism is a necessary condition for the evolution of the product, not a &ldquo;nice to have&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>If the pressure to build new features engenders complexity, we can work to reduce it after the fact.</li>
  <li>The progression toward complexity is reversible.</li>
  <li>Working on reducing complexity is generally considered second-class work and not career-boosting.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-1.3"></a>1.3 - Frugal Software</h2>
<ul>
  <li>It isn&rsquo;t so much the code they write, but they decide to work on.</li>
  <li>You can&rsquo;t become a superstar if you have to pick the next entry in a so-called backlog.</li>
  <li>Atwood: If you can&rsquo;t get away with no code, next best thing is to start with brevity.</li>
  <li>Lawrence Kesteloot: Every line of code you write is a potential bug.</li>
  <li>Atwood: visible logging code is clutter, it actively obscures the code that is doing the real work in the application. We have since removed all logging from Stack Overflow, relying exclusively on exception logging. Honestly, I don&rsquo;t miss it at all.</li>
  <li>Filter feature requests before queuing them.</li>
  <li>Two approaches in API design:
  <ol>
    <li>Minimal.</li>
    <li>Humane: strives to support as many reasonable use cases as possible.</li>
  </ol>
  <ul>
    <li>A developer writing against a minimal API will have to write more code but learn less than against a humane one.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Josue Block:
  <ul>
    <li>API should be as small as possible, but not smaller.</li>
    <li>The two requirements seem to almost directly contradict each other.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>What is more frugal than an API with a single entry that does it all?</li>
  <li>&ldquo;Negative feature list&rdquo;: a list of features that it does not offer.</li>
  <li>Mythical Man-Month: it is better to have a system omit certain anomalous features and improvements, but to reflect one set of design ideas, than to have one that contains many good but independent and uncoordinated ideas.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-1.4"></a>1.4 - Hardware</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The missing keyboard of the iPhone.</li>
  <li>RISC architecture.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-1.5"></a>1.5 - Verbosity and Bloatware</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Hoare: Wouldn&rsquo;t you be delighted if your Fairy Godmother offered to wave her wand over your program to remove all its errors and only made the condition that you should write out and key in your whole program three times!</li>
  <li>After a bug was identified while in orbit, Boeing decided to review the whole code base for the project.
  <ul>
    <li>Unfortunately, there were already a million LOC to review.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Maciej Ceglowski: two steps secret to improve the performance of any website:
  <ol>
    <li>Make sure that the most important elements of teh page download and render first.</li>
    <li><p>Stop there. You don&rsquo;t need all that other crap. </p>
    <blockquote>There are two ways of constructing a software design: one way is to make it so simple that there are obviously no deficiencies and the other way is to make it so complicated that there are no obvious deficiencies. The first method is far more difficult. <cite><a href="http://zoo.cs.yale.edu/classes/cs422/2011/bib/hoare81emperor.pdf">Hoare</a></cite>
    </blockquote></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>SQL is not a small language. PostgreSQL implementation contains 469 keywords. Just part 2 (out of 14) of the SQL:2016 standard has 1732 pages.</li>
  <li>If the DRY principle guides Python and Ruby, Java should be considered a WET language: Write Explicitly Tenfold.</li>
  <li>Bad code begets bad code.</li>
  <li>Let the rot spread a little and meet your deadline.</li>
  <li>Development these days is fragmented into long series of self-inflicted emergencies.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-1.6"></a>1.6 - Code Considered Harmful</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Go To Statement.</li>
  <li>Ifs: <a href="https://www.antiifprogramming.com/about-the-anti-if.php">Anti-If Manifesto</a>.</li>
  <li>Class inheritance.</li>
  <li>You have never been paid to write code. Indeed, code is a nasty byproduct of being a sw dev.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-2"></a>Chapter 2 - Science and Engineering</h1><h2><a name="ch-2.1"></a>2.1 - Epistemology, Statistics and Machine Learning</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The Parsimony Principle:
  <ul>
    <li>Plurality should not be posited without necessity.</li>
    <li>Aristotle: we may assume the superiority, other things being equal, of the demonstration which derives from fewer postulates or hypotheses.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Bayesian statistics inadequate for science, as conclusions are too dependent on the choice of prior - that is why its dominant variant is called subjective Bayesianism.</li>
  <li>Deep Learning: Sun and co-authors concluded that &ldquo;performance increases logarithmically based on volume of training data&rdquo;.
  <ul>
    <li>An additive improvement requires order-of-magnitude larger datasets and models and two orders of magnitude more computing power.</li>
    <li>Convolutional nets and deep nets, which, for the same size, show better performance.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-2.3"></a>2.3 - Engineering and Design</h2>
<blockquote><p>Perfection is finally attained not when there is no longer anything to add, but when there is no longer anything to take away <cite>Antonie de Saint-Exupery</cite></p>
</blockquote><h1><a name="ch-3"></a>Chapter 3 - Literature, Visual Arts and More</h1><h2><a name="ch-3.1"></a>3.1 - Speaking and Writing</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Shorter sentences are easier to read and understand.</li>
  <li>With strict paper length limits: Many a choice turn of phrase and illustrative simile had to be sacrificed to precision, flow and brevity.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>I would have written a shorter letter, but I did not have the time <cite>Blaise Pascal</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
  <li>Plausibly extending a text was easier for this AI system than summarizing it.</li>
  <li>Lawyered-up companies try to gain the upper end on smaller ones or private citizens by overwhelming them with long and complex contracts.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-3.2"></a>3.2 - Visual Arts</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Everything that is not useful in the picture is, it follows, harmful.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-3.4"></a>3.4 - Management</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Not only can most things wait, most things should. You either can&rsquo;t stop thinking about them, or those thoughts fade away. Let time do some work for you.</li>
  <li>Time acts as a filter.</li>
</ul>]]></description></item><item><title>Book notes: Flow Engineering</title><link>https://danlebrero.com/2024/05/01/flow-enginnering-book-summary/</link><guid>https://danlebrero.com/2024/05/01/flow-enginnering-book-summary/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><description><![CDATA[<p>These are my notes on <a href="https://amzn.to/4bi6p1H">Flow Engineering: From Value Stream Mapping to Effective Action</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/steveelsewhere/">Steve Pereira</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewDavis_io">Andrew Davis</a>.</p><p>&ldquo;Flow Engineering is a set of practices that build on the foundations of cybernetics and the Toyota Production System to provide a lightweight and iterative way of building value, clarity, and flow.&rdquo;</p><p>I love the approach to do the minimal amount of work to take you to next step:</p>
<blockquote><p>Value Stream Map in Flow Engineering is significantly simpler than the traditional one.</p>
</blockquote><p>You can find a Miro board with <a href="https://miro.com/app/board/uXjVKNndJVU=/?share_link_id=73825138920">all Flow Engineering Maps</a>.</p><h1>Key Insights</h1>
<ul>
  <li>The default approach to addressing the problem of scale is to increase coordination.</li>
  <li>In the absence of a simple purpose oriented around the customer, teams default to acting in incoherent and self-serving ways.</li>
  <li>The fastest path to clarity is visibility.</li>
  <li>Silos are a natural consequence of specialization and scale.</li>
  <li>Ringelmann effect: as more people are involved in a task, their average performance decreases, with each participant tending to feel that their own effort is not critical to overall performance.</li>
  <li>Solution to scale must have:
  <ol>
    <li>Engage all participants, like generative methods, to avoid disengagement.</li>
    <li>Simple and aligned, like prescriptive methods, to avoid disorientation.</li>
    <li>Fast and easy to put into practice, unlike prescriptive methods, to avoid distraction.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>To manage and optimize the flow of work, we must first see the flow of work.</li>
  <li>Value is our target, clarity allow us to understand a path to the target, and flow is about optimizing that path.</li>
  <li>Value, clarity and flow are hard to establish and easily lost.</li>
  <li>The act of mapping enables you to learn by doing.</li>
  <li>Maps:
  <ol>
    <li>Outcome Map:
    <ul>
      <li>Goal is to focus the team while surfacing doubts, testing assumptions, and enabling the emergence of new insights.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Current State Value Stream Map.</li>
    <li>Dependency Map: identify dependencies by studying constraints.</li>
    <li>Future State Value Stream Map: how things will look like in 6 months.</li>
    <li>Flow Roadmap: organize insights, actions, and ownership into an improvement roadmap.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>If there are no obstacle to achieving our desired goal, we would already be there.</li>
  <li>Explicit obstacles mean they can be dealt with consciously.</li>
  <li>Working backwards involves beginning with a clear definition of a desired target state (outcome) and using that target to guide decisions and actions.</li>
  <li>Where there is a customer, there is a value stream.</li>
  <li>For Value Stream Mapping (VSM) to be effective, the team needs to be aligned on their objectives and aspirations.</li>
  <li>Don Reinertsen, in <a href="https://amzn.to/3VP4c9k">Principles of Product Development Flow</a>:
  <ul>
    <li>The value added by an activity is the difference in the price that an economically rational buyer would pay for a work product before, and after, the activity is performed.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Cocreating a Current State Value Stream Map reveals issues that allow teams to get at least 20% of their time back immediately.</li>
  <li>&ldquo;It depends&rdquo; isn&rsquo;t an acceptable excuse for deliberation.</li>
  <li>The rapid VSM done in Flow Engineering intentionally sacrifices precision for speed and ease:
  <ul>
    <li>Aim to gather just enough information to identify a critical constraint.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Nothing is ever truly autonomous.</li>
  <li>An SLA will consume the maximum time the SLA allows.</li>
  <li><p>Approach Dependency Mapping with curiosity, not accusation or demand.</p>
  <blockquote>Seek first to understand, then to be understood <cite>Stephen Covey, The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People</cite>
  </blockquote></li>
  <li><a href="/2021/01/06/toyota-kata-in-software-development-continuous-improvement/">Improvement Kata cycle</a>:
  <ol>
    <li>Vision and challenge: Outcome Map.</li>
    <li>Gasp current condition: Current State Map and Dependency Map.</li>
    <li>Target condition: Future State Map.</li>
    <li>Experiments: Flow Roadmap.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Work in progress is the silent killer of productivity.</li>
  <li>You may miss something going too fast, and you may waste time going too deep.</li>
  <li>Delivering value is an act of cooperation, not a zero-sum game.</li>
  <li>We can only measure value by getting feedback from those experiencing it.</li>
  <li>Flow implies a quality of steadiness in motion.</li>
  <li>Optimizing for flow is contradictory to optimizing for resource utilization.</li>
  <li>In sw dev, there is significant variation in how long work takes, so you need slack capacity to accommodate this variation.</li>
  <li>Creating a pull-based system of work is an extraordinary feat.</li>
  <li>Learning is central to removing waste.</li>
  <li>Streetlight effect: we tend to look for things where it&rsquo;s easy to look.</li>
  <li>If you are not getting better, you are getting worse.</li>
  <li><a href="#types">Developmental vs Operational</a> value streams and Core vs Supportive value streams.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>Strategy is a commodity, execution is an art <cite>Peter Drucker</cite></p>
</blockquote><h1>TOC</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#ch-0">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#p-1">Part 1 - The Flow Landscape</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-1">Chapter 1 - The Problem with Scale</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-2">Chapter 2 - Solutions to Scale</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-3">Chapter 3 - The Elements of Action</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-4">Chapter 4 - Flow Engineering</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-2">Part 2 - Mapping the Landscape</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-5">Chapter 5 - Outcome Mapping</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-6">Chapter 6 - Current State Value Stream Mapping</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-7">Chapter 7 - Dependency Mapping</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-8">Chapter 8 - Future State Value Stream Mapping</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-9">Chapter 9 - The Flow Roadmap</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-3">Part 3 - Navigating the Landscape</a></li>
  <li><a href="#ch-10">Chapter 10 - Principles of Flow Engineering</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-11">Chapter 11 - Leading Flow Engineering</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-12">Chapter 12 - Traps to Avoid</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-13">Chapter 13 - Value Stream Management</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-14">Chapter 14 - Scaling Flow Engineering</a></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-0"></a>Introduction</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Radical transformations (Lean/Agile/DevOps) often devolve into rebranding and renaming the status quo.</li>
  <li>Clarity is often sacrificed at the altar of getting things done.</li>
  <li>The default approach to addressing the problem of scale is to increase coordination.</li>
  <li>Maturation as an individual/team/org is shifting our energy from survival to benevolence.</li>
  <li>To enable an effective and sustainable flow of work, a team&rsquo;s shared purpose needs to be oriented around the customer.
  <ul>
    <li>In the absence of a simple purpose oriented around the customer, teams default to acting in incoherent and self-serving ways.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>The fastest path to clarity is visibility.</li>
  <li>The paradox of modern orgs is that the more specialized workers become, the more they struggle to understand the broader system in which they fit.
  <ul>
    <li>Silos are a natural consequence of specialization and scale.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Flow Engineering is a series of collaborative mapping exercises designed to connect the dots between an unclear current state a clear path to a target state.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-1"></a>Part 1 - The Flow Landscape</h1><h2><a name="ch-1"></a>Chapter 1 - The Problem with Scale</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Scale undermines the foundations of effective action.</li>
  <li>Costs brought on by scale:
  <ul>
    <li>Distraction.</li>
    <li>Disorientation.</li>
    <li>Disengagement.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Ringelmann effect: as more people are involved in a task, their average performance decreases, with each participant tending to feel that their own effort is not critical to overall performance.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-2"></a>Chapter 2 - Solutions to Scale</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Prescriptive methods:
  <ul>
    <li>Centralized approach.</li>
    <li>Small number of leaders/experts define how teams should organize and interact.</li>
    <li>Provide more clarity and direction.</li>
    <li>Heavy and constraining.</li>
    <li>&ldquo;All or nothing&rdquo;.</li>
    <li>Requires massive investment in learning and structure.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Generative methods:
  <ul>
    <li>Distributed approach.</li>
    <li>Bring stakeholders throughout the org and hope they find an emergent solution.</li>
    <li>When people are involved in creating a solution, they are more invested in delivering the outcome.</li>
    <li>Takes longer.</li>
    <li>Individual contributors can lack important context.</li>
    <li>Challenging to convert into clear, actionable business value.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Solution to scale must have:
  <ol>
    <li>Engage all participants, like generative methods, to avoid disengagement.</li>
    <li>Simple and aligned, like prescriptive methods, to avoid disorientation.</li>
    <li>Fast and easy to put into practice, unlike prescriptive methods, to avoid distraction.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Cybernetics: any attempt to navigate towards a goal depends on effective control systems.</li>
  <li>The scope of a value stream is the complete loop from customer need to customer satisfaction.
  <ul>
    <li>It represents a complete cybernetic control system.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>To manage and optimize the flow of work, we must first see the flow of work.</li>
  <li>Flow Engineering is a set of practices that build on the foundations of cybernetics and the Toyota Production System to provide a lightweight and iterative way of building value, clarity, and flow.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-3"></a>Chapter 3 - The Elements of Action</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Value is our target, clarity allow us to understand a path to the target, and flow is about optimizing that path.</li>
  <li>Value, clarity and flow are hard to establish and easily lost.</li>
  <li>Human collaboration doesn&rsquo;t scale naturally.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-4"></a>Chapter 4 - Flow Engineering</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The act of mapping enables you to learn by doing.</li>
  <li>Aim to address the gaps in understanding that arise from silos of activity, concern, and visibility.</li>
  <li>It enables effective collective action.</li>
  <li>Connects the dots from efforts, activities, and improvements to the most critical focus for the organization.</li>
  <li>Build relationships across stakeholders and contributors.</li>
  <li>5 key maps:
  <ol>
    <li>Outcome Map: target outcome.</li>
    <li>Current State Value Stream Map: constraints in the current workflow.</li>
    <li>Dependency Map: identify dependencies by studying constraints.</li>
    <li>Future State Value Stream Map.</li>
    <li>Flow Roadmap: organize insights, actions, and ownership into an improvement roadmap.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>When:
  <ul>
    <li>To cut costs, boost efficiency, or improve time to market.</li>
    <li>Reorg.</li>
    <li>Your calendar is eaten up by meetings.</li>
    <li>Acquisition.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Who:
  <ul>
    <li>Responsible and accountable parties within a given value stream.</li>
    <li>Leadership and those who are able to change the system.</li>
    <li>You can maximize context and clarity by involved the same group in all mappings.</li>
    <li>12 people max.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Facilitator:
  <ul>
    <li>Should not have skin in the game.</li>
    <li>Caution any individual from talking too much.</li>
    <li>Promote standard, non-disruptive interruption method.</li>
    <li>Emphasize the need to stay focused on the time horizon in question.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>First complete all maps in sequence, then redo individual maps depending on your needs.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-2"></a>Part 2 - Mapping the Landscape</h1><h2><a name="ch-5"></a>Chapter 5 - Outcome Mapping</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Future state you want to be in within a set amount of time.
  <ul>
    <li>Typically, 6 months.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Desired outcome from the outset gives context and purpose to all the subsequent maps.</li>
  <li>Goal is to focus the team while surfacing doubts, testing assumptions, and enabling the emergence of new insights.</li>
  <li>5 stages:
  <ol>
    <li>Outcome discovery:
    <ul>
      <li>What is out target?</li>
      <li>Prompts: context, goals, pains, ideas, questions.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Defining the Target Outcome:
    <ul>
      <li>What goal do we want to achieve?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Defining Benefits:
    <ul>
      <li>Why does this outcome matter?</li>
      <li>3 different perspectives:
      <ul>
        <li>Value for customers.</li>
        <li>Value for the org.</li>
        <li>Value for individual contributors.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>If you struggle to define the benefits, either:
      <ul>
        <li>You should not be working on this.</li>
        <li>You haven&rsquo;t fully understood the broader context in which you are working.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Defining Obstacles:
    <ul>
      <li>What could get in the way?</li>
      <li>If there are no obstacle to achieving our desired goal, we would already be there.</li>
      <li>Explicit obstacles mean they can be dealt with consciously.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Defining Next Steps:
    <ul>
      <li>How are we going to proceed?</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Working backwards involves beginning with a clear definition of a desired target state (outcome) and using that target to guide decisions and actions.</li>
  <li>Flow Engineering mapping exercises are structured conversations with defined outputs.</li>
  <li>Who:
  <ul>
    <li>People involved in executing the workflow.</li>
    <li>People who have the situational awareness to accurately determine where changes can be made.</li>
    <li>Aim to involve the minimum number of people required to make decisions that will be trusted and accepted by the rest of the team.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Time allocation: 60 mins.</li>
  <li>Mechanics:
  <ol>
    <li>Outcome mapping:
    <ul>
      <li>One color per category.</li>
    </ul>
    <ol>
      <li>Brain dump: 5 mins.</li>
      <li>Review, identifying perspectives and presenting themes. 5 mins.</li>
      <li>Group notes into themes/topics. 3 mins.</li>
      <li>Vote on which theme to tackle.  <img src="/images/blog/books/flow-engineering/flow-engineering-outcome-discovery-map.png" alt="Outcome discovery map" /><br/></li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>Defining target outcome:
    <ul>
      <li>Craft a target outcome that captures the information from the sticky notes from outcome mapping and represents a valuable target.</li>
      <li>Maybe have a secondary outcome to counterbalance.</li>
      <li>SMART goals.</li>
      <li>Add to &ldquo;outcome&rdquo; column</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Define benefits, obstacles, next steps:
    <ul>
      <li>For each column:
      <ol>
        <li>Reflect silently to generate ideas. 1 min.</li>
        <li>In pairs, share ideas. 2 mins.</li>
        <li>Join 2 pais and consolidate their ideas. 4 mins.</li>
        <li>Whole group votes on highest priority ideas and moves them to the top. 2 mins. <img src="/images/blog/books/flow-engineering/flow-engineering-outcome-map.png" alt="Outcome map" /><br></li>
      </ol></li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-6"></a>Chapter 6 - Current State Value Stream Mapping</h2><p><img src="/images/blog/books/flow-engineering/flow-engineering-current-simplified-value-stream-map.png" alt="Current simplified value stream map" /></p>
<ul>
  <li>The stream already exists, and the flow is already present.</li>
  <li>Guiding principles to &ldquo;see&rdquo; value streams:
  <ul>
    <li>A value stream is just a pattern. Where this pattern appears, you can apply a consistent set of practices.</li>
    <li>Where there is a customer, there is a value stream.</li>
    <li>No stream is independent.</li>
    <li>Working backward is easier than forward.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Hiring, customer onboarding, support, roadmap definition and quarterly planning can be treated as a value stream.</li>
  <li>Don Reinertsen, in <a href="https://amzn.to/3VP4c9k">Principles of Product Development Flow</a>:
  <ul>
    <li>The value added by an activity is the difference in the price that an economically rational buyer would pay for a work product before, and after, the activity is performed.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>For Value Stream Mapping (VSM) to be effective, the team needs to be aligned on their objectives and aspirations.</li>
  <li>Time is the one thing we can&rsquo;t scale and the easiest thing for us to waste. It&rsquo;s also quite factual.</li>
  <li>From raw materials (which in sw dev is typically just an idea) to a finished product (working software).</li>
  <li>Value Stream Map in Flow Engineering is significantly simpler than the traditional one.</li>
  <li>VSM is widely espoused but not frequently practiced.</li>
  <li>Other than process time and wait time, other metrics are added in a just-in-time fashion as investigations indicate the need.</li>
  <li>Cocreating a Current State Value Stream Map reveals issues that allow teams to get at least 20% of their time back immediately.</li>
  <li>90 mins at a brisk pace. 2 hours if it is your first time.</li>
  <li>Up to 10 people.</li>
  <li>Steps:
  <ol>
    <li>Stream selection:
    <ul>
      <li>Recent.</li>
      <li>Real: something that has business impact.</li>
      <li>Reach: traverses the full value stream.</li>
      <li>Representative: typical piece of work.</li>
      <li>Road-tested: in production.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Add activities:
    <ul>
      <li>Work backwards.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Add timing:
    <ul>
      <li>Typical cycle time (process time) and delay time (wait time).</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Add dimensions and total metrics:
    <ul>
      <li>Lead time = total cycle time + total wait time.</li>
      <li>Add any extra dimensions that seem relevant to your target outcome.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Highlight constraint:
    <ul>
      <li>Target for future work and is the constraint used in Dependency Mapping.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Focus on what is happening most often. This involved repeatedly asking the team, &ldquo;How long does it usually take?&rdquo; and reminding them that &ldquo;it depends&rdquo; isn&rsquo;t an acceptable excuse for deliberation.</li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t try to thoroughly accommodate edge cases. If the flow seems to branch based on variations in process, capture it in a note but focus on what happens most often.</li>
  <li>Rough estimates are sufficient.</li>
  <li>If there&rsquo;s disagreement, take the worst-case time.</li>
  <li>If there is high variability, capture best and worse time.</li>
  <li>Focus the scope of the VSM on steps that are within this group&rsquo;s ability to influence.</li>
  <li>Other possible dimensions: Quality, efficiency, work in progress, queues, roles, tools, artifacts and deliverables.</li>
  <li>Tracking quality of work at each step typically requires intensive data-gathering and analysis. It can also be a bit of a sensitive topic.</li>
  <li>It is possible to parallelize the exercise by having each participant create their own representation of the VSM.</li>
  <li>It is possible to map asynchronously.</li>
  <li>If next steps seem unclear or blocked, you can use 15% solutions: &ldquo;What can you do without more resources or authority that would get you 15% of the way to a solution?&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>The analysis is focused on activities, not roles.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-7"></a>Chapter 7 - Dependency Mapping</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The rapid VSM done in Flow Engineering intentionally sacrifices precision for speed and ease:
  <ul>
    <li>Aim to gather just enough information to identify a critical constraint.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Dependency Mapping is specifically designed to improve the resolution on this critical constraint, so we can identify precise remedies.
  <ul>
    <li>Aim to gather just enough information to uncover viable opportunities for improvement.</li>
    <li>Challenge assumptions about where problems lie by digging deeper into likely hot spots.</li>
    <li>There is no need to analyze or understand every dependency.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Stages:
  <ol>
    <li>Start with constraints:
    <ul>
      <li>Copy the Value Stream Map but remove all data that does not related to the constraint.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Zoom in on a constraint by creating a sub-Value Stream Map:</li>
    <li>Identify hot spots.</li>
    <li>Identify direct causes for hot spots.</li>
    <li>Dig deeper into the constraint:
    <ul>
      <li>5 Whys.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Nothing is ever truly autonomous.</li>
  <li>Participants: those who have a deep understanding of the constrained step.</li>
  <li>Key questions:
  <ol>
    <li>What is the precise process through which step is enabled?</li>
    <li>What are typical timings of the sub-steps in that process?</li>
    <li>What other challenges are we are aware of in this process?</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Consider conflicting incentives.</li>
  <li>Share context with the Outcome Map and VSM.</li>
  <li>An SLA will consume the maximum time the SLA allows.</li>
  <li>Approach Dependency Mapping with curiosity, not accusation or demand.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>Seek first to understand, then to be understood <cite>Stephen Covey, The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
  <li>Consider dependency matrix.</li>
  <li>Wardley mapping can be useful to explore the strategic impact of interdependent capabilities.</li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SIPOC">SIPOC</a> diagrams.</li>
  <li>RACI matrix.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-8"></a>Chapter 8 - Future State Value Stream Mapping</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Ideal State Maps:
  <ul>
    <li>If we had all the necessary capabilities and resources and could remove all wait time between steps.</li>
    <li>Determined the upper limit of what is possible.</li>
    <li>Elicit creative ideas.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Future State Maps: how things will look like in 6 months.</li>
  <li>Reducing or eliminating wait time can often reduce lead time by 80% or more.</li>
  <li>PDSA cycle:
  <ul>
    <li>Plan: Future State Map.</li>
    <li>Do: Flow Roadmap.</li>
    <li>Study and Act: every 3 months, reassess current VSM.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Improvement Kata cycle:
  <ol>
    <li>Vision and challenge: Outcome Map.</li>
    <li>Gasp current condition: Current State Map and Dependency Map.</li>
    <li>Target condition: Future State Map.</li>
    <li>Experiments: Flow Roadmap.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Stages:
  <ol>
    <li>Review the target outcome and finding from previous maps:
    <ul>
      <li>Make copy of Current State Map.</li>
      <li>10 mins.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Identify targets for improvements:
    <ul>
      <li>Review DOWNTIME wastes.</li>
      <li>20 mins.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Redesign the stream:
    <ul>
      <li>Modify the parts of teh map that constitute the bottleneck.</li>
      <li>10 mins.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Measure the future state:
    <ul>
      <li>Estimate wait and cycle times.</li>
      <li>Focus on what can be achieved in the next 3 to 6 months.</li>
      <li>10 mins.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Optimizing delivery is a fine balancing act, and teams can benefit as much from limiting controls as they can from expanding controls.</li>
  <li>Work in progress is the silent killer of productivity.</li>
  <li>Eight wastes of Lean in knowledge work (DOWNTIME):
  <ol>
    <li>Defects.</li>
    <li>Overproduction: features no used, abandoned tasks, data duplication.</li>
    <li>Waiting: delays, slow hand offs, queuing, approvals, unnecessary/inefficient meetings.</li>
    <li>Non-utilized talent: missing capabilities, insufficient tooling, inadequate training, underutilized staff, bad incentives, lost morale.</li>
    <li>Transport: moving data between teams/systems/databases/tools, manual hand offs.</li>
    <li>Inventory: queues, backlogs, WIP, branches.</li>
    <li>Motion: unnecessary hand-offs, context switching data transfer/duplication.</li>
    <li>Extra processing: Unnecessary gates/approvals/reviews/validation, excess requirement details, gold-plating, excess UAT, polished docs when rough docs will suffice.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Reducing cognitive load can help reduce motion waste.</li>
  <li>Participants: original current VSM + key people from Dependency Mapping.</li>
  <li>Goal is to set a target. Details left for the Flow Roadmap.</li>
  <li>For your first Future State Map:
  <ul>
    <li>Aim for 3 improvements.</li>
    <li>Consider a shorter improvement horizon, such as 4-6 weeks.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Add more people or resources, preprocess work to simplify or increase team&rsquo;s awareness of the backlog.</li>
  <li>A common reason for a team being overloaded is excessive work in progress (WIP):
  <ul>
    <li>Say &ldquo;no&rdquo;.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-9"></a>Chapter 9 - The Flow Roadmap</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The Flow Roadmap is a plan for how to improve workflow.</li>
  <li>Plot actions, experiments, and mechanisms to improve the way you deliver.</li>
  <li>Stages:
  <ol>
    <li>Identify improvement opportunities:
    <ul>
      <li>List the target improvement areas identified during the Future State Map.</li>
      <li>For each, identify specific actions.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Prioritize each activity:
    <ul>
      <li>Plot on the vertical axis the importance and the feasibility on the horizontal axis.</li>
      <li>Indicate dependencies.  <img src="/images/blog/books/flow-engineering/flow-engineering-action-priorities.png" alt="Action priorities" /><br/></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Sequence activities into a roadmap:
    <ul>
      <li>Pick the most important and feasible.</li>
      <li>Identify a measure of progress for the &ldquo;now&rdquo; actions.</li>
      <li>Assign owners to the actions.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>You may miss something going too fast, and you may waste time going too deep.</li>
  <li>Participants: Those likely to be involved in the next steps.</li>
  <li>Key questions:
  <ol>
    <li>What are the highest-priority actions to deliver out target outcome?</li>
    <li>How will we measure progress?</li>
    <li>Who will own the progress?</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>In the upper left, include a copy of the Future State Map.</li>
  <li>Less feasible:
  <ol>
    <li>Multiple contributors.</li>
    <li>Lack of a capability.</li>
    <li>With dependencies on other teams.</li>
    <li>Unknown scopes.</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-3"></a>Part 3 - Navigating the Landscape</h1><h2><a name="ch-10"></a>Chapter 10 - Principles of Flow Engineering</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Effective action depends on the ability of each individual to identify value, build clarity, and enable flow.</li>
  <li>Two different ways of seeing an org:
  <ol>
    <li>Prescriptive approach:
    <ul>
      <li>An org can be designed and engineered like a machine.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Generative approach:
    <ul>
      <li>An org is composed of living workers whose behavior necessarily emerges from their own values and understanding.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol>
  <ul>
    <li>Both approaches needed as orgs have a dual nature.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Principles:
  <ul>
    <li>Specify value:
    <ul>
      <li>Value is subjective and transitory because it is a measure of how positively we feel about something, and whether it addresses a need.</li>
      <li>Delivering value is an act of cooperation, not a zero-sum game.</li>
      <li>We can only measure value by getting feedback from those experiencing it.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Map the value stream:
    <ul>
      <li>Western rationalism has habituated most of us to very linear ways of thinking.</li>
      <li>Visibility enables observability; observability enables clarity.</li>
      <li>Effort invested in gaining clarity allows us to avoid waste and risk.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Create flow:
    <ul>
      <li>Flow implies a quality of steadiness in motion.</li>
      <li>Optimizing for flow is contradictory to optimizing for resource utilization.</li>
      <li>To maximize value, we must focus on flow efficiency (cycle time / lead time).</li>
      <li>In sw dev, there is significant variation in how long work takes, so you need slack capacity to accommodate this variation.</li>
      <li>Theory of Constraints: flow is always limited by one and only one constraint at any given time.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Pull don&rsquo;t push:
    <ul>
      <li>Steve Spear in <a href="https://amzn.to/44zserv">The High-Velocity Edge</a>. The ideal:
      <ol>
        <li>Defect-free.</li>
        <li>On demand.</li>
        <li>One piece at a time.</li>
        <li>Immediate.</li>
        <li>Without waste.</li>
        <li>Safe.</li>
        <li>Secure.</li>
      </ol></li>
      <li>Pull creates a direct connection between what is needed and what is delivered.</li>
      <li>Creating a pull-based system of work is an extraordinary feat.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Pursue perfection:
    <ul>
      <li>Learning is central to removing waste.</li>
      <li>Implicit in enabling learning is a sense of psychological safety.</li>
      <li>Learning implies letting go of our current models.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-11"></a>Chapter 11 - Leading Flow Engineering</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Effective principles requires:
  <ul>
    <li>Consistent practice, which requires</li>
    <li>Discipline and mindfulness, which requires</li>
    <li>Strong and sustained effort, which requires</li>
    <li>Confidence, which requires</li>
    <li>Inspiration and vision.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>To safely deliver change, you must control risk, for which you need the ability to respond quickly and effectively when problems emerge.</li>
  <li><p>Feedback loops must also evolve as target outcome evolve.</p>
  <blockquote>Strategy is a commodity, execution is an art <cite>Peter Drucker</cite>
  </blockquote></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-12"></a>Chapter 12 - Traps to Avoid</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Top five:
  <ol>
    <li>Neglecting the narrative.</li>
    <li>Misaligned and conflicting incentives.</li>
    <li>Not mapping the complete stream.</li>
    <li>Craving unnecessary precision.</li>
    <li>Conflict with existing operating models.</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-14"></a>Chapter 13 - Value Stream Management</h2>
<ul>
  <li>A new strategic and operational approach to the data capture, analysis, planning and implementation of effective change within the core cross-functional or cross-company processes required to achieve a truly lean enterprise.</li>
  <li>Two primary activities:
  <ol>
    <li>Optimizing the flow of work that delivers customer value.</li>
    <li>Measuring those delivered outcomes to make better decisions.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>The transition from project to product is a story of flow.</li>
  <li>Streetlight effect: we tend to look for things where it&rsquo;s easy to look.</li>
  <li>If you are not getting better, you are getting worse.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-14"></a>Chapter 14 - Scaling Flow Engineering</h2>
<ul>
  <li>To have a large-scale impact, you must achieve this across an entire organization:
  <ul>
    <li>That&rsquo;s neither feasible nor affordable one stream at a time.</li>
    <li>It is often simple to see that dependencies are common, and by addressing them for one stream, you can address them across the entire organization.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Rapid methods to reach out beyond a single stream:
  <ul>
    <li>Sharing maps.</li>
    <li>Surveying.</li>
    <li>Communities of Practice.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a name="types"></a>Developmental vs Operational value streams:
  <ul>
    <li>Developmental: focus on delivering something new each time.</li>
    <li>Operational: focus on delivering a consistent product.</li>
    <li>Don&rsquo;t choose one or the other, but one over the other.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul>
<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th> </th>
      <th>Developmental </th>
      <th>Operational </th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Focused on </td>
      <td>Effectiveness </td>
      <td>Efficiency </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Design </td>
      <td>Execution </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Innovation </td>
      <td>Stability </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Novelty </td>
      <td>Maintenance </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Value creation </td>
      <td>Value maximization </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Characterized by </td>
      <td>Variation </td>
      <td>Consistency </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Uncertainty </td>
      <td>Certainty </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Investigation </td>
      <td>Measurement </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Experimentation </td>
      <td>Optimization </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Function of constraints </td>
      <td>Enablement </td>
      <td>Governance </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<ul>
  <li>Core vs Supportive value streams:
  <ul>
    <li>Core:
    <ul>
      <li>Directly contributes to revenue or value creation for the business.</li>
      <li>Contribute directly to external customer value.</li>
      <li>Are <em>why</em> you are in business.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Supportive:
    <ul>
      <li>Provide services and capabilities to core streams.</li>
      <li>Are <em>how</em> you stay in business.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="https://observablehq.com/@troymagennis/impact-of-multiple-team-dependencies-in-software-developm">Troy Magennis</a>: Every dependency you can remove DOUBLES your chances of successful on-time delivery.</li>
  <li>Started with Flow Engineering by conducting a conversational Outcome Map.</li>
  <li>Fit mapping into existing time boxes like retrospectives or off-site meetings.</li>
</ul>]]></description></item><item><title>Book notes: Continuous Discovery Habits</title><link>https://danlebrero.com/2024/02/28/continuous-discovery-habits-summary/</link><guid>https://danlebrero.com/2024/02/28/continuous-discovery-habits-summary/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><description><![CDATA[<p>These are my notes on <a href="https://amzn.to/48Ihqbv">Continuous Discovery Habits</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/ttorres">Teresa Torres</a>.</p><p>Very practical advise and tool for Product Managers. To quote Teresa:</p>
<blockquote><p>Approach to give you confidence to act while preparing you to be wrong.</p>
</blockquote><p>Interestingly, a lot of the advice it very applicable to software architecture:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Best path to desired outcome is the &ldquo;ill-structured problem&rdquo;:
  <ul>
    <li>There is no right or wrong, only better or worse.</li>
    <li>Most of the work is framing the problem itself:
    <ul>
      <li>Framing impacts how we solve it.</li>
      <li>Good problem-solvers try many framings.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1>Key Insights</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Product trio:
  <ul>
    <li>Product Manager + Designer + SW eng.</li>
    <li>Product trios should interview together.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>At minimum, weekly touch points with customers by the team building the product where they conduct small research activities in pursuit of a desired outcome.
  <ul>
    <li>Continuous interviewing is the keystone habit for continuous discovery.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Opportunity Solution Tree (OST):<br/>  <img src="/images/blog/books/continuous-discovery-habits/ost.jpg" alt="OST" /></li>
  <li>Avoid &ldquo;whether or not&rdquo; decisions, but a &ldquo;compare and contrast&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>Best designers evolve the problem and solution space together.</li>
  <li>When an idea does not work, take the time to reflect on what you learned.</li>
  <li>Josh Seiden, <a href="https://amzn.to/493cjm7">Outcomes Over Outputs</a>:
  <ul>
    <li>An outcome is a change in human behavior that drives business results.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Primary research question:
  <ul>
    <li>What opportunity matter most to this customer?</li>
    <li>Best is to ask them to share specific stories about their experience:
    <ul>
      <li>Dig into the details.</li>
      <li>Don&rsquo;t allow them to generalize.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>An opportunity should have more than one potential solution, otherwise it is simply a solution in disguise.</li>
  <li>Do not score opportunities:
  <ul>
    <li>Make a data-informed, subjective comparison.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Choosing an opportunity is an easily reversible decision, so:
  <ul>
    <li>Avoid analysis-paralysis:
    <ul>
      <li>We will learn more by acting.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>You are just committing to explore it further.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Research shows:
  <ul>
    <li>More idea == more diverse and novel.</li>
    <li>Most original ideas tend to be generated toward the end of the ideation session.</li>
    <li>Individuals outperformed brainstorming groups.</li>
    <li>We are better at evaluating ideas as a group.</li>
    <li>Best:
    <ol>
      <li>Generate ideas individually.</li>
      <li>Share.</li>
      <li>Go to 1.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Fast discovery iterations only possible if instead of testing ideas, test the assumptions that need to be true in order for the ideas to succeed.
  <ul>
    <li>Do not test one idea at a time, but assumptions from all ideas at the same time.</li>
    <li>Assumption tests should simulate an experience, so that the participant behaves, not only says that they will do or not.</li>
    <li>Define evaluation criteria upfront.</li>
    <li>You are not trying to prove that an assumption is true, but to reduce the risk.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1>TOC</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#ch-0">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#p-1">Part I - What is Continuous Delivery?</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-1">Chapter 1 - The What and Why of Continuous Delivery</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-2">Chapter 2 - A Common Framework for Continuous Delivery</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-2">Part II - Continuous Discovery Habits</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-3">Chapter 3 - Focusing on Outcomes over Outputs</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-4">Chapter 4 - Visualizing What You Know</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-5">Chapter 5 - Continuous Interviewing</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-6">Chapter 6 - Mapping the Opportunity Space</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-7">Chapter 7 - Prioritizing Opportunities, Not Solutions</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-8">Chapter 8 - Supercharged Ideation</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-9">Chapter 9 - Identifying Hidden Assumptions</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-10">Chapter 10 - Testing Assumptions, Not Ideas</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-11">Chapter 11 - Measure Impact</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-12">Chapter 12 - Managing The Cycles</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-13">Chapter 13 - Slow You Work</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-3">Part III - Developing You Continuous Discovery Habits</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-14">Chapter 14 - Start Small, and Iterate</a></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-0"></a>Introduction</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Focus on customers was a better strategy than obsessing about our competitors.</li>
  <li>Naively thought business would be human centered.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-1"></a>Part I - What is Continuous Delivery?</h1><h2><a name="ch-1"></a>Chapter 1 - The What and Why of Continuous Delivery</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Questions:
  <ul>
    <li>Does the customer want it?</li>
    <li>Are you improving over time?</li>
    <li>Are you creating value for the customer and your business?</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Approach to give you confidence to act while preparing you to be wrong.</li>
  <li>Product trio:
  <ul>
    <li>Product Manager + Designer + SW eng.</li>
    <li>Other roles are welcomed but beware of the cost.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Mindset:
  <ol>
    <li>Outcome-oriented.</li>
    <li>Customer-centric.</li>
    <li>Collaborative.</li>
    <li>Visual:
    <ul>
      <li>Humans have an immense capacity for spatial reasoning.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Experimental.</li>
    <li>Continuous.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>At minimum, weekly touch points with customers by the team building the product where they conduct small research activities in pursuit of a desired outcome.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-2"></a>Chapter 2 - A Common Framework for Continuous Delivery</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The focus on outcomes at the cost of the customer is not uncommon.</li>
  <li>Best path to desired outcome is the &ldquo;ill-structured problem&rdquo;:
  <ul>
    <li>There is no right or wrong, only better or worse.</li>
    <li>Most of the work is framing the problem itself:
    <ul>
      <li>Framing impacts how we solve it.</li>
      <li>Good problem-solvers try many framings.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Pursue business value by creating customer value.</li>
  <li>Opportunity: customer needs, pain points or desires.</li>
  <li>Opportunity Solution Tree (OST):<br/> <img src="/images/blog/books/continuous-discovery-habits/ost.jpg" alt="OST" />
  <ul>
    <li>Shared understanding.</li>
    <li>Split big opportunities into smaller and smaller ones.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Chip and Dan Heath, <a href="https://amzn.to/3Hx7x4I">Decisive Book</a>:
  <ul>
    <li>4 villains of decision-making:
    <ol>
      <li>Looking too narrowly at a problem.</li>
      <li>Confirmation bias.</li>
      <li>Letting short-term emotions affect decisions.</li>
      <li>Overconfidence.</li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>First book to read after this one.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Avoid &ldquo;whether or not&rdquo; decisions, but a &ldquo;compare and contrast&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>Best designers evolve the problem and solution space together.</li>
  <li>When an idea does not work, take the time to reflect on what you learned.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-2"></a>Part II - Continuous Discovery Habits</h1><h2><a name="ch-3"></a>Chapter 3 - Focusing on Outcomes over Outputs</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Josh Seiden, <a href="https://amzn.to/493cjm7">Outcomes Over Outputs</a>:
  <ul>
    <li>An outcome is a change in human behavior that drives business results.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Product teams have to do discovery work to identify the connection between product outcomes (metrics they can influence) and business outcomes (metrics that drive the business).</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/47M7Pzm">Measure What Matters</a> valid criticisms from <a href="https://felipecastro.com/en/blog/book-review-measure-what-matters/">Felipe Castro</a>.</li>
  <li>Outcomes communicate uncertainty.</li>
  <li>Multiple teams with the same business outcome make it easy to blame other teams for the lack of progress.</li>
  <li>Traction metrics (usage of a particular feature) do not give product teams any latitude:
  <ul>
    <li>They are outputs.</li>
    <li>Avoid them except:
    <ol>
      <li>Junior product teams.</li>
      <li>When optimizing a solution instead of finding a new solution.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Outcome negotiated between product leader and product trio.</li>
  <li>Stable product trio focused on the same outcome is critical, so that they do not need to learn again how to move the metric:
  <ul>
    <li>Start with a learning goal, then move to a SMART goal.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-4"></a>Chapter 4 - Visualizing What You Know</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Steps:
  <ol>
    <li>Agree on scope, focusing on desired outcome.</li>
    <li>Individually create an experience map.</li>
    <li>Study each other&rsquo;s map.</li>
    <li>Co-create a map:
    <ul>
      <li>Include all individual nodes of all maps.</li>
      <li>Collapse similar nodes.</li>
      <li>Map more than the happy path.</li>
      <li>Add context (visually if possible)</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Experience maps are visual.</li>
  <li>Drawing is more specific than writing. Language is vague.
  <ul>
    <li>I strongly disagree.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Maps:
  <ul>
    <li>Nodes: moment in time, action or event.</li>
    <li>Links.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Refine the map as you learn.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-5"></a>Chapter 5 - Continuous Interviewing</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Interviewing is not to ask your customers what you should build:
  <ul>
    <li>It is to discover and explore opportunities.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Direct (factual) questions require recalling facts without context:
  <ul>
    <li>Prone to cognitive biases.</li>
    <li>Answers not accurate.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Confidence isn&rsquo;t a good indicator of truth or reality.</li>
  <li>When information is missing, our brains simply fill in details to make the story coherent.</li>
  <li>Primary research question:
  <ul>
    <li>What opportunity matter most to this customer?</li>
    <li>Best is to ask them to share specific stories about their experience:
    <ul>
      <li>Dig into the details.</li>
      <li>Don&rsquo;t allow them to generalize.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Use the experience map as a guide.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Research question: what you are trying to learn.</li>
  <li>Interview question: what you ask in your interview.</li>
  <li>Synthesize using an interview snapshot:
  <ul>
    <li>Quick facts: help identify type of customer.</li>
    <li>Opportunities: use customer&rsquo;s words.</li>
    <li>Top right, experience map for this customer.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><p><img src="/images/blog/books/continuous-discovery-habits/interview-snapshot.png" alt="Interview snapshot" /></p>
<ul>
  <li>Interview at least one customer every week.</li>
  <li>Source of candidates:
  <ul>
    <li>While users are using your product.</li>
    <li>Ads.</li>
    <li>Support.</li>
    <li>Marketing.</li>
    <li>Customer Advisory Board.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Product trios should interview together.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-6"></a>Chapter 6 - Mapping the Opportunity Space</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Our job is to address customer opportunities that drive our desired outcome.</li>
  <li>Branches in the OST must not have overlaps.</li>
  <li>Look for key moments (or nodes) in:
  <ol>
    <li>Experience Map.</li>
    <li>From patterns in interview experience maps.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Avoid:
  <ul>
    <li>Opportunities framed from your company&rsquo;s perspective.</li>
    <li>Vertical opportunities (trees with no branches).</li>
    <li>Opportunities with two parents.</li>
    <li>Capturing feelings as opportunities.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>An opportunity should have more than one potential solution, otherwise it is simply a solution in disguise.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-7"></a>Chapter 7 - Prioritizing Opportunities, Not Solutions</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Compare top level opportunities in the tree, and recursively do the same with the children of the chosen one.</li>
  <li>Comparison criteria:
  <ol>
    <li>Size: how many customers and how often?</li>
    <li>Market: how if affects our position in the market:
    <ul>
      <li>Differentiators vs table stakes.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Company:
    <ul>
      <li>Does it support company/business unit/team vision/mission/strategy?</li>
      <li>Available skills in the team.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Customer:
    <ul>
      <li>How important it is.</li>
      <li>How satisfied customers are with the current solution?</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Do not score opportunities:
  <ul>
    <li>Make a data-informed, subjective comparison.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Choosing an opportunity is an easily reversible decision, so:
  <ul>
    <li>Avoid analysis-paralysis:
    <ul>
      <li>We will learn more by acting.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>You are just committing to explore it further.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-8"></a>Chapter 8 - Supercharged Ideation</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Research shows:
  <ul>
    <li>More idea == more diverse and novel.</li>
    <li>Most original ideas tend to be generated toward the end of the ideation session.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Brainstorming rules:
  <ol>
    <li>Focus on quantity.</li>
    <li>Defer judgement.</li>
    <li>Combine and improve ideas.</li>
    <li>Welcome unusual ideas.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Research shows that individuals outperformed brainstorming groups due to:
  <ol>
    <li>Social loafing:
    <ul>
      <li>People tend to work harder on their own.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Group conformity:
    <ul>
      <li>People censored themselves due to concerns about how others would judge their ideas.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Production blocking:
    <ul>
      <li>You are about to say an idea, somebody else jumps in, and you forget your idea.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Downward not setting:
    <ul>
      <li>Performance of a group tends to be limited to the lowest-performing member.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Brainstorming groups are subject to &ldquo;illusion of group productivity&rdquo;:
  <ul>
    <li>Groups overestimate their performance, because &ldquo;cognitive failures&rdquo; (getting stuck) happens less often than to individuals.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Best:
  <ol>
    <li>Generate ideas individually.</li>
    <li>Share.</li>
    <li>Go to 1.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Tips for ideation:
  <ul>
    <li>Take frequent breaks.</li>
    <li>Walk.</li>
    <li>Change scenery.</li>
    <li>Try different times of the day.</li>
    <li>Sleep over it.</li>
    <li>Look at competitors or other industries for analogous problems.</li>
    <li>Pretend to have a magic want.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Research shows that we are better at evaluating ideas as a group.</li>
  <li>Dot-vote ideas as a group:
  <ul>
    <li>First, remove ideas that do not address the opportunity.</li>
    <li>Only criteria is how well the idea addresses the target opportunity.</li>
    <li>Until you have set aside <em>3 ideas</em>.</li>
    <li>Each idea should have a strong advocate.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Include the whole team in ideation:
  <ul>
    <li>Consider also including key stakeholders.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-9"></a>Chapter 9 - Identifying Hidden Assumptions</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Fast discovery iterations only possible if instead of testing ideas, test the assumptions that need to be true in order for the ideas to succeed.</li>
  <li>Use story mapping to align/understand ideas:
  <ul>
    <li>Be specific.</li>
    <li>Story map what would be the best solution based on what we know right now.</li>
    <li>List assumptions in each step.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Assumptions == risks (desirability, feasibility, usability) + ethical viability.</li>
  <li>Use pre-mortems:
  <ul>
    <li>Imagine it is 6 months into the future and the product/initiative launched, and it was a complete failure. What went wrong?</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Walk up the OST and be very specific about why the solution will address the opportunity and the opportunity the outcome.</li>
  <li>Prioritizing assumptions:
  <ul>
    <li>Place them relative to each other.</li>
    <li>Pick the 2-3 top right most.</li>
    <li>More important == less likely to have a workaround.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><p><img src="/images/blog/books/continuous-discovery-habits/opportunity-prioritization.png" alt="Prioritizing assumptions" /></p>
<ul>
  <li>Expect to generate ~20 assumptions per idea.</li>
  <li>Phrase your assumptions so that they need to be true:
  <ul>
    <li>NO: customer will not remember their password.</li>
    <li>YES: customers will remember their password.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-10"></a>Chapter 10 - Testing Assumptions, Not Ideas</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Do not test one idea at a time, but assumptions from all three ideas at the same time:
  <ul>
    <li>Avoid confirmation bias and escalation of commitment.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Assumption tests should simulate an experience, so that the participant behaves, not only says that they will do or not.</li>
  <li>It is common for ideas to share assumptions:
  <ul>
    <li>Can rule out multiple ideas at once.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Define evaluation criteria upfront:
  <ul>
    <li>Be explicit:
    <ul>
      <li>How many people we&rsquo;ll test.</li>
      <li>How many people need to exhibit the behaviour.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>You are not trying to prove that an assumption is true, but to reduce the risk:
  <ul>
    <li>Start small and iterate to bigger, more reliable tests.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>In the majority of cases, you will learn plenty from small-scale tests.</li>
  <li>Tools:
  <ol>
    <li>Unmoderated user testing:
    <ul>
      <li>Produce a video test you can watch later.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>One-question surveys.</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-11"></a>Chapter 11 - Measure Impact</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Measure not only what you need to evaluate our assumption tests, but also what we need to measure impact on our outcome.</li>
  <li>Start small and experiment your way to the best instrumentation.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-12"></a>Chapter 12 - Managing The Cycles</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Most of the work in discovery is not following the process; it is managing the cycles.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-13"></a>Chapter 13 - Slow You Work</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Share with stakeholders your whole journey, so they can make their own conclusions and help co-create.</li>
  <li>Use your discovery framework to help stakeholders see where their idea does (or does not) fit.</li>
  <li>You aren&rsquo;t going to win the ideological war in one conversation (or never).</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-3"></a>Part III - Developing You Continuous Discovery Habits</h1><h2><a name="ch-14"></a>Chapter 14 - Start Small, and Iterate</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Continuous interviewing is the keystone habit for continuous discovery.</li>
  <li>The best time to advocate for discovery is when a feature falls short of expectations.</li>
  <li>Consider what you can do in the unique company&rsquo;s context and let go of the &ldquo;That would never work here&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>]]></description></item><item><title>Book notes: The Staff Engineer's Path: A Guide for Individual Contributors Navigating Growth and Change</title><link>https://danlebrero.com/2024/01/24/the-staff-engineers-path-summary/</link><guid>https://danlebrero.com/2024/01/24/the-staff-engineers-path-summary/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><description><![CDATA[<p>These are my notes on <a href="https://amzn.to/3thSc4p">The Staff Engineer&rsquo;s Path: A Guide for Individual Contributors Navigating Growth and Change</a> by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tanyareilly">Tanya Reilly</a>.</p><p>Must-read for anybody interested on growing in the individual contributor track.</p>
<blockquote><p>Be the engineer that everyone wants to work with. <cite>Tanya Reilly, this book</cite></p>
</blockquote><h1>Key Insights</h1><p><img src="/images/blog/books/staff-engineers-path/pillars.png" alt="Staff engineer pillars" /></p>
<ul>
  <li>Staff eng roles come in a lot of shapes, but not all orgs will need all kinds of staff engs.</li>
  <li>Senior is a &ldquo;tenure&rdquo; level: you don&rsquo;t need to go further.</li>
  <li>Whenever there is a feeling of &ldquo;someone should do something here&rdquo;, there is a reasonable change that the someone is you.</li>
  <li>Autonomous: Find your own problems to work on.</li>
  <li>Know why the problem you are working on is strategically important, and it is not, do something else.</li>
  <li>Not necessary to provide solution but to ensure there is agreed-upon, well-understood solution that solves the problem.</li>
  <li>Feedback loops will be months.</li>
  <li>Write down a &ldquo;what do I do here?&rdquo; doc to ensure expectations/focus in shared with manager and peers.</li>
  <li>Vision/Strategy is not always needed:
  <ul>
    <li>It is a big project.</li>
    <li>Getting the people to agree <strong>is</strong> the work.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>None of the options can make everybody happy:
  <ul>
    <li>Rather than asking &ldquo;Is everyone ok with option A?&rdquo; ask &ldquo;Can anyone not live with option A?&rdquo;</li>
    <li>Not deciding is a decision, usually not a good one.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>You have to make peace with walking past things that are broken or suboptimal.</li>
  <li>Do what is important for the company, but also what is important for you.</li>
  <li>Notice when you are doing busy work because you are tired, and find a way to rest instead.</li>
  <li>Put non meetings in the calendar too:
  <ul>
    <li>Not &ldquo;make time&rdquo; but specific items.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>The usual reason why a project is difficult is that you are dealing with ambiguity.</li>
  <li>Number one tool for project success: writing things down.</li>
  <li>As a project lead, you will fill any roles that you don&rsquo;t have someone in them.</li>
  <li>Recruit people that are optimistic, good at conflict resolution and comms.</li>
  <li>Better wrong than vague: chance to change direction early.</li>
  <li>If it seems trivial, it is because you do not understand it.</li>
  <li>Writing code is rarely the highest leverage thing you can spend time on.
  <ul>
    <li>Coding gives you a depth of understanding that is hard to gain otherwise.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Something will always go wrong:
  <ul>
    <li>Take it as an opportunity to learn.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Techniques to get unstuck:
  <ol>
    <li>Understand and explain.</li>
    <li>Make the work easier.</li>
    <li>Get org support.</li>
    <li>Make alternative plans.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Supporting an untrained person through making a change in a difficult codebase takes more effort than doing it yourself.</li>
  <li>Three bullet points and a call to action:
  <ul>
    <li>Three bullet points detailing the issue at hand.</li>
    <li>One and only one call to action.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Blocked by:
  <ul>
    <li>A decision: make a guess and document it with an ADR.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>No talk about implementation until all agree about the problem.</li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t just tell people that the solution exists: you need to keep telling them.</li>
  <li>If the project is not in good shape by the end of it, it will never be.</li>
  <li>People assume that you know what you are talking about, so be careful with what you say.</li>
  <li>Values is what you do.</li>
  <li>The degree to which other people want to work with you is a direct indication of how successful you&rsquo;ll be in your career as an engineer.</li>
  <li>Do not accept a management role until you are a solid senior engineer.</li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/@ElizAyer/dont-ask-forgiveness-radiate-intent-d36fd22393a3">Radiating intent</a> (instead of seeking permission or asking for forgiveness).</li>
  <li>Attributes of a staff engineer:
  <ol>
    <li>Competent.</li>
    <li>Responsible.</li>
    <li>Remembers the goal:
    <ul>
      <li>SW is a means to a goal, not a goal itself.</li>
      <li>There is always a budget.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Look Ahead.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t jump to give advice, sometimes the mentee just need to vent or get empathy on the situation.</li>
  <li>If you cannot think on what to improve, ask yourself why they aren&rsquo;t one level more senior.</li>
  <li>You cannot be an expert in everything.</li>
  <li>Every job should help you grow towards your long-term goals and meet your immediate needs.</li>
  <li>Keep a weekly record of your job signals.</li>
  <li>Staying in one place for long gives you the feedback loop that comes from seeing the consequences of your actions.</li>
</ul><h1>TOC</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#ch-0">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#p-1">Part I - The Big Picture</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-1">Chapter 1 - What would you say you do here?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-2">Chapter 2 - Three Maps</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-3">Chapter 3 - Creating the Big Picture</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-2">Part II - Execution</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-4">Chapter 4 - Finite Time</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-5">Chapter 5 - Leading Big Projects</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-6">Chapter 6 - Why Have We Stopped?</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-3">Part III - Leveling Up</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-7">Chapter 7 - You&rsquo;re a Role Model Now (Sorry)</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-8">Chapter 8 - Good Influence at Scale</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-9">Chapter 9 - What&rsquo;s Next?</a></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-0"></a>Introduction</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Both paths need many of the same skills.</li>
  <li>Pillars:
  <ol>
    <li>Big-picture thinking.</li>
    <li>Execution.</li>
    <li>Leveling up others.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>When acting as a role model, you need to be right.</li>
</ul><p><img src="/images/blog/books/staff-engineers-path/pillars.png" alt="Staff engineer pillars" /></p><h1><a name="p-1"></a>Part I - The Big Picture</h1><h2><a name="ch-1"></a>Chapter 1 - What would you say you do here?</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Staff eng roles come in a lot of shapes, but not all orgs will need all kinds of staff engs.</li>
  <li>Senior is a &ldquo;tenure&rdquo; level: you don&rsquo;t need to go further.</li>
  <li>Big picture:
  <ul>
    <li>Good decisions need context:
    <ul>
      <li>Gathering context requires time and effort.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Managers, as the people responsible for assigning headcount to technical initiatives, need to be part of major tech decisions.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Project management:
  <ul>
    <li>Unstuck.</li>
    <li>Tech quality.</li>
    <li>High level system design.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Whenever there is a feeling of &ldquo;someone should do something here&rdquo;, there is a reasonable change that the someone is you.</li>
  <li><a href="https://kind.engineering/">https://kind.engineering/</a>.</li>
  <li>Programming will often not be the best use of your time:
  <ul>
    <li>Enough work to make problems manageable by someone else:
    <ul>
      <li>Growth opportunity for less experience devs.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Autonomous: Find your own problems to work on.</li>
  <li>Not necessary to provide solution but to ensure there is agreed-upon, well-understood solution that solves the problem.</li>
  <li>Who you report to influences:
  <ol>
    <li>Support you receive.</li>
    <li>Information you can access.</li>
    <li>How you are perceived.</li>
    <li>Scope: domain, teams:
    <ul>
      <li>Too broad:
      <ul>
        <li>Lack of impact: distracted with side-quests.</li>
        <li>Become a bottleneck: take part on every decision.</li>
        <li>Decision fatigue.</li>
        <li>Missing relationships: not enough regular contact.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Too narrow:
      <ul>
        <li>Lack of impact.</li>
        <li>Opportunity cost: working on less important stuff.</li>
        <li>Overshadowing other engineers: no room for other engs to solve problems.</li>
        <li>Over-engineering: too much time on your hands.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Ensure your scope is aligned to your preference of broad vs deep work.</li>
  <li>4 disciplines in any job:
  <ul>
    <li>Core tech skills.</li>
    <li>Product management.</li>
    <li>Project management.</li>
    <li>People management.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Consider how much you want to code.</li>
  <li>Feedback loops will be months.</li>
  <li>Know why the problem you are working on is strategically important, and it is not, do something else.</li>
  <li><a href="/2022/02/23/staff-engineering-leadership-beyond-the-management-track-book-summary/#ch-1">4 staff eng archetypes</a>.</li>
  <li>Write down a &ldquo;what do I do here?&rdquo; doc to ensure expectations/focus in shared with manager and peers:
  <ul>
    <li>Overview.</li>
    <li>Goals.</li>
    <li>Sample activities.</li>
    <li>What success looks like?</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-2"></a>Chapter 2 - Three Maps</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Locator map:
  <ul>
    <li>Where are you in the org, and what is outside your bubble.</li>
    <li>Put your work in a bigger context.</li>
    <li>To make good decisions, you&rsquo;ll need to be able to see from others point of view.</li>
    <li>Risk of focusing only on your context:
    <ol>
      <li>Prioritizing badly:
      <ul>
        <li>Your problems seem more important and special.</li>
        <li>It is unusual to find a problem that is genuinely brand now.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Losing empathy:
      <ul>
        <li>Think other domains are simpler.</li>
        <li>Overestimate what others know from your domain.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Tuning out the background noise:
      <ul>
        <li>Stop noticing some problems because you get so used to them.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Forgetting what they work is for:
      <ul>
        <li>Lose connection with the company&rsquo;s goals.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Topological map:
  <ul>
    <li>Discover existing &ldquo;dangers&rdquo; and paths:
    <ul>
      <li>How leaders prefer to work.</li>
      <li>How decisions are made.</li>
      <li>&ldquo;Shadow org&rdquo; charts.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Issues without one:
    <ol>
      <li>Your good ideas don&rsquo;t get traction.</li>
      <li>You don&rsquo;t find the difficult parts until you get there.</li>
      <li>Everything takes longer.</li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>Understand your org:
    <ul>
      <li>Culture:
      <ul>
        <li>Open or secret?
        <ul>
          <li>Open information can lead to more drama.</li>
        </ul></li>
        <li>Oral or written?</li>
        <li>Top-down or bottom-up?</li>
        <li>Fast change or deliberate change?
        <ul>
          <li>Tightly connected to oral/written.</li>
        </ul></li>
        <li>Back channels or front doors?</li>
        <li>Allocated or available?
        <ul>
          <li>If there are plenty of available people, changes are that a competing novel grassroots initiatives are about to start.</li>
        </ul></li>
        <li>Liquid (meritocracy of sorts) or crystallized (structured hierarchy and promotion)?</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Points of interests:
    <ol>
      <li>Chasms between teams/orgs:
      <ul>
        <li>Difficult to communicate, make decisions and resolve disputes.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Fortresses:
      <ul>
        <li>Well-intended gatekeepers, but stop projects/change from happening.</li>
        <li>Avoid a battle, even if you might win.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Disputed territory:
      <ul>
        <li>When two or more teams need to work closely together, their projects can fall into chaos if they don&rsquo;t have the same clear view of where they are trying to get to.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Uncrossable desserts:
      <ul>
        <li>Unwinnable battles.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Paved roads, shortcuts and busy ways around.</li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>You need to be technically correct and convince the right people.</li>
    <li>Figure out where decisions are happening:
    <ul>
      <li>You can influence higher up decisions by making sure relevant information reaches via your reporting chain.</li>
      <li>Ask to join but show how it will make the org more likely to achieve its goals.</li>
      <li>Figure out shadow org chart:
      <ul>
        <li>Connectors: people that know everybody.</li>
        <li>Old-timers.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Be a bridge.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Treasure map:
  <ul>
    <li>Where and why.</li>
    <li>Destination and stop points.</li>
    <li>Long term view.</li>
    <li>If only short term vision:
    <ol>
      <li>Harder to keep everybody going in the same direction.</li>
      <li>Not finish big things.</li>
      <li>Accumulate cruft.</li>
      <li>Competing initiatives.</li>
      <li>Engineers stop growing:
      <ul>
        <li>Small project problems != big project ones.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>If the map is not clear, create a new one.</li>
    <li>Trail map:
    <ul>
      <li>Tell the story of the work.</li>
      <li>Every small task become part of a bigger story.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
</ol>
<ul>
  <li>You learn some parts of the map through everyday learning, but you need to be deliberate for others.</li>
  <li>Hiking example: easy to find out what you miss by looking at others:
  <ul>
    <li>They had learned to pay attention adn they know what they were looking for.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Habit of paying attention:
  <ul>
    <li>Take notes.</li>
    <li>What? Anything that helps you or others:
    <ul>
      <li>Have context.</li>
      <li>Navigate your org.</li>
      <li>Progress towards your goals.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Techniques for seeing the bigger picture:
  <ol>
    <li>Taking an outsider view:
    <ul>
      <li>A new person to the team/org can always see the problems.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Befriend other staff eng to understand from their point of view what your team/group looks like.</li>
    <li>Befriend non-eng to learn what is important for business.</li>
    <li>Understand your customer.</li>
    <li>Understand what already exists inside and outside your org before creating something new.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.thevoid.community/report">The VOID report</a>: incidents newsletter.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.rawsignal.ca/newsletter">Raw signal</a>: management and leadership newsletter.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-3"></a>Chapter 3 - Creating the Big Picture</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Tech vision:
  <ul>
    <li>Describe future as if all work to get there had been done.</li>
    <li>Any scope:
    <ul>
      <li>Smaller scopes should inherit from larger ones.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Tech strategy:
  <ul>
    <li>Plan of action: how to achieve your goals, and navigating past the obstacles.</li>
    <li><a href="/2020/08/31/good-strategy-bad-strategy-summary/#content">Good/Bad strategy</a>:
    <ol>
      <li>Diagnosis: distill the situation to its most essential characteristic.</li>
      <li>Guiding policy: short and clear signpost, marking the direction forward.</li>
      <li>Coherent action: specific based from diagnosis/guiding policy.
      <ul>
        <li>They are a time commitment.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ol>
    <ul>
      <li>Strategy should draw on your advantages.</li>
      <li>Strategy is realistic and within your org constraints.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Vision/Strategy is not always needed:
  <ul>
    <li>It is a big project.</li>
    <li>Getting the people to agree <strong>is</strong> the work.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>The approach:
  <ul>
    <li>Good strategy is boring to write about:
    <ul>
      <li>Should be obvious.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Join existing initiatives.</li>
    <li>Find a sponsor:
    <ul>
      <li>Ensure your plan fix some of their problems.</li>
      <li>Elevator pitch.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Choose your core group:
    <ul>
      <li>Makes you accountable.</li>
      <li>Small (2-4), committed to 8-12 hours per week.</li>
      <li>Consider bringing those who will oppose the most.</li>
      <li>Keep a broader set of allies informed and engaged.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Set scope:
    <ul>
      <li>How much of the ord you plan to influence.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Make sure it is achievable:
    <ul>
      <li>Cut scope.</li>
      <li>Be prepared to give up.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Make it official.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>The writing:<br/> <img src="/images/blog/books/staff-engineers-path/writing.png" alt="Writing process" />
  <ul>
    <li>Questions:
    <ul>
      <li>What is great as it is?</li>
      <li>What is important?</li>
      <li>What will future you wish that present you had done?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Reviewers will be biased by what is already in the doc:
    <ul>
      <li>Mitigations:
      <ul>
        <li>Talk more before writing.</li>
        <li>Make clear what parts you don&rsquo;t feel strong about.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Interviews final questions:
    <ul>
      <li>What else should I have asked you?</li>
      <li>Is there anything important I missed?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>None of the options can make everybody happy:
    <ul>
      <li>Rather than asking &ldquo;Is everyone ok with option A?&rdquo; ask &ldquo;Can anyone not live with option A?&rdquo;</li>
      <li>Decide upfront who is the tiebreaker.</li>
      <li>Not deciding is a decision, usually not a good one.</li>
      <li>Document any decision, including trade-offs and reasons.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Alignment:
  <ul>
    <li>Stay aligned with your sponsor, at minimum in the major checkpoints.</li>
    <li>Nemawashi: by the time of voting, you should know the result.</li>
    <li>Vision or strategy that not everyone knows is of little value.</li>
    <li>Find a one-liner slogan.</li>
    <li>What is the difference between your document being yours and the organizations?
    <ul>
      <li>Belief.</li>
      <li>Staffing the work, second.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-2"></a>Part II - Execution</h1><h2><a name="ch-4"></a>Chapter 4 - Finite Time</h2>
<ul>
  <li>You have to make peace with walking past things that are broken or suboptimal.</li>
  <li>Do what is important for the company, but also what is important for you.
  <ul>
    <li>Consider:
    <ul>
      <li>Energy:
      <ul>
        <li>Your current level and what the project will consume.</li>
        <li>Different people need different levels of energy for the same project.</li>
        <li>How many things are you already doing? Limit WIP.</li>
        <li>Does this kind of work give you or take energy?</li>
        <li>Are you procrastinating?
        <ul>
          <li>Notice when you are doing busy work because you are tired, and find a way to rest instead.</li>
        </ul></li>
        <li>Is this fight worth it?
        <ul>
          <li>Compare with other work.</li>
        </ul></li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Quality of life:
      <ul>
        <li>Do you enjoy this work?</li>
        <li>How do you feel about the project&rsquo;s goals?</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Credibility:
      <ul>
        <li>Does this project use your technical skills?</li>
        <li>Does this project show your leadership skills?</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Social capital:
      <ul>
        <li>It this the kind of work that your company and your manager expect at your level?
        <ul>
          <li>Making your reporting chain successful gives them social capital that they can spend to help you.</li>
        </ul></li>
        <li>Will this work be respected?</li>
        <li>Are you squandering the capital you have built?</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Skills:
      <ul>
        <li>Each project will increase or decrease these.</li>
        <li>Will this project teach you something you want to learn?</li>
        <li>Will people around you raise your game?</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Everything you commit to have an opportunity cost.</li>
  <li>Put non meetings in the calendar too:
  <ul>
    <li>Not &ldquo;make time&rdquo; but specific items.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t allocate 100% of your time:
  <ul>
    <li>Spikes in work will spill to your personal life.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Increase your skills in three ways:
  <ol>
    <li>Deliberately learn something: take a class, buy a book, take a toy project.
    <ul>
      <li>Unlikely to happen at work.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Work with someone more skilled.</li>
    <li>Learn by doing: most common.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>What if it is the wrong project?
  <ul>
    <li>If it is temporal, maybe do it.</li>
    <li>Let others lead: mentorship opportunity.</li>
    <li>Resize it.</li>
    <li>Say no.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-5"></a>Chapter 5 - Leading Big Projects</h2>
<ul>
  <li>A great project lead has:
  <ul>
    <li>Perseverance.</li>
    <li>Courage.</li>
    <li>Willingness to talk to other people.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>The usual reason why a project is difficult is that you are dealing with ambiguity.</li>
  <li>Big project == several months + multiple teams.</li>
  <li>Number one tool for project success: writing things down.</li>
  <li>Ambiguity is the nature of the work.</li>
  <li>To make a project less overwhelming at the beginning:
  <ol>
    <li>Write things down: ideas, leads, rumors, to-dos, &hellip;</li>
    <li>Talk to your sponsor: understand what they want to achieve.</li>
    <li>Find at least one person that you can be open and unsure with.</li>
    <li>Give yourself a win: small steps.</li>
    <li>Use your strengths.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Building context:
  <ol>
    <li>Goals: why are you doing this project?</li>
    <li>Understand customers:
    <ul>
      <li>Working with PMs, ask for their advice.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Success metrics.</li>
    <li>Stakeholders.</li>
    <li>Figure out fixed constraints.</li>
    <li>Risks and mitigations.</li>
    <li>History of the project:
    <ul>
      <li>Respect what came before.</li>
      <li>Where it did come from?</li>
      <li>How was it announced?</li>
      <li>Who has already tried? What they left behind?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Team.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Project structure:
  <ul>
    <li>Define roles:
    <ul>
      <li>Specially important if multiple senior people are involved.</li>
      <li>To avoid overlaps and cracks/orphaned work/responsibilities.</li>
      <li><a href="https://www.cio.com/article/287088/project-management-how-to-design-a-successful-raci-project-plan.html">RACI matrix</a>:
      <ul>
        <li>Responsible: doing the work.</li>
        <li>Accountable: only one per task.</li>
        <li>Consulted.</li>
        <li>Informed.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>As a project lead, you will fill any roles that you don&rsquo;t have someone in them.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Recruit people that are optimistic, good at conflict resolution and comms.</li>
    <li>Scope and milestones:
    <ul>
      <li>People don&rsquo;t act with a sense of urgency until there is a deadline that they cannot avoid thinking about.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>I have met almost nobody who is good at time estimation.</li>
    <li>Estimating should take into account other teams that you depend on:
    <ul>
      <li>If you ask those teams for last minute changed, you are disrupting the time estimation of other projects.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Set rituals, comm channels, dev practices.</li>
    <li>Kick off meeting.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Driving the project:
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://leaddev.com/agile-other-ways-working/avoid-lake">Avoid the lake!</a> by Kripa Krishnan.</li>
  </ul>
  <ol>
    <li>Explore:
    <ul>
      <li>Get to the point where you can concisely explain what different teams in the project want in a way that they&rsquo;ll agree is accurate:
      <ul>
        <li>Loads of talking <strong>and listening</strong>.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Build elevator pitch: reduce it to its most important aspects.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Clarify:
    <ul>
      <li>Give mental models for what you are all doing:
      <ul>
        <li>Hook your model to the person&rsquo;s existing knowledge.</li>
        <li>Analogies and metaphors.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Glossary: ubiquitous language.</li>
      <li>Graph/pictures.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Design:
    <ul>
      <li>A written design is a very cheap iteration, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/cian-synnott/">Cian Synnott</a>.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>We are built for novelty and excitement, not for careful attention to detail. Discipline is something we have to work at. <cite>Atul Gawande, <em>The Checklist Manifesto</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
  <li>RFC:
  <ul>
    <li>The implementation should serve the goal; it should not be the goal.</li>
    <li>Design section:
    <ul>
      <li>Readers should understand what you intend to do, and should be able to tell you whether they think it will work.</li>
      <li>Better wrong than vague: chance to change direction early.</li>
      <li>Avoid passive voice:
      <ul>
        <li>Dr. Rebecca Johnson: If you can insert &lsquo;by zombies&rsquo; after the verb, you have passive voice.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>If it seems trivial, it is because you do not understand it.</li>
      <li>Any part of your solution that involves humans changing their workflows or behaviour will be difficult and needs to be part of the design.</li>
      <li>Figure the hard parts earlier.</li>
      <li>Name who will be on call for any new system.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Coding:
  <ul>
    <li>Writing code is rarely the highest leverage thing you can spend time on.</li>
    <li>Coding gives you a depth of understanding that is hard to gain otherwise.</li>
    <li>Avoid being in the critical path.</li>
    <li>Set example (design, patterns, &hellip;).</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Communicating well is key for delivering a project in time.</li>
  <li>If your project is stuck, don&rsquo;t hide it: ask for help.</li>
  <li>Something will always go wrong:
  <ul>
    <li>Take it as an opportunity to learn.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-6"></a>Chapter 6 - Why Have We Stopped?</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Techniques to get unstuck:
  <ol>
    <li>Understand and explain.</li>
    <li>Make the work easier.</li>
    <li>Get org support:
    <ul>
      <li>Show it is an objective.</li>
      <li>Show value.</li>
      <li>Escalate.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Make alternative plans.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Supporting an untrained person through making a change in a difficult codebase takes more effort than doing it yourself.</li>
  <li>Three bullet points and a call to action:
  <ul>
    <li>Three bullet points detailing the issue at hand.</li>
    <li>One and only one call to action.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Blocked by:
  <ul>
    <li>A decision: make a guess and document it with an ADR.</li>
    <li>A single &ldquo;please click this button&rdquo;:
    <ul>
      <li>Might be a big queue of &ldquo;just click this button&rdquo;.</li>
      <li>The other person is responsible for the result.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Unassigned work:
    <ul>
      <li>Rollup the context to make it explicit.</li>
      <li>Volunteer to mentor/advise/join the team that will own it.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>By a huge crowd of people:
    <ul>
      <li>Like a migration.</li>
      <li>Be a bridge
      <ul>
        <li>The team pushing for the migration to do as much work as possible.</li>
        <li>Make the new way the default:
        <ul>
          <li>Consider adding some friction to the old way.</li>
        </ul></li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>You are stuck:
  <ul>
    <li>Don&rsquo;t know where you&rsquo;re all going:
    <ul>
      <li>No agreement. Too many disparate voices, all interested in the problem:
      <ol>
        <li>Clarify roles:
        <ul>
          <li>Leader is the final decision maker.</li>
        </ul></li>
        <li>Choose strategy:
        <ul>
          <li>No talk about implementation until all agree about the problem.</li>
          <li>Don&rsquo;t try to solve everything neither please everyone.</li>
        </ul></li>
        <li>Choose stakeholder:
        <ul>
          <li>Reorient the project around getting something to someone.</li>
          <li>Vertical slices.</li>
        </ul></li>
      </ol></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>You don&rsquo;t know how to get there:
    <ul>
      <li>Path is unknown but not unknowable.</li>
      <li>Articulate the problem.</li>
      <li>Revisit your assumptions:
      <ul>
        <li>Have you already assumed a specific solution?</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Step away from the problem for a few days.</li>
      <li>Look for prior art, including outside IT.</li>
      <li>Connect with the community.</li>
      <li>Start small.</li>
      <li>Look at the problem from a completely different angles.</li>
      <li>Ask for help.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>You don&rsquo;t know where you stand:
    <ul>
      <li>Is the work still necessary?</li>
      <li>Less comms or interest from leadership.</li>
      <li>Go and ask.</li>
      <li>You will not get what you want if you don&rsquo;t ask for it.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Team thinks project is done but problem is not solved:
  <ol>
    <li>&ldquo;Finished&rdquo; but not usable yet:
    <ul>
      <li>Agree on a definition of done.</li>
      <li>Be your own user.</li>
      <li>Celebrate only once users are happy.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Done but nobody uses it:
    <ul>
      <li>Don&rsquo;t just tell people that the solution exists: you need to keep telling them.</li>
      <li>Make it easy to find.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Built on shaky foundations:
    <ul>
      <li>If the project is not in good shape by the end of it, it will never be.</li>
      <li>Set a culture of quality.</li>
      <li>User stories out of bugs and incidents.</li>
      <li>Negotiate ring-fencing resources for technical work.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Reasons to stop:
  <ul>
    <li>Further investment is not worth the cost.</li>
    <li>You learn that it will not work.</li>
    <li>Project cancelled by higher management:
    <ul>
      <li>Even if it is for good reasons, you will feel bad about it.</li>
      <li>Be the one telling the team.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>You finished! Celebrate!</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-3"></a>Part III - Leveling Up</h1><h2><a name="ch-7"></a>Chapter 7 - You&rsquo;re a Role Model Now (Sorry)</h2>
<ul>
  <li>People assume that you know what you are talking about, so be careful with what you say.</li>
  <li>You are a role model: how you behave is how others will behave.</li>
  <li>Values is what you do.</li>
  <li>The clearest indication of what the company is what gets people promoted.</li>
  <li>Attributes of a staff engineer:
  <ol>
    <li>Competent:
    <ol>
      <li>Technically:
      <ul>
        <li>You can learn a lot from books but there is no substitute for doing it yourself.</li>
        <li>Do not accept a management role until you are a solid senior engineer.</li>
        <li>Beware if you are only learning how your company operated, but nothing technical.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Self-aware:
      <ul>
        <li>What you cant do.</li>
        <li>How long will take.</li>
        <li>What you don&rsquo;t know.</li>
        <li>Your own context (which will be different from others).</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>High standards:
      <ul>
        <li>Seek constructive criticism.</li>
        <li>Own your mistakes:
        <ul>
          <li>Communicate clearly and quickly.</li>
          <li>Set to fix it.</li>
        </ul></li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Be reliable: finish what you start.</li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>Responsible:
    <ol>
      <li>Take ownership:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://medium.com/@ElizAyer/dont-ask-forgiveness-radiate-intent-d36fd22393a3">Radiating intent</a> (instead of seeking permission or asking for forgiveness).</li>
        <li>Make decisions.</li>
        <li>Ask &ldquo;obvious&rdquo; questions: make the implicit explicit.</li>
        <li>Glue work.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Take charge:
      <ul>
        <li>Redirecting colleagues to more valuable work.</li>
        <li>Take control of a mess/incident.</li>
        <li>Drive meetings:
        <ul>
          <li>Take notes.</li>
          <li>Ensure agenda.</li>
          <li>Keep it focused.</li>
        </ul></li>
        <li>Speak up when you see behavioral problems.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Create calm:
      <ul>
        <li>Make big problems small.</li>
        <li>Keep small problems small.</li>
        <li>Be consistent.</li>
        <li>Take time off.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>Remember the goal:
    <ul>
      <li>SW is a means to a goal, not a goal itself.</li>
      <li>There is always a budget.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Look Ahead:
    <ul>
      <li>Don&rsquo;t optimize for now at the cost of future velocity or capability.</li>
      <li>Announce intention to deprecate old systems.</li>
      <li>Continually make your environment better.</li>
      <li>Faster safer deploys.</li>
      <li>Document.</li>
      <li>Build the expectation of failure into your products.</li>
      <li>Optimize for maintenance, not creation.</li>
      <li>Keep it simple: spend at least the same amount of time on possible second solution as you will in the first one.</li>
      <li>Build with decommission in mind.</li>
      <li>Create future leaders.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>The degree to which other people want to work with you is a direct indication of how successful you&rsquo;ll be in your career as an engineer. Be the engineer that everyone wants to work with.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-8"></a>Chapter 8 - Good Influence at Scale</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Three tiers of influence:
  <ul>
    <li>Individual.</li>
    <li>Group.</li>
    <li>Catalyst: your influence continue even after you step away.</li>
    <li>Do the first two first, only go broader if value is clear.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>4 forms:</li>
</ul>
<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th> </th>
      <th>Individual </th>
      <th>Group </th>
      <th>Catalyst </th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Advice </td>
      <td>Mentoring, sharing knowledge, feedback </td>
      <td>Tech talks, documentation, articles </td>
      <td>Mentorship program, tech talk events </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Teaching </td>
      <td>Code reviews, design review, coaching, pairing, shadowing </td>
      <td>Classes, codelabs </td>
      <td>Onboarding curriculum, teaching people to teach </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Guardrails </td>
      <td>Code review, change review, design review </td>
      <td>Processes, linters, style guides </td>
      <td>Frameworks, culture change </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Opportunity </td>
      <td>Delegating, sponsorship, cheerleading, ongoing support </td>
      <td>Sharing the spotlight, empowering your team </td>
      <td>Creating a culture of opportunity, watching with pride as your superstar junior colleagues change the world </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<ol>
  <li>Advise:
  <ul>
    <li>Should be tailored to the person receiving it.</li>
    <li>Mentorship:
    <ul>
      <li>Sharing <strong>your</strong> experience so others can leverage on it:
      <ul>
        <li>Might not be useful/applicable.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Don&rsquo;t jump to give advice, sometimes the mentee just need to vent or get empathy on the situation.</li>
      <li>Set objectives for mentorship.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Be kindly honest.</li>
    <li>Peer reviews:
    <ul>
      <li>2 audiences:
      <ul>
        <li>Person who asked for feedback.</li>
        <li>Their manager.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>If you cannot think on what to improve, ask yourself why they aren&rsquo;t one level more senior.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Encourage people to write things down.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Teaching:
  <ul>
    <li>Code reviews:
    <ul>
      <li>Careful to not destroy somebody&rsquo;s confidence and growth mindset.</li>
      <li>Call out the good as well as the bad.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Guardrails:
  <ul>
    <li>Encourage autonomy, exploration and innovation:
    <ul>
      <li>They will not stop you going over the edge.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Reviews:
    <ul>
      <li>Should the work exists?</li>
      <li>Does it solve the problem?</li>
      <li>Will it handle failure?</li>
      <li>Understandable?</li>
      <li>Fits the bigger picture?</li>
      <li>Do the right people know about it?</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Opportunity:
  <ul>
    <li>Finding people the experience that they need to grow.</li>
    <li>Delegation:
    <ul>
      <li>Give them a messy, unscoped project with a bit of a safety net.</li>
      <li>When you delegate, you are not going to get a clone:
      <ul>
        <li>Good as long as they achieve the goals.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Sponsorship:
    <ul>
      <li>You are investing your time and social capital in their growth.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
</ol><h2><a name="ch-9"></a>Chapter 9 - What&rsquo;s Next?</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Expand your perspective by reading, attending conferences and asking others about their journey.</li>
  <li>You cannot be an expert in everything.</li>
  <li>If the work fills you with dread or exhausts you, instead of exciting you, look for a different path to your goal.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.scienceofpeople.com/conference-networking/">How to network</a> by Vanessa Van Edwards.</li>
  <li>Build visibility.</li>
  <li>The most time-efficient way to build skills, visibility and contacts is as part of your job. You&rsquo;ll get better at whatever you spend time on.</li>
  <li>Every job should help you grow towards your long-term goals and meet your immediate needs.</li>
  <li>Keep a weekly record of your job signals:
  <ol>
    <li>Are you growing/learning?</li>
    <li>Are the skills transferable?</li>
    <li>Would you recruit friends to your company?</li>
    <li>How is your confidence? How capable you feel?</li>
    <li>How stressed you feel?</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Staying in one place for long gives you the feedback loop that comes from seeing the consequences of your actions.</li>
  <li>What to do next:
  <ul>
    <li>You may just want to use your current skills and keep doing much the same job until you retire.</li>
    <li>Promotion.</li>
    <li>Work less:
    <ul>
      <li>If you weren&rsquo;t able to avoid working overtime at five days a week, why you think you can stick to working four?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Change internal team.</li>
    <li>New specialization.</li>
    <li>Management.</li>
    <li>Find/invent your own niche:
    <ul>
      <li>Learn what your strengths are, and then finding &ldquo;holes that are shaped like you&rdquo;.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Same job, different employer.</li>
    <li>Change jobs and level up or down.</li>
    <li>Your own start-up.</li>
    <li>Go independent.</li>
    <li>Change careers.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul>]]></description></item><item><title>Book notes: Deming's Journey to Profound Knowledge: How Deming Helped Win a War, Altered the Face of Industry, and Holds the Key to Our Future</title><link>https://danlebrero.com/2024/01/04/deming-journey-to-profound-knowledge-summary/</link><guid>https://danlebrero.com/2024/01/04/deming-journey-to-profound-knowledge-summary/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><description><![CDATA[<p>These are my notes on <a href="https://amzn.to/3FFsMQH">Deming&rsquo;s Journey to Profound Knowledge: How Deming Helped Win a War, Altered the Face of Industry, and Holds the Key to Our Future</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/botchagalupe">John Willis</a> with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dereklewisbooks/">Derek Lewis</a>.</p><p>&ldquo;This book is truly about how the lens of Profound Knowledge was found&rdquo;.</p><h1>Key Insights</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Deming is the foundation of Lean, Agile and DevOps.</li>
  <li>Variability is a fact of life.</li>
  <li>Elements of the System of Profound Knowledge:
  <ol>
    <li>A Theory of Knowledge: How we know what we believe we know?</li>
    <li>A Theory of Variation: How do we analyze and understand what we know?</li>
    <li>A Theory of Psychology: How do we account for human behaviour?</li>
    <li>An Appreciation of Systems/Systems Thinking: Are we seeing the bigger picture?</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>The opposite of analytic thinking is systems thinking.</li>
  <li>Japanese workers believed they were doing something that <em>mattered</em>.</li>
  <li>No matter how precise the machines and the processes, the outputs all slightly varied from each other.</li>
  <li>Less waste allowed manufacturers to do more and more with less and less.</li>
  <li>Shewharts method enabled management to see defects as result of process instead of the workers.</li>
  <li>Defect classification:
  <ol>
    <li>Common cause: variations that could be predicted and should be planned for.</li>
    <li>Special cause: couldn&rsquo;t be predicted and shouldn&rsquo;t be planned for.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>The real value of Statistical Process Control is that it allows you to observe variation and look at random vs non-random patterns:
  <ul>
    <li>A random pattern represents a stable process, aka a process &ldquo;under control&rdquo;.</li>
    <li>A non-random pattern is a useful predictor of potential defects, signaling an amount of uncertainly in the process.</li>
    <li>And here is the root of all evil: misidentifying variation.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Under-performing and brand-new operators would have 100% of their work inspected until their work fell within the control limits.</li>
  <li>We really didnt believe. We did what we were told and it worked.</li>
  <li>They shouldnt strive to be better than others but to strive to be better than themselves - that is true competition.</li>
  <li>Management by means (MBM):
  <ul>
    <li>If you don&rsquo;t know how you achieved your objective, how do you know if you can do it again?</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="https://deming.org/explore/fourteen-points/">14 Points for Management</a></li>
  <li>A common disease that afflicts management is the impression that our problems are different.</li>
  <li>Only 6% of problems are due to human error. 94% are system error. And since the system is the responsibility of management, 94% of problems are caused by bad management.</li>
  <li><p>Quality is not so much about improving the product as it is about improving the process.</p>
  <blockquote>In God we trust. All others must bring data. <cite>Dr. Deming</cite>
  </blockquote></li>
  <li>Organizations need to be a place where people can teach themselves.</li>
  <li>Perfection is not for this world.</li>
</ul><h1>TOC</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#p-0">Preface</a></li>
  <li><a href="#p-00">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#p-1">Part I - Foundations of Profound Knowledge</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-1">Chapter 1 - Humble Origins &amp; Non-Determinism</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-2">Chapter 2 - The Jungle in Paradise</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-3">Chapter 3 - The Birth of Quality Control &amp; Standardization</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-4">Chapter 4 - The Root of All Evil</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-5">Chapter 5 - Pragmatist</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-2">Part II - Applications of Profound Knowledge</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-6">Chapter 6 - Dr. Deming Goes to Washington</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-7">Chapter 7 - Rosie &amp; World War II</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-8">Chapter 8 - CLASSIFIED</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-3">Part III - International Implications of Profound Knowledge</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-9">Chapter 9 - Samurai Statistics</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-10">Chapter 10 - JUSE &amp; the Gentle Giant</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-11">Chapter 11 - The Butterfly Effect</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-12">Chapter 12 - Made in Japan</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-13">Chapter 13 - Rising Sun, Falling Eagle</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-14">Chapter 14 - Demingmania</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-15">Chapter 15 - Dr. Quinn, Medicine Woman</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-4">Part IV - The Next Generation of Profound Knowledge</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-16">Chapter 16 - The Digital Cambrian Explosion</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-17">Chapter 17 - What Would Deming Do?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-18">Chapter 18 - Deming&rsquo;s Dark Legacy</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-19">Chapter 19 - Out of the Cyber Crisis</a></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-0"></a>Preface</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/3s94VpF">Eliyahu Goldratt</a> books:
  <ul>
    <li>The Goal.</li>
    <li>Theory of Constraints.</li>
    <li>Critical Chain.</li>
    <li>It&rsquo;s Not Luck.</li>
    <li>Necessary but Not Sufficient.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Deming is the foundation of Lean, Agile and DevOps.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="p-00"></a>Introduction</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The Allies won because the US outproduced the rest of the world:
  <ul>
    <li>Despite the absence of millions of skilled American workers and managers.</li>
    <li>Thanks to the statistical process control method.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>The very nature of reality is random.</li>
  <li>Variability is a fact of life.</li>
  <li>Elements of the System of Profound Knowledge:
  <ol>
    <li>A Theory of Knowledge: How we know what we believe we know?</li>
    <li>A Theory of Variation: How do we analyze and understand what we know?</li>
    <li>A Theory of Psychology: How do we account for human behaviour?</li>
    <li>An Appreciation of Systems/Systems Thinking: Are we seeing the bigger picture?</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Deming&rsquo;s mission was to work himself out of a job.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-1"></a>Part I - Foundations of Profound Knowledge</h1><h2><a name="ch-1"></a>Chapter 1 - Humble Origins &amp; Non-Determinism</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Determinism (Newtonian Physics): World operates solely on cause and effect.</li>
  <li>Non-Determinism:
  <ul>
    <li>No matter how much you know, there is an infinite amount of change and randomness in the universe.</li>
    <li>No such thing as absolute certainty.</li>
    <li>Crucial role in shaping Deming&rsquo;s worldview:
    <ol>
      <li>Long-established and long-held beliefs weren&rsquo;t necessarily true.</li>
      <li>Underpinnings of our very existence are random.</li>
      <li>Forced him to look at problems as multifaceted, complex systems.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>The opposite of analytic thinking is systems thinking.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-2"></a>Chapter 2 - The Jungle in Paradise</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Hawthorne Works:
  <ul>
    <li>Treated its workers more like partners than peasants. And it worked.</li>
    <li>Corporate success forged a bond of loyalty with its employees.</li>
    <li>&ldquo;Hawthorne Effect&rdquo;:
    <ul>
      <li>The act of subjects changing their behaviour in response to being observed.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Japanese workers believed they were doing something that <em>mattered</em>.</li>
  <li>Workers:
  <ul>
    <li>Ford:
    <ul>
      <li>Saw them as inconvenient cogs in the machine.</li>
      <li>Standardize to make them interchangeable.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Taylor:
    <ul>
      <li>Scientific management.</li>
      <li>Saw them as machines themselves.</li>
      <li>Optimize them for maximum efficiency, through right physical and psychological conditions.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Both:
    <ul>
      <li>Think that workers don&rsquo;t want to work.</li>
      <li>Antagonism between workers and managers.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Piecework is man&rsquo;s lowest degradation:
  <ul>
    <li>Incentivices workers to focus on quantity, not quality.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-3"></a>Chapter 3 - The Birth of Quality Control &amp; Standardization</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The eternal question of quality has always been this: &ldquo;How good is good enough?&rdquo;</li>
  <li>Machine age: standardization was the catalyst.</li>
  <li>Interchangeable parts were the turning point in the history of quality control and led to the theory of variation.</li>
  <li>No matter how precise the machines and the processes, the outputs all slightly varied from each other:
  <ul>
    <li>This spawned a need to allow for variance in product specifications.</li>
    <li>This is more in line with a non-deterministic approach.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-4"></a>Chapter 4 - The Root of All Evil</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Statistics is about how confident you feel when dealing with uncertainty.</li>
  <li>Operational definition: procedure agreed upon to translate a concept into a precise measurement.</li>
  <li>If you can track variation, then you can trace variation to better understand why a production line creates defects and detect it much earlier in the process.</li>
  <li>Statistical Process Control (SPC) let managers compare variation across workers and machines.</li>
  <li>Less waste allowed manufacturers to do more and more with less and less.</li>
  <li>Shewhart&rsquo;s method enabled management to see defects as result of process instead of the workers.</li>
  <li>Plan, do, check, study.</li>
  <li>Defect classification:
  <ol>
    <li>Common cause: variations that could be predicted and should be planned for.</li>
    <li>Special cause: couldn&rsquo;t be predicted and shouldn&rsquo;t be planned for.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Shewhart: as long as the variance fell within standard-deviation limits, the variance was inherent to the manufacturing process (common cause).</li>
  <li>The real value of SPC is that it allows you to observe variation and look at random vs non-random patterns:
  <ul>
    <li>A random pattern represents a stable process, aka a process &ldquo;under control&rdquo;.</li>
    <li>A non-random pattern is a useful predictor of potential defects, signaling an amount of uncertainly in the process.</li>
    <li>And here is the root of all evil: misidentifying variation.</li>
    <li>As a result, managers can spend their time on things they can control.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>SPC allows you to statistically predict defects before they occur.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-5"></a>Chapter 5 - Pragmatist</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The philosophy of pragmatism, what Deming would later call the Theory of Knowledge.</li>
  <li>A meter would be defined as the cord length needed for a clock&rsquo;s pendulum to travel one swing per second.</li>
  <li>Two types of knowledge: a priori and a posteriori.</li>
  <li>A posteriori thinkers or &ldquo;pragmatists&rdquo;:
  <ul>
    <li>Experience is the best teacher.</li>
    <li>Begin with observations and empirical data (hard evidence) and then work their way backwards.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>A standard is a measurement that suffices and that everybody agrees upon.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-2"></a>Part II - Applications of Profound Knowledge</h1><h2><a name="ch-6"></a>Chapter 6 - Dr. Deming Goes to Washington</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Under-performing and brand-new operators would have 100% of their work inspected until their work fell within the control limits.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-7"></a>Chapter 7 - Rosie &amp; World War II</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Victory came because the US outproduced the rest of the world.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-8"></a>Chapter 8 - CLASSIFIED</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Bounded rationality: humans can process only so much information at a time.</li>
  <li>David Woods: Anomaly response situations frequently involved time pressure, multiple interacting goals, high consequences of failure, and multiple interleaved tasks.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-3"></a>Part III - International Implications of Profound Knowledge</h1><h2><a name="ch-9"></a>Chapter 9 - Samurai Statistics</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The US used statistics to win the war, even as Japan threw statistics out of the windows. Afterwards, Japan used statistics to win the economic war, even as the US threw statistics out the window.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-10"></a>Chapter 10 - JUSE &amp; the Gentle Giant</h2>
<ul>
  <li>SPC wasn&rsquo;t just about applying statistics to output. Quality touched everything in the process, including the quality of raw materials and components received from supplier and vendors.</li>
  <li>Ed knew that unless it included top management, the classes were unlikely to succeed.</li>
  <li>JUSE used the proceeds from the lecture fees and book royalties to fund a prize in Deming&rsquo;s honor. Accomplished three critical purposes:
  <ol>
    <li>Associated JUSE with one of the most famous statisticians in the world.</li>
    <li>Laid a sort of territorial claim to the man.</li>
    <li>Guaranteed Deming&rsquo;s involvement in Japan.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Deming: They wanted more conferences, so we had more. It was a terrifying experience for me because I was new at it. I was a technical man.</li>
  <li>We really didn&rsquo;t believe. We did what we were told and it worked.</li>
  <li>He inspired hope, if not confidence.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-11"></a>Chapter 11 - The Butterfly Effect</h2>
<ul>
  <li>He demonstrated how even competitors working together benefited their respective companies and, more importantly, their customers.</li>
  <li>What is Deming&rsquo;s real legacy? It is seeing the grander scheme and preaching cooperation instead of competition.</li>
  <li>They shouldn&rsquo;t strive to be better than others but to strive to be better than themselves - that is true competition.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-12"></a>Chapter 12 - Made in Japan</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Because demand and profit margins were so high, US companies could afford waste, rework, stockpiling inventory, and other inefficiencies.</li>
  <li>Taylorism focused on eliminating individual waste. Ohno focused on systemic waste.</li>
  <li>Assembly-line workers were cross-trained in different positions.</li>
  <li>Machines were make multipurpose.</li>
  <li>Kanban:
  <ul>
    <li>The aim was to produce only what was needed, when it was needed, and in the amount needed.</li>
    <li>It went against everything Henry Ford believed and practiced.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-13"></a>Chapter 13 - Rising Sun, Falling Eagle</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Kaizen: a process of deliberate, patient, continual refinement.</li>
  <li>How long do you think it will take the US to catch up with Japan?
  <ul>
    <li>Do you think Japan is standing still?</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>What made one manufacturing plant better than others? Adopting a lean manufacturing philosophy trumped all those other factors.</li>
  <li>US companies focused on the process but forgot the people.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-14"></a>Chapter 14 - Demingmania</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Management by means (MBM):
  <ul>
    <li>If you don&rsquo;t know how you achieved your objective, how do you know if you can do it again?</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="https://deming.org/explore/fourteen-points/">14 Points for Management</a>:
  <ul>
    <li>Improve constantly and forever the system.</li>
    <li>Eliminate slogans, exhortations, and targets for the workforce asking for zero defects and new levels of productivity. Such exhortations only create adversarial relationships, as the build of the causes of low quality and low productivity belong to the system and thus lie beyond the power of the workforce.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Waraniak didn&rsquo;t focus on the race: he looked at the preparations and training leading up to it:
  <ul>
    <li>By using two cars and two teams in the design, training, and setup phases, GM could prototype twice the number of ideas and innovations.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-15"></a>Chapter 15 - Dr. Quinn, Medicine Woman</h2><h1><a name="p-4"></a>Part IV - The Next Generation of Profound Knowledge</h1><h2><a name="ch-16"></a>Chapter 16 - The Digital Cambrian Explosion</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Dr. Deming reaction to someone who was complaning that he had changed something in his teaching: &ldquo;I will never apologize for learning&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>Lean development focus on waste, whereas agile focus on delivery.</li>
  <li>Steve Blank, The Lean Startup: putting together build, measure, learn and MVP with agile and lean methodologies.</li>
  <li>DevOps: collaboration between devs and ops, and automation of agile and lean principles.</li>
  <li>Read Deming&rsquo;s 14 Points of Management to understand the roots of DevOps.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-17"></a>Chapter 17 - What Would Deming Do?</h2>
<ul>
  <li>A common disease that afflicts management is the impression that &ldquo;our problems are different&rdquo;:
  <ul>
    <li>They are different, to be sure, but the principles that will help are universal in nature.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>To profoundly change a system, requires know-how outside of that system.
  <ul>
    <li>If the system had the knowledge, then it would change itself on its own.</li>
    <li>Ed&rsquo;s System of Profound Knowledge does not require someone from the outside.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Only 6% of problems are due to human error. 94% are system error.
  <ul>
    <li>And since the system is the responsibility of management, 94% of problems are caused by bad management.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-18"></a>Chapter 18 - Deming&rsquo;s Dark Legacy</h2>
<ul>
  <li>From 2021, federal government&rsquo;s vendors are required to supply a software bill of materials.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-19"></a>Chapter 19 - Out of the Cyber Crisis</h2>
<ul>
  <li>When you silo cybersecurity, seeing it as an independent component instead of a system, you put your entire organization at risk.</li>
  <li><p>Shannon Lietz: security needs to be designed into an organization&rsquo;s system.</p>
  <blockquote>It is not necessary to change. Survival is not mandatory. <cite>Dr. Deming</cite>
  </blockquote></li>
  <li>Today, leaders wait until there is a problem before they fix it.</li>
  <li>Quality is not so much about improving the product as it is about improving the process.</li>
  <li>Tighter relationships with fewer suppliers lead to increased process alignment and lower overall costs.</li>
  <li>In God we trust. All others must bring data.</li>
  <li>Instead of looking at incidents through arbitrary categories (P1 to P4), System of Profound Knowledge could be used to identify common-cause and special-cause patterns across all incidents.</li>
  <li>Blameless post-mortem: instead of assigning a problem to a certain person, blame would be placed on the system.</li>
  <li>&ldquo;I didn&rsquo;t question it&rdquo;: famous last words.</li>
  <li>Plenty of executive managers still don&rsquo;t understand the nature of the digital world and demand &ldquo;zero defects&rdquo; or &ldquo;never fail&rdquo; software.</li>
  <li>Maginot Line thinking is when you expend considerable resources in an effort to counteract a past threat.</li>
  <li>The security industry should assume that hackers will gain access to the system. We should plan for the inevitability of them getting in.</li>
  <li>Too often, managing by hard numbers sacrifices quality.</li>
  <li>Organizations need to be a place where people can teach themselves.</li>
  <li>Perfection is not for this world.</li>
</ul>]]></description></item><item><title>Book notes: Wiring the Winning Organization</title><link>https://danlebrero.com/2023/11/27/wiring-the-winning-organization-summary/</link><guid>https://danlebrero.com/2023/11/27/wiring-the-winning-organization-summary/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2023 23:30:00 +0100</pubDate><description><![CDATA[<p>These are my notes on <a href="https://amzn.to/3tT8Xmk">Wiring the Winning Organization</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/RealGeneKim">Gene Kim</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/StevenJSpear">Steven J. Spear</a>.</p><p>Gene and Steven present the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Unified_Theory">Grand Unified Theory</a> of organization performance.</p><p>3 questions to get started:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Are we solving our toughest problems in planning and practice, where we can iterate and learn?</li>
  <li>Are we shaping our problems so that they are easier to solve because they are simple, low risk, controllable, and easy to understand and iterate and learn from?</li>
  <li>Are we calling out problems loudly and consistently so that they can be swarmed, container, solved and prevent future occurrences?</li>
</ol><h1>Key Insights</h1>
<ul>
  <li>People with the best work experiences need fewer resources, less capital equipment, and less time to accomplish greater things:
  <ul>
    <li>It is the management system.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Collaborative problem-solving occurs in three distinct layers:
  <ol>
    <li>Layer 1 contains the technical objects being worked on. Code in our case.</li>
    <li>Layer 2 contains the tools.</li>
    <li>Layer 3 contains the social circuitry:
    <ul>
      <li>Workers have what they need, when they need it, and in the format they need it.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol>
  <ul>
    <li>Layer 1 and 2 are the &ldquo;technical&rdquo; part of a sociotechnical system. Layer 3 is the &ldquo;socio&rdquo; part.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Three mechanisms which create the difference between success and failure:
  <ol>
    <li>Slowification, to make solving problems easier to do:
    <ul>
      <li>Pulling problem-solving out of the realm of performance (operations or execution).</li>
      <li>Instead, realms of planning and practice.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Simplification, to make the problems themselves easier to solve:
    <ul>
      <li>Partitioning large systems into smaller, coherent pieces allow to solve more problems independently and in parallel.</li>
    </ul>
    <ol>
      <li>Incrementalization:
      <ul>
        <li>Partition what is novel (which needs to be tested) from what is known (which is already validated).</li>
        <li>Adds to the novelty in smaller increments.</li>
        <li>Allow to iterate and test changes on fewer factors, so more quickly and safely.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Modularization:
      <ul>
        <li>Smaller, simpler, more numerous coherent pieces.</li>
        <li>Less coupled as they are connected through only a few well-defined and stable interfaces.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Linearization:
      <ul>
        <li>Assembly line.</li>
        <li>Partitions operations that share resources to accomplish multiple objectives into independent and coherent workflows.</li>
        <li>Coherence is achieved by committing all resources needed to generate outputs to workflows.</li>
        <li>Partitioning across workflows is achieved by preventing the sharing of resources between them.</li>
        <li>Partitioning within workflows is achieved by defining hand-offs between steps.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>Amplification, to make it obvious that there are problems that demand attention and whether they&rsquo;ve been seen and solved.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Toyota + General Motors joint venture <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NUMMI">NUMMI</a>:
  <ul>
    <li>From worst to best with same people after changing management system.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Difference between exceptional and ordinary is obvious by observing the experiences of people doing their work.</li>
  <li>Boundary of a group solving problems must be large enough that it is coherent, having all the people and resources needed, but small enough to not require large amounts of coordination.
  <ul>
    <li>How much coupling there is determines how much coherence leaders must create.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>To slowify or not is a choice that leaders make.</li>
  <li>To make things simpler, aim to no need to coordinate with anyone outside the team.</li>
  <li>Change their behaviours, which is a precursor for changing their beliefs.</li>
  <li>When we have more time, lower stakes, and less fear, our creativity can flourish.</li>
  <li>Three phases of work:
  <ol>
    <li>Planning.</li>
    <li>Practice:
    <ul>
      <li>Preproduction/testing.</li>
      <li>We can control the pace and the incremental complexity of what is occurring, so we are not overwhelmed.</li>
      <li>Feedback is used to find flaws and improve our plans.</li>
      <li>Time to coach and improve our abilities to execute those plans.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Performance:
    <ul>
      <li>Force us to depend on already-developed routines, skills, and habits.</li>
      <li>Bring issues back to practice or planning.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Training on speaking up directly, fostering psychologically safe conditions for others to speak up.</li>
  <li>Knowledge capture and the potential for continued progress are never-ending.</li>
  <li>A learning leader are more concerned with asking the question and listening to their team.</li>
  <li>Knowledge can also be captured as code.</li>
  <li>Knowledge capture can be conveyed in routines.</li>
  <li>They believed they couldn&rsquo;t think their way to the right answer; instead, they experimented relentlessly with great frequency and at low cost.</li>
  <li><p><a href="#center-out">Center-out leadership</a>.</p>
  <blockquote>As the complexity of the system increases, so do the cognitive demands on the organization. Managing cognitive load through teams with clear responsibilities and boundaries is a distinguishing focus of effective team design. <cite><a href="https://twitter.com/ruthmalan">Ruth Malan</a></cite>
  </blockquote></li>
  <li>Linearized processes can be fragile:
  <ul>
    <li>Without various stabilization mechanisms, they can quickly devolve into &ldquo;job shops&rdquo;.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Design requires isomorphism between Layers 1 and 3. Production requires isomorphism in all three layers:
  <ul>
    <li>If there is a mismatch, orgs underperform.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>If effectively run orgs:
  <ul>
    <li>The functional leader is responsible for &ldquo;who&rdquo; and &ldquo;how&rdquo; - providing trainer people.</li>
    <li>The flow owner is responsible for the &ldquo;what&rdquo; and &ldquo;when&rdquo; of how those people are deployed.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Accident investigations that stop at &ldquo;human error&rdquo; are not just bad but dangerous.</li>
  <li>Control theory addresses a broad variety of situations where no static plan can achieve the desired goal, no matter how good the plan is:
  <ul>
    <li>Feedback mechanisms are needed.</li>
    <li>Must be significantly faster and more reliable than the object being controlled.</li>
    <li>Fail: People become indifferent, when they point out problems that are never fixed, or help is requested but never arrives.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Standards make succeeding easier; they make it more obvious that something is difficult or even wrong.</li>
  <li>One team leader for every four or so associates doing direct work:
  <ul>
    <li>Primary job is to help associates when they encounter problems.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>When we consider that the most precious resource in any organization is people&rsquo;s ingenuity and creativity, the most common risk is cognitive overload.</li>
</ul><h1>Practices</h1><p>List of practices and theories and if they support Slowification, Simplification ( <strong>I</strong>ncrementalization, <strong>M</strong>odularization, <strong>L</strong>inearization) or Amplification.</p>
<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th> </th>
      <th>Slowification</th>
      <th>Simplification </th>
      <th>Amplification </th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Toyota Production System </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td>I M L </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>DevOps </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td>I M L </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Deming </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td>L </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Agile SW Dev </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td>I </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Lean Startup </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td>I </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Resilience Engineering </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td>M </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>System Dynamics </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Double-Loop Learning </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Improvement Kata </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Gemba walks, Empowerment, Participative Management </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Conway&rsquo;s Law </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>M L </td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Cognitive Load </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>M L </td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Team Topologies </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td>M L </td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Technical Debt </td>
      <td>X </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Software Architecture </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>M </td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Normalization of Deviance </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Lean Thinking </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>L </td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Psychological Safety </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Westrum Cultural Typologies </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>X </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table><p><br/></p><h1>Case Studies</h1><p>List of all cases studies in the book:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Chapter 5:
  <ul>
    <li>Case studies:</li>
    <li>MIT Sloan School Sailing Team.</li>
    <li>Mrs. Morris/Ms. Morrison.</li>
    <li>Apollo 11.</li>
    <li>The Columbia Space Shuttle Disaster.</li>
    <li>The Imperial Japanese Navy and Command, Control, and Compliance Leadership.</li>
    <li>The US Navy and Learning Leadership.</li>
    <li>United Airlines Flight 232 Crash Landing.</li>
    <li>United Airlines Flight 173 Crash.</li>
    <li>Google and Amazon Disaster Readiness Drills.</li>
    <li>Netflix.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Chapter 6:
  <ul>
    <li>Boston Marathon: Preparing for a Mass Casualty Event.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Chapter 8:
  <ul>
    <li>Wright Brother&rsquo;s First Flight.</li>
    <li>Incrementalization in the Arts.</li>
    <li>Apple iPhone vs Nokia.</li>
    <li>Menomonee Falls Safe School Reopenings.</li>
    <li>Mastering New Naval Technology.</li>
    <li>Amazon (pre-2002).</li>
    <li>IBM System/360.</li>
    <li>Accelerate Drug Development.</li>
    <li>Pratt &amp; Whitney&rsquo;s Jet Engine Design.</li>
    <li>Team of Teams.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Chapter 9:
  <ul>
    <li>NASA Space Program: Mercury, Gemini, and Apollo.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Chapter 10:
  <ul>
    <li>Toyota.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ol><h1>TOC</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#p-0">Preface</a></li>
  <li><a href="#p-1">Part I - A New Theory of Performance Management</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-1">Chapter 1 - The Pinnacles of Human Achievement and Why We Form Organizations</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-2">Chapter 2 - Navigating from Danger Zones to Winning Zones</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-3">Chapter 3 - Winning Based on Liberating Ingenuity</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-2">Part II - Slowification</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-4">Chapter 4 - Slowification: A Theory Overview</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-5">Chapter 5 - Slowification: Case Studies in Planning, Practice, and Performance</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-6">Chapter 6 - Slowification: Exemplar Case Study and Further Examination</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-3">Part III - Simplification</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-7">Chapter 7 - Simplification: A Theory Overview</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-8">Chapter 8 - Simplification: Case Studies in Incrementalization, Modularization, and Linearization</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-9">Chapter 9 - Simplification: Exemplar Case Study and Further Examination</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-4">Part IV - Amplification</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-10">Chapter 10 - Amplification: A Theory Overview and Exemplar Case Study</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-5">Conclusion</a></li>
  <li><a href="#p-6">Appendix B - Transactional vs Developmental Leadership</a></li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-0"></a>Preface</h1>
<ul>
  <li>People with the best work experiences need fewer resources, less capital equipment, and less time to accomplish greater things:
  <ul>
    <li>It is the management system.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Social circuity: the overlay of precesses, procedures, routines, and norms that enable people to do their work easily and well.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-1"></a>Part I - A New Theory of Performance Management</h1><h2><a name="ch-1"></a>Chapter 1 - The Pinnacles of Human Achievement and Why We Form Organizations</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Three mechanisms which create the difference between success and failure:
  <ol>
    <li>Slowification, to make solving problems easier to do:
    <ul>
      <li>Pulling problem-solving out of the realm of performance (operations or execution).</li>
      <li>Instead, realms of planning and practice.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Simplification, to make the problems themselves easier to solve:
    <ul>
      <li>Through incrementalization, modularization, and linearization.</li>
      <li>Aim to make Layer 1 problem-solving parallel with little coordination from Layer 3.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Amplification, to make it obvious that there are problems that demand attention and whether they&rsquo;ve been seen and solved:
    <ul>
      <li>Early and often, before problem become large and systematically disruptive.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Toyota + General Motors joint venture <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NUMMI">NUMMI</a>:
  <ul>
    <li>From worst to best with same people after changing management system.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Difference between exceptional and ordinary is obvious by observing the experiences of people doing their work.</li>
  <li>Collaborative problem-solving occurs in three distinct layers:
  <ol>
    <li>Layer 1 contains the technical objects being worked on. Code in our case.</li>
    <li>Layer 2 contains the tools.</li>
    <li>Layer 3 contains the social circuitry:
    <ul>
      <li>Workers have what they need, when they need it, and in the format they need it.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol>
  <ul>
    <li>Layer 1 and 2 are the &ldquo;technical&rdquo; part of a sociotechnical system. Layer 3 is the &ldquo;socio&rdquo; part.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-2"></a>Chapter 2 - Navigating from Danger Zones to Winning Zones</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Boundary of a group solving problems must be large enough that it is coherent, having all the people and resources needed, but small enough to not require large amounts of coordination.</li>
  <li>Coherent:
  <ul>
    <li>Having the quality of a unified whole.</li>
    <li>In the same group, communicating directly with the needed frequency, speed, accuracy and detail required.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Coupling:
  <ul>
    <li>When changes in one affect the other.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>How much coupling there is determines how much coherence leaders must create.</li>
  <li>Bad:
  <ul>
    <li>Over coupled and under partitioned.</li>
    <li>Under coupled and over partitioned.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Estimates for the time (to remove furniture) is nearly always wrong:
  <ul>
    <li>First, they try to create a more accurate schedule by getting better information.</li>
    <li>Then, try to help by finding from others teams who doesn&rsquo;t seem too busy.</li>
    <li>This makes matters much worse.</li>
    <li>Now had two problems instead of one.</li>
    <li>Instead: keep people that are good at dealing with trickier issues in reserve.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-3"></a>Chapter 3 - Winning Based on Liberating Ingenuity</h2>
<ul>
  <li>To slowify or not is a choice that leaders make.</li>
  <li>To make things simpler, aim to no need to coordinate with anyone outside the team.</li>
  <li>Recursive modularization:
  <ul>
    <li>Work was increasingly able to be performed and improved in parallel.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Linearization does for sequential processes what modularization does for parallel processes.</li>
  <li>Flawed wiring: talking to the wrong people, at the wrong time, in the wrong way, about the wrong things.</li>
  <li>Wiring also dictates the type of feedback that is generated.</li>
  <li>Model line:
  <ul>
    <li>Transformative tool.</li>
    <li>Segment of the larger enterprise where new approaches can be tested.</li>
    <li>Small but coherent.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Change their behaviours, which is a precursor for changing their beliefs.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-2"></a>Part II - Slowification</h1><h2><a name="ch-4"></a>Chapter 4 - Slowification: A Theory Overview</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Slowification is applied in one of two ways:
  <ol>
    <li>Slowing ourselves down, so we can be more deliberative and self-reflective.</li>
    <li>Slowing down the environment.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>When we have more time, lower stakes, and less fear, our creativity can flourish.</li>
  <li>When using System 1 (fast thinking):
  <ul>
    <li>We use only what we already know.</li>
    <li>Does not encourage or allow time to improve our thinking.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Three phases of work:
  <ol>
    <li>Planning:
    <ul>
      <li>Safest environment.</li>
      <li>Cost of expressing and capturing ideas is low.</li>
      <li>Allow for slowification.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Practice:
    <ul>
      <li>Preproduction/testing.</li>
      <li>Ideas are put into action.</li>
      <li>We can control the pace and the incremental complexity of what is occurring, so we are not overwhelmed.</li>
      <li>Feedback is used to find flaws and improve our plans.</li>
      <li>Time to coach and improve our abilities to execute those plans.</li>
      <li>Develop capabilities to address:
      <ul>
        <li>Most likely scenarios.</li>
        <li>Less likely but highly consequential scenarios.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol>
  <ul>
    <li>Allow for slowification.</li>
  </ul>
  <ol>
    <li>Performance:</li>
  </ol>
  <ul>
    <li>It controls the pace of the experience.</li>
    <li>Force us to depend on already-developed routines, skills, and habits.</li>
    <li>Bring issues back to practice or planning.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Common element to slowification is feedback.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-5"></a>Chapter 5 - Slowification: Case Studies in Planning, Practice, and Performance</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Deming&rsquo;s learning cycle of Plan-Do-Study-Act is a tool to encourage slowification.</li>
  <li>Leaders must capture the lessons learned to create an ever-improving baseline.</li>
  <li>&ldquo;Pause time&rdquo; culture to figure out what the problem is.</li>
  <li>Stress-testing their systems during practice sessions.</li>
  <li>Compliance leadership expect that instructions are followed without question.</li>
  <li>In learning leadership, plans are treated as best guesses and are subject to forceful backup.</li>
  <li>Training on speaking up directly, fostering psychologically safe conditions for others to speak up.</li>
  <li>Certain engineers were marked as either &ldquo;abducted by aliens&rdquo; or &ldquo;killed by zombies&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>An often-overlooked area of testing is business process and communications.</li>
  <li>Most often, stress testing discovered weak points in the Layer 3 social circuitry of their operations.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-6"></a>Chapter 6 - Slowification: Exemplar Case Study and Further Examination</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Knowledge capture and the potential for continued progress are never-ending.</li>
  <li>Book of lessons learned.</li>
  <li>How often and well do we capture lessons learned in a way that is easy to access?</li>
  <li>How often are incorporated into future planning and used in future practice?</li>
  <li>Knowledge can also be captured as code.</li>
  <li>Knowledge capture can be conveyed in routines.</li>
  <li>A learning leader are more concerned with asking the question and listening to their team.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-3"></a>Part III - Simplification</h1><h2><a name="ch-7"></a>Chapter 7 - Simplification: A Theory Overview</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Partitioning large systems into smaller, coherent pieces allow to solve more problems independently and in parallel.</li>
  <li>A coherent component often requires teams to be cross-functional.</li>
  <li>When a coherent unit is decoupled from others, disruptions in one don&rsquo;t spill over.</li>
  <li>Three simplification techniques:
  <ol>
    <li>Incrementalization:
    <ul>
      <li>Partition what is novel (which needs to be tested) from what is known (which is already validated) into their own self-contained, coherent units.</li>
      <li>Adds to the novelty in smaller increments.</li>
      <li>Allow to iterate and test changes on fewer factors, so more quickly and safely.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Modularization:
    <ul>
      <li>Smaller, simpler, more numerous coherent pieces.</li>
      <li>Less coupled as they are connected through only a few well-defined and stable interfaces.</li>
      <li>Creates option value: decouple (temporally) decisions tomorrow from conditions today, giving latitude of action to decision-makers.</li>
      <li>Downsides:
      <ul>
        <li>Potential incompatibility.</li>
        <li>Misspecification at the interfaces.</li>
        <li>Inability to change the interface when it proves to be inadequate.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Leader has the Layer 3 responsibility to balance independence of action with ensuring enough compatibility that all integrate into a cohesive whole.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Linearization:
    <ul>
      <li>Assembly line.</li>
      <li>Partitions operations that share resources to accomplish multiple objectives into independent and coherent workflows.</li>
      <li>Coherence is achieved by committing all resources needed to generate outputs to workflows.</li>
      <li>Partitioning across workflows is achieved by preventing the sharing of resources between them.</li>
      <li>Partitioning within workflows is achieved by defining hand-offs between steps.</li>
      <li>4 elements:
      <ol>
        <li>Sequentialization: outputs are generated along the single dedicated, non-looping pathway of connected activities.</li>
        <li>Standardization: output, steps/activities, handoffs and how work is done in each individual activity.</li>
        <li>Stabilization: triggers when there is a problem and resources to swarm it.</li>
        <li>Self-synchronization: system can automatically self-pace without elaborate scheduling.</li>
      </ol></li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>People can focus on a small number of novel items in a small number of projects and interact with the smallest number of people necessary.</li>
  <li>Ideally, there should be coordinated collaboration among those whose work depends on or is depended on by others:
  <ul>
    <li>However, too often, coordination is done only &ldquo;at the top of the silo&rdquo;.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Nonlinearized flows need considerably more Layer 3 coordination.</li>
  <li>Managing how work is performed at the bottleneck is much simpler and more effective than scheduling the entire factory.</li>
  <li>Linearization is also essential in high-speed, sustained improvement.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-8"></a>Chapter 8 - Simplification: Case Studies in Incrementalization, Modularization, and Linearization</h2>
<ul>
  <li>They believed they couldn&rsquo;t think their way to the right answer; instead, they experimented relentlessly with great frequency and at low cost.</li>
  <li>Breaking large problems into smaller pieces, around which it is easier to experiment and learn.</li>
  <li>Nokia engineers took over 48 hours to compile the Symbian OS, and two week to get a software build that could run on a prototype.</li>
  <li><a name="center-out"></a>Center-out leadership:
  <ul>
    <li>Collect as much information as they can get and push it out to those running local operations.</li>
    <li>Then delegate authority to local leaders to generate solutions that work for their unique situations.</li>
    <li>Then gather local lessons and synthesize them into shareable, collective wisdom.</li>
    <li>Useful when operational responsibility is distributed or when work happens in coherent local units that do not affect each other.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Amazon pre-2002:
  <ul>
    <li>To change the ordering process, the digital teams would walk to the 80 different ordering teams and say &ldquo;We need to change this&rdquo;. The ordering teams would respond that they hadn&rsquo;t budgeted for it.</li>
    <li>SKU changes caused many global outages.</li>
    <li>Hire more project managers to help coordinate the work.</li>
    <li>Put in more approval processes in an attempt to reduce outages.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Ruth Malan: As the complexity of the system increases, so do the cognitive demands on the organization. Managing cognitive load through teams with clear responsibilities and boundaries is a distinguishing focus of effective team design.</li>
  <li>Stabilization mechanism: they assigned only enough work to account for 85% of their colleagues&rsquo; time.</li>
  <li>Linearized processes can be fragile:
  <ul>
    <li>Without various stabilization mechanisms, they can quickly devolve into &ldquo;job shops&rdquo;.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-9"></a>Chapter 9 - Simplification: Exemplar Case Study and Further Examination</h2>
<ul>
  <li>By having clarity around how these technical subsystems interact at Layer 1, orgs can be formed on how they should interact in Layer 3.</li>
  <li>Design requires isomorphism between Layers 1 and 3. Production requires isomorphism in all three layers:
  <ul>
    <li>If there is a mismatch, orgs underperform.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>If effectively run orgs, the functional leader is responsible for &ldquo;who&rdquo; and &ldquo;how&rdquo; - providing trainer people.</li>
  <li>The flow owner is responsible for:
  <ul>
    <li>The &ldquo;what&rdquo; and &ldquo;when&rdquo; of how those people are deployed.</li>
    <li>Establish what outputs.</li>
    <li>Work is sequenced properly.</li>
    <li>Balance cycle times and work load.</li>
    <li>Exchanges and handoffs between steps are well established.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>All-at-once leadership:
  <ul>
    <li>Must hold in their heads the entire Layer 1 system for which they are responsible and must coordinate nearly everyone and everything in Layer 3.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Incremental leadership:
  <ul>
    <li>Maintain comm channels and mechanism of knowledge sharing.</li>
    <li>Partition novel from validated and ensuring experiments are being conducted rigorously and frequently.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-4"></a>Part IV - Amplification</h1><h2><a name="ch-10"></a>Chapter 10 - Amplification: A Theory Overview and Exemplar Case Study</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Amplification is the act of calling out problems loudly and consistently enough so help is triggered to swarm them.</li>
  <li>Control theory addresses a broad variety of situations where no static plan can achieve the desired goal, no matter how good the plan is:
  <ul>
    <li>Feedback mechanisms are needed.</li>
    <li>It can fail because of delays and imprecision.</li>
    <li>Must be significantly faster and more reliable than the object being controlled.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Layer 3 processes and procedures must integrate signaling that should be frequent enough, fast enough, accurate enough, and loud enough.
  <ul>
    <li>Signaling must be designed well and deliberately.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Six steps of amplification:
  <ol>
    <li>Sender generates signal:
    <ul>
      <li>Fail: People become indifferent, when they point out problems that are never fixed, or help is requested but never arrives.</li>
      <li>NASA culture: call out and examine anything anomalous or unexpected, and study it until it could be explained.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Sender transmits signal:
    <ul>
      <li>Fail: People recognize a problem but do not feel safe calling it out.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Receiver receives signal:
    <ul>
      <li>Simon Sinek: Communication is not about speaking what we think. It&rsquo;s about ensuring others hear what we mean.</li>
      <li>Fail: Leaders consumed with maintaining operational tempo can&rsquo;t pause long enough to develop new approaches.</li>
      <li>Apollo missions: only people allowed to communicate with astronauts in space were CAPCOMs:
      <ul>
        <li>Backup astronauts or training crew.</li>
        <li>Same training and same shared experiences allowed them to develop a highly efficient code.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Corrective reaction is started:
    <ul>
      <li>Fail: signal arrives too late.</li>
      <li>Fail: nobody reacts to signal.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Corrective reaction is completed.</li>
    <li>Sender confirms that reported problem has been solved:
    <ul>
      <li>Otherwise, they send another signal.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>In the best factories, mechanics pulled the anon cord twelve times a shift:
  <ul>
    <li>There were enough capable team leaders to consistently provide help.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Accident investigations that stop at &ldquo;human error&rdquo; are not just bad but dangerous.</li>
  <li>Toyota&rsquo;s policy of &ldquo;global localization&rdquo;: building where it sells and buying where it builds.</li>
  <li>Exemplar case study:
  <ul>
    <li>One vehicle per minute.</li>
    <li>Varied and complex work.</li>
    <li>Several thousand employees.</li>
    <li>On-site suppliers.</li>
    <li>One team leader for every four or so associates doing direct work:
    <ul>
      <li>Primary job is to help associates when they encounter problems.</li>
      <li>Deliberate inversion of who was responsible.</li>
      <li>Ratio depends on technical sophistication of the work, and the frequency and severity with which problems occur.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>President:
    <ul>
      <li>Spend several hours a day on the shop floor.</li>
      <li>See the nuance and detail of what is actually occurring.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Stopping the line was routine:
    <ul>
      <li>Short pause, associates tidy the work area.</li>
      <li>Long pauses: improvement activities or training.</li>
      <li>Back-shop teams use the time to do maintenance and repair.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>62 problem-solving stations:
    <ul>
      <li>Each focused in one big problem.</li>
      <li>Shared by both shifts, collaborating continually.</li>
      <li>Clear visibility.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Standards make succeeding easier; they make it more obvious that something is difficult or even wrong.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-5"></a>Conclusion</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Successes are fantastic, yet often without obvious evidence of leadership involvement:
  <ul>
    <li>Leadership was everywhere in planning and practice.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Both DevOps and TPS have the commonality of being developed to create conditions in which it is easier for individuals to succeed at what they do and have their efforts contribute seamlessly to a much larger whole.</li>
  <li>When we consider that the most precious resource in any organization is people&rsquo;s ingenuity and creativity, the most common risk is cognitive overload.</li>
  <li>3 questions to get started:
  <ol>
    <li>Are we solving our toughest problems in planning and practice, where we can iterate and learn?</li>
    <li>Are we shaping our problems so that they are easier to solve because they are simple, low risk, controllable, and easy to understand and iterate and learn from?</li>
    <li>Are we calling out problems loudly and consistently so that they can be swarmed, container, solved and prevent future occurrences?</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-6"></a>Appendix B - Transactional vs Developmental Leadership</h1>
<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th> </th>
      <th>Transactional orientation </th>
      <th>Developmental orientation </th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Limit </td>
      <td>Scare resources </td>
      <td>Useful understanding of resources&rsquo; best possible use </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Actions </td>
      <td>Optimization by allocation of scarce resources to best possible use </td>
      <td>Make it quicker and easier to solve difficult problems better </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>People has to adapt to the system </td>
      <td>The system has to adapt to the people </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>How increase output </td>
      <td>More resources </td>
      <td>Better problem-solving </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<ul>
  <li>Transactional leaders focus on the process itself.</li>
  <li>Developmental mindset assumes that their limitation is insufficient understanding about how to use the resource available to them. They don&rsquo;t try to fix everything all at once.</li>
</ul>]]></description></item><item><title>Book notes: Code that fits in your head: Heuristics for Software Engineering</title><link>https://danlebrero.com/2023/11/08/code-that-fits-your-head-summary/</link><guid>https://danlebrero.com/2023/11/08/code-that-fits-your-head-summary/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><description><![CDATA[<p>These are my notes on <a href="https://amzn.to/3Hi4Y6K">Code that fits in your head: Heuristics for Software Engineering</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/ploeh">Mark Seemann</a>.</p><p>Good advise for junior and mid level devs that have to work with Object-Oriented languages.</p><p>But my favourite quote:</p>
<blockquote><p>Do yourself a favour and learn functional programming. It fits better in your head.</p>
</blockquote><h1>Key Insights</h1>
<ul>
  <li><p>Only unsuccessful software ends.</p>
  <blockquote>The act of describing a program in unambiguous detail and the act of programming are one and the same <cite>Kevlin Henney</cite>
  </blockquote></li>
  <li>SW engineering was derailed by personal computers:
  <ul>
    <li>They created a generation of self-taught programmers that grow unaware of existing SW engineering knowledge.</li>
    <li>SW engineering should make the SW dev process more <strong>regular</strong>.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Change compiler and linter warnings into errors.</li>
  <li>High-level tests should go easy on assertions.</li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t get derailed: write down your improvement ideas and move on.</li>
  <li>Explicit is better than implicit.</li>
  <li>Cyclomatic complexity is one of the rare code metrics that I find useful in practice.</li>
  <li>You can compose code in many ways, but there are more wrong ways than good ways.</li>
  <li>Good interface design considers not only what is possible, but also what should be deliberately impossible.</li>
  <li>Every time your code successfully builds, commit it.</li>
  <li>Code reviews that take more than one hour are not effective.</li>
  <li>Do not sit with the author to do a code review:
  <ul>
    <li>Author will influence the reviewer.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>The more you edit test code, the less you can trust it.</li>
  <li>Write a test to reproduce the bug.</li>
  <li>Time it takes to execute a test suite matters: Less than 10 seconds.</li>
  <li>Do yourself a favour and learn functional programming. It fits better in your head.</li>
  <li>What to log:
  <ul>
    <li>Log all impure actions but not more.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Meetings don&rsquo;t scale, documentation does.</li>
  <li>Security is like insurance.</li>
</ul><h1>TOC</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#part-1">Part I: Acceleration</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-1">Chapter 1: Art or Science?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-2">Chapter 2: Checklists</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-3">Chapter 3 - Tackling Complexity</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-4">Chapter 4 - Vertical Slice</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-5">Chapter 5 - Encapsulation</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-6">Chapter 6 - Triangulation</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-7">Chapter 7 - Decomposition</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-8">Chapter 8 - API Design</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-9">Chapter 9 - Teamwork</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-2">Part II - Sustainability</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-10">Chapter 10 - Augmenting Code</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-11">Chapter 11 - Editing Unit Tests</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-12">Chapter 12 - Troubleshooting</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-13">Chapter 13 - Separation of Concerns</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-14">Chapter 14 - Rhythm</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-15">Chapter 15 - The Usual Suspects</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-16">Chapter 16 - Tour</a></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="part-1"></a>Part I: Acceleration</h1><h2><a name="ch-1"></a>Chapter 1: Art or Science?</h2>
<ul>
  <li>How we think about SW development shapes how we work.</li>
  <li>Only unsuccessful software ends.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>The act of describing a program in unambiguous detail and the act of programming are one and the same <cite>Kevlin Henney</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
  <li>None of the metaphors fit:
  <ul>
    <li>House building:
    <ul>
      <li>Projects.</li>
      <li>Phases.</li>
      <li>Dependencies.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Garden:
    <ul>
      <li>Who grows the garden?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Craftsman:
    <ul>
      <li>Heuristics: It does not scale.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>SW engineering:
    <ul>
      <li>It was derailed by personal computers:
      <ul>
        <li>They created a generation of self-taught programmers that grow unaware of existing SW engineering  knowledge.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>The skills you need to work as a professional SW dev tend to be situational (codebase, tools, &hellip;).</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>Programming is Pop Culture <cite>Alan Kay</cite></p>
</blockquote><h2><a name="ch-2"></a>Chapter 2: Checklists</h2>
<ul>
  <li>To enable, support and liberate.
  <ul>
    <li>Not to monitor or audit.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Improve the outcome with no increase in skill.</li>
  <li>Change compiler and linter warnings into errors.
  <ul>
    <li>On existing codebases, enable one rule/namespace at a time.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>You are the technical expert, it is your job to make technical decisions, which includes internal quality decisions.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-3"></a>Chapter 3 - Tackling Complexity</h2>
<ul>
  <li>What does fit in your head.</li>
  <li>SW engineering should make the SW dev process more <strong>regular</strong>.</li>
  <li>Sustainability: balance between too much focus vs too little on value.</li>
  <li>Why is programming difficult?
  <ol>
    <li>Short-memory con hold only 4-7 pieces of information.</li>
    <li>You spend more time reading than writing code:</li>
  </ol>
  <ul>
    <li>Optimise for code readability.</li>
    <li>Every minute you invest in making the code easier to understand pays itself back tenfold.</li>
  </ul>
  <ol>
    <li>System 1 (making decision based on immediate information) vs System 2.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>You can do SW engineering without understanding Computer Science.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-4"></a>Chapter 4 - Vertical Slice</h2>
<ul>
  <li>SW eng: methodology to make sure that SW works as intended, and that stays that way.
  <ul>
    <li>As intended != solving the user problem.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Implement features with the simples possible code, but look out for duplication.</li>
  <li>Walking skeleton.</li>
  <li>Drive changes through tests.</li>
  <li>Author ignores compiler warning when writing tests because readability, but does not for production code.</li>
  <li>High-level tests should go easy on assertions:
  <ul>
    <li>Make only the essentials visible.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Author moves to unit tests with all behaviours test in green (???).</li>
  <li>DTO, Repository, Entity, equals &amp; hashcode. Very glad I left all of this behind.</li>
  <li>Manual testing from time to time is ok.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-5"></a>Chapter 5 - Encapsulation</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Trading a compile-time error for a runtime exception is a poor trade-off.</li>
  <li>Encapsulation is a contract that describes valid interactions between objects and callers.</li>
  <li>Red-green-refactor.</li>
  <li>Postel&rsquo;s Law: Be conservative in what you send, be liberal in what you accept.</li>
  <li>With immutable objects, you only need to consider validity in one place: the constructor.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-6"></a>Chapter 6 - Triangulation</h2>
<ul>
  <li>When you work with legacy code, you slowly, painstakingly commit the structure of the code base to long-term memory:
  <ul>
    <li>Information in long-term memory is harder to change, hence legacy code is harder to change.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t get derailed: write down your improvement ideas and move on.</li>
  <li>Explicit is better than implicit.</li>
  <li>Devil&rsquo;s advocate technique: try to pass test with an obviously incomplete implementation:
  <ul>
    <li>This works as a critique of your tests.</li>
    <li>When to stop? Ask &ldquo;How likely is such a regression to happen?&rdquo;</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Use only &lt; or &lt;=.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-7"></a>Chapter 7 - Decomposition</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Once the team&rsquo;s mindset has changed, the rule itself becomes redundant.</li>
  <li>Cyclomatic complexity is one of the rare code metrics that I find useful in practice.</li>
  <li>No more than 7 things should be going on in a single piece of code:
  <ul>
    <li>Each branch as one thing, so no more than cyclomatic complexity of 7.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>&ldquo;Static&rdquo; methods or methods with 0 parameters are a code smell.</li>
  <li>Parse, don&rsquo;t validate:
  <ul>
    <li>Instead of returning a bool, return either an error or a class from the domain model.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Fractal architecture:
  <ul>
    <li>Each layer/piece of code should have no more than 7 things, those things themselves being composed of no more than 7 things.</li>
    <li>Low level details should be represented as a single abstract chunk, and higher level details should be either irrelevant at that level of zoom, or otherwise explicitly visible as method parameters or injected dependencies.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Count variables to measure complexity:
  <ul>
    <li>Params + locals + class fields.</li>
    <li>Consider refactoring to Parameter Object if complexity becomes high.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>&ldquo;If you know ASP.NET &hellip;&rdquo;: In my experience with Spring, this is a big &ldquo;if&rdquo;. Spring has become a beast able to do many things, so knowing a lot of complex machinery beforehand should count somehow towards the complexity of the codebase.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-8"></a>Chapter 8 - API Design</h2>
<ul>
  <li>You can compose code in many ways, but there are more wrong ways than good ways:
  <ul>
    <li>It requires skill and taste.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Good interface design considers not only what is possible, but also what should be deliberately impossible.
  <ul>
    <li>Design APIs so that it is difficult to misuse them.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Favour specialised APIs over Swiss Army API.</li>
  <li>Remove method names from an interface and see if you can guess what they do out of the interface name + inputs + outputs.</li>
  <li>Methods with side effects should return no data (void), so makes it trivial to recognise them:
  <ul>
    <li>Does this mean throw exceptions to signal errors?</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>From best to worse communication options:
  <ol>
    <li>Types as they are check at compile time.</li>
    <li>Method names.</li>
    <li>Comments.</li>
    <li>Automated tests.</li>
    <li>Commit messages.</li>
    <li>Documentation.</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-9"></a>Chapter 9 - Teamwork</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Git: 50/72 rule
  <ul>
    <li>Headline in imperative 50 chars.</li>
    <li>Body 72 chars wide.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>CI: integrate every 4 hours.</li>
  <li>Every time your code successfully builds, commit it.</li>
  <li>Reject big PR.</li>
  <li>Code reviews that take more than one hour are not effective.</li>
  <li>Code review question: Will I be okay maintaining this?</li>
  <li>Do not sit with the author to do a code review:
  <ul>
    <li>Author will influence the reviewer.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Cheer when you see something you like.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-2"></a>Part II - Sustainability</h1><h2><a name="ch-10"></a>Chapter 10 - Augmenting Code</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Strangler pattern at the method and class level.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-11"></a>Chapter 11 - Editing Unit Tests</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The more you edit test code, the less you can trust it.</li>
  <li>You can&rsquo;t refactor unit tests.</li>
  <li>A test method having only one assertion: too simplistic.</li>
  <li>When you need to change your test code, try to do it without touching the production code.</li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t trust a test that you haven&rsquo;t seen fail:
  <ul>
    <li>Comment out production code and bring it back a piece at a time.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-12"></a>Chapter 12 - Troubleshooting</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Step 1: Try to understand what is going on:
  <ul>
    <li>Use the scientific method:
    <ol>
      <li>Make a prediction (hypothesis).</li>
      <li>Perform an experiment.</li>
      <li>Compare outcome with prediction.</li>
      <li>Goto 1 until you understand.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Delete code to simplify.</li>
  <li>Time-box the process and take breaks if no progress is made.</li>
  <li>Rubber ducking: the mere act of explaining a problem tends to produce new insights.</li>
  <li>When a bug appears, stop what you are doing and fix it.</li>
  <li>Write a test to reproduce the bug.</li>
  <li>Time it takes to execute a test suite matters: Less than 10 seconds.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-13"></a>Chapter 13 - Separation of Concerns</h2>
<ul>
  <li>You must be able to recompose what you decomposed.</li>
  <li>Nested composition:
  <ul>
    <li>Typical in OO</li>
    <li>Around side-effects:
    <ul>
      <li>You model actions.</li>
      <li>Compose by nesting.</li>
      <li>Hidden interactions: increases complexity.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Sequential composition:
  <ul>
    <li>Pipeline.</li>
    <li>No side-effects.</li>
    <li>Good, pure functions.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Push side-effects to the edge of the system.</li>
  <li>Functional programming fits better in your head.</li>
  <li>If you see an exception in the logs, treat it as a defect.</li>
  <li>What to log:
  <ul>
    <li>HTTP request + response.</li>
    <li>DB request + response.</li>
    <li>Log all impure actions but not more.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-14"></a>Chapter 14 - Rhythm</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Personal:
  <ul>
    <li>Pomodoro: time-box 25 mins, 5 min break even when in the flow.</li>
    <li>Don&rsquo;t work long hours.</li>
    <li>Meetings don&rsquo;t scale, documentation does.</li>
    <li>Learn to touch type.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Team:
  <ul>
    <li>Update dependencies regularly.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-15"></a>Chapter 15 - The Usual Suspects</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Security is like insurance.</li>
  <li>STRIDE:
  <ul>
    <li>Spoofing: try to pose as somebody else.</li>
    <li>Tampering.</li>
    <li>Repudiation: deny performing an action, like receiving an item.</li>
    <li>Information disclosure.</li>
    <li>Denial of service.</li>
    <li>Elevation of privilege.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Property base testing.</li>
  <li><a href="https://codescene.com/">Behavioural code analysis</a></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-16"></a>Chapter 16 - Tour</h2>
<ul>
  <li>File organization: put all files in one directory:
  <ul>
    <li>Break into multiple packages to enforce no cyclic dependencies.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Learn a new system from tests.</li>
</ul>]]></description></item><item><title>Book notes: Wrong fit, Right fit: Why How We Work Matters More Than Ever</title><link>https://danlebrero.com/2023/10/25/right-fit-wrong-fit-summary/</link><guid>https://danlebrero.com/2023/10/25/right-fit-wrong-fit-summary/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><description><![CDATA[<p>These are my notes on <a href="https://amzn.to/3QrhK7X">Wrong Fit, Right Fit: Why How We Work Matters More Than Ever</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/gramico">Andr Martin</a></p><p>Very interesting view on how to find your ideal job, and how companies can hire the right people: focus a lot more on how day-to-day work is done (and our preferences).</p><h1>Key Insights</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Fit: Deep and authentic connection to how a company works day-to-day.</li>
  <li>No place will be a perfect match.</li>
  <li>Working harder to fit in does not produce right fit; rather the opposite.</li>
  <li>Who a company says they are rarely matches how that company works day-to-day.</li>
  <li>Talent is &ldquo;forced&rdquo; to bump into ill-defined ways of working, use their creative energy to understand how things actually get done.</li>
  <li>Begin sharing the choice you are planning to make. If feel hesitation, doubt, or anxiety as you share there is likely something not lining up.</li>
  <li>Top 20% talent produce 80% of value.</li>
  <li>What if interviews where less like first dates and more like family reunions?</li>
  <li><a href="#ch-4">Chapter 4</a> is gold to understand yourself. Holistic Candidate Profile:
  <ol>
    <li>What are my core values?</li>
    <li>What is the life I am building?</li>
    <li>What is my craft/superpower?</li>
    <li>Who is my ideal leader?</li>
    <li>How do I like to work?</li>
    <li>What am I solving for?</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>When a product appears superior on aspects that are comparable with other products, we will fill in the gaps on missing information or difficult to ascertain attributes in a manner that supports that superiority.</li>
  <li>As an interviewee, &ldquo;How can I position myself as the best candidate for the job?&rdquo;
  <ul>
    <li>We end up &ldquo;acting&rdquo; versus &ldquo;being&rdquo;.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Most variance in satisfaction of an employee can be accounted for by their manager or leader.</li>
  <li><a href="#questions">Questions to understand ways of working in the company</a>:
  <ol>
    <li>What is the profile of the person who succeeds here?</li>
    <li>What is the reputation of the function/team you are joining?</li>
    <li>What happens here that didn&rsquo;t happen at the other companies you worked at previously?</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>New talent is highly impressionable. Make sure they are surrounded by the &ldquo;models of your culture&rdquo; early and often.</li>
  <li>Onboarding:
  <ul>
    <li>Keep a journal.</li>
    <li>90 days.</li>
    <li>To figure out if it is right fit.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#howwork">How does the company get work done?</a>
  <ol>
    <li>How does the company collaborate?
    <ul>
      <li>Most fundamental attribute of right fit.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How company assess performance?
    <ul>
      <li>Companies pay for one of:
      <ol>
        <li>Performance.</li>
        <li>Demonstrated expertise.</li>
        <li>Lived values/behaviours.</li>
        <li>Long-term commitment.</li>
      </ol></li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Who owns my career, the company or me?</li>
  <li>Our education has trained us to ignore all the positives and go straight to the places to improve.</li>
  <li>As an executive leader, how you decide to work sets the floor (minimum expectation), not the ceiling.</li>
  <li>The Fit Assessment (page 126).</li>
  <li>The later you marry, the less likely you are to divorce.</li>
  <li>Learning improves self-confidence, curb anxiety and depression.</li>
  <li>Companies that promote learning regularly outperform competitors.</li>
  <li>Try to create a week calendar that is closer to your ideal in terms of time, types of meeting, and people you work alongside.</li>
  <li>A team makes the manager, not the other way around.</li>
  <li>Individual feedback have an inverse relationship to seniority. (Should be the opposite!).</li>
  <li>If you don&rsquo;t say no, then your yes is meaningless.</li>
  <li>Culture is an outcome.</li>
  <li>With each new recruit, it gets harder to consistently teach or develop consistent unwritten practices.</li>
  <li>To know how to the company should work in the future, study the company&rsquo;s most productive teams of today:
  <ul>
    <li>Somewhere out in your company, there is a better practice for everything.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#realistic-job-preview">Realistic job preview</a>.</li>
  <li>Team membership is as much of an art as team leadership.</li>
  <li>Transition from one role to another:
  <ul>
    <li>Companies usually ask to cover for both roles:
    <ul>
      <li>More stress in an already stressful situation.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Instead:
    <ul>
      <li>7 days off to rest.</li>
      <li>7 days for reflection, reconnection and reset.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1>TOC</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#p-0">Introduction: There is a Right Fit Company Waiting for You</a></li>
  <li><a href="#p-1">Part 1: Context + Right Fit</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-1">Chapter 1: How the Workplace Has Changed</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-2">Chapter 2 - Why Right Fit Is So Rare</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-2">Part 2 - Talent + Right Fit</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-3">Chapter 3 - Beginning the Search for Right Fit</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-4">Chapter 4 - Self-Reflection and Fit Excursions</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-3">Part 3 - Interviewing and Onboarding + Right Fit</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-5">Chapter 5 - Don&rsquo;t Judge a Company by Its Career Page</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-6">Chapter 6 - Figuring Out If You Really Fit</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-4">Part 4 - Buffers + Right Fit</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-7">Chapter 7 - Inspirational Buffers and Enhancing Fit Over Time</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-8">Chapter 8 - Relational Buffers and Enhancing Fit Over Time</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#p-5">Part 5 - Company + Right Fit</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-9">Chapter 9 - Crafting and Communicating How the Company Works</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-10">Chapter 10 - Reimagining Fit - Recruiting and (Re)recruiting for Right Fit</a></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-0"></a>Introduction: There is a Right Fit Company Waiting for You</h1>
<ul>
  <li>What if it isn&rsquo;t about changing how we work, but rather improving our chances of creating and finding a better fit?</li>
  <li>Book based on 65 in-depth interviews, all level and different company sizes.</li>
  <li>Fit:
  <ul>
    <li>Deep and authentic connection to how a company works day-to-day.</li>
    <li>Days feel easy, work is meaningful and connection with company grows exponentially.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Ways of working is innate in the fabric of the company and often emanate from early days:
  <ul>
    <li>How prioritize work, solve problems, innovate, manage conflict, socialize projects.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Way of working often undervalued during recruitment.</li>
  <li>Pressure during interview to &ldquo;fit in&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>Three key misalignments:
  <ol>
    <li>Total mismatch: &ldquo;Nobody at the company looks like me or works like me&rdquo;.</li>
    <li>Person mismatch: &ldquo;Nobody at the company looks like me, but many people work how I prefer to work&rdquo;.</li>
    <li>Way of working mismatch: &ldquo;People look like me but nobody works the way I prefer to work&rdquo;.</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-1"></a>Part 1: Context + Right Fit</h1><h2><a name="ch-1"></a>Chapter 1: How the Workplace Has Changed</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Great Resignation:
  <ul>
    <li>2022, 77% of talent resigns within the first three years. 45% within one year.</li>
    <li>Survey: Of 2000 US employees with less than 6 month at the company, 50% are actively looking for something new.</li>
    <li>2020:
    <ul>
      <li>PwC estimated 65% employees are looking for a new job.</li>
      <li>Gallup estimated $7.8 trillion of productivity loss due to disengaged employees.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>As human being, we want to be part of a community and be committed to something bigger than ourselves.</li>
  <li>Trends:
  <ol>
    <li>Rise of the culture deck:
    <ul>
      <li>Netflix started it.</li>
      <li>Brand campaigns made culture aspirational and the day-to-day climate less and less of a priority.</li>
      <li>More adept to talking about culture than doing.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>The Ping-Pong table of purposeless perks:
    <ul>
      <li>Clarity about what actually matters was being clouded by more and more stuff.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>The decade of decedent growth:
    <ul>
      <li>2009 to 2020 marked the longest economic expansion in the last 80 years.</li>
      <li>Habits are formed that dont help in tougher times.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>A crisis of commitment:
    <ul>
      <li>With the abundance that surrounds us, we have entered into a constant state of infinite browsing where we strive to &ldquo;keep our options open&rdquo; over &ldquo;the option to choose to dedicate ourselves to&rdquo;.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>The side hustle economy:
    <ul>
      <li>46% americans took on a side hustle to cover their monthly budget.</li>
      <li>Formal employers are getting the rest of us, not the best of us.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Being more vs doing more:
    <ul>
      <li>Does what I am doing matter?</li>
      <li>2017 study: found that 41% of a typical knowledge worker task don&rsquo;t add value.</li>
      <li>Not simply doing less, but better connect all the things we do to a higher purpose.</li>
      <li>When we are inspired, we have a nearly insatiable energy to create.</li>
      <li>Proximity can accelerate work.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>If youre talent, maybe its time to start searching for a place you can love day-to-day in balance with searching for a position you can do or a brand you revere.</li>
  <li>If you&rsquo;re a leader, create an experience that fits those who &ldquo;love what we love&rdquo; as opposed to either allowing many cultures under one umbrella or trying to create a place where everyone can be, on average, not unhappy.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-2"></a>Chapter 2 - Why Right Fit Is So Rare</h2>
<ul>
  <li>World Health Organization definition of burnout: a syndrome resulting from workplace stress that has not been successfully managed.
  <ul>
    <li>Three dimensions:
    <ul>
      <li>Feeling of energy depletion.</li>
      <li>Increased mental distance or negative feeling about one&rsquo;s job.</li>
      <li>Reduced professional efficacy.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Cost of labor is typically 70% of operating budget.</li>
  <li>Cognitive dissonance:
  <ul>
    <li>Discomfort of making a choice or acting in a manner that is incongruent with one&rsquo;s stated values, opinions or preferences.</li>
    <li>Begin sharing the choice you are planning to make. If feel hesitation, doubt, or anxiety as you share there is likely something not lining up.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Approach and Avoidance Systems:
  <ul>
    <li>Avoidance system: stop us from doing thing that put us in danger.</li>
    <li>Approach system:
    <ul>
      <li>Pleasure-based desires.</li>
      <li>Pleasure now and pain later.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>When choosing a job, approach system can overtake the avoidance system.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>BIRG-ing and Fit:
  <ul>
    <li>BIRG-ing:
    <ul>
      <li>Basking in reflected glory.</li>
      <li>Using others&rsquo; success to boost our own self-image.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>CORF-ing:
    <ul>
      <li>Cutting off reflected failure.</li>
      <li>Distance ourselves from failure.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Football: we won vs they lost.</li>
    <li>Choosing a job for BIRG-ing.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Fit is not about fitting in.
  <ul>
    <li>In wrong fit, we end up using our creative energy to &ldquo;fit in&rdquo;.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Do I fit here?</li>
</ul><p><img src="/images/blog/books/wrong-fit-right-fit/do-i-fit-here.jpeg" alt="Do I fit here?" /></p><h1><a name="p-2"></a>Part 2 - Talent + Right Fit</h1><h2><a name="ch-3"></a>Chapter 3 - Beginning the Search for Right Fit</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Researchers were able to prove that there is no standard bell curve when it comes to performance.
  <ul>
    <li>Top 20% talent produce 80% of value.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>82% of Fortune 500 executive said they do not recruit highly talented people. 93% don&rsquo;t believe they develop people fast and effectively.</li>
  <li>What if interviews where less like first dates and more like family reunions?</li>
  <li>Holistic Candidate Profile:
  <ol>
    <li>What are my core values?</li>
    <li>What is the life I am building?</li>
    <li>What is my craft/superpower?</li>
    <li>Who is my ideal leader?</li>
    <li>How do I like to work?</li>
    <li>What am I solving for?</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Realistic Experience Preview:
  <ol>
    <li>What are our lived values?</li>
    <li>What promise do we make to talent?</li>
    <li>How do we make money/have an impact?</li>
    <li>What is the profile of your leader?</li>
    <li>What is the job the next 12-18 months?</li>
    <li>What are the principles, practices, and platforms that define how work gets done?</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-4"></a>Chapter 4 - Self-Reflection and Fit Excursions</h2><p>For talent, 8 core question. This chapter contains one &ldquo;Excursion&rdquo;/exercise to help you answer them.</p>
<ol>
  <li>What are the values you most consistently hold?
  <ul>
    <li>Pick from pairs of values.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>What is the life you are trying to build?
  <ul>
    <li>In two years time, what if:
    <ul>
      <li>Nothing changed.</li>
      <li>Dream the dream.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>What are your superpowers? What are you best at (vs what do you love to do)?
  <ul>
    <li>Superpowers:
    <ul>
      <li>What gaps do you fill in every company you have joined?</li>
      <li>What areas of expertise are you attempting to hone?</li>
      <li>What do people come to you for?</li>
      <li>What activities do you volunteer to take?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Shadow side:
    <ul>
      <li>Often from overused strengths or non-productive behaviours when under stress.</li>
      <li>When under stress for long period, we flip into &ldquo;the grip&rdquo; <a href="https://www.psychologyjunkie.com/what-youre-like-during-grip-stress-based-on-your-myers-briggs-personality-type/">(Myers Briggs)</a>: unfamiliar and unproductive version of ourselves.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Are you of craft, company or cause?</li>
  <li>Who is your ideal leader? What do you need from them to succeed?
  <ul>
    <li>Good chemistry with a manager is so important and so rare that many successful talent and leadership experts advocate for following a great manager.</li>
    <li>Things that we look for in our managers, will be gifted at ourselves.</li>
    <li>We gain our skills as managers from our managers.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>If you were to start a company, what would you do? How would you want it to feel?</li>
  <li>Above all else, what matters most to you right now? What are you solving for?
  <ul>
    <li>Our careers can be central to our life in some moments, and they can be enablers of our life in others.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>How to you bring all of your answers together into a single leadership story?
  <ul>
    <li>At the heart of finding right fit is changing the frame of how you see yourself.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ol><h1><a name="p-3"></a>Part 3 - Interviewing and Onboarding + Right Fit</h1><h2><a name="ch-5"></a>Chapter 5 - Don&rsquo;t Judge a Company by Its Career Page</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motivated_reasoning">Motivated reasoning</a>: When the early signals we get about a product or a place are positive and hold true, we will likely stop our search for new information or comparisons to other options.</li>
  <li>When a product appears superior on aspects that are comparable with other products, we will fill in the gaps on missing information or difficult to ascertain attributes in a manner that supports that superiority.</li>
  <li>Confirmation bias: potentially confirmatory evidence tends to be taken at face value while potentially dis-confirmatory evidence is subjected to critical and skeptical scrutiny.</li>
  <li>Information available about a company is &ldquo;mostly true version of the truth&rdquo;:
  <ul>
    <li>Doesn&rsquo;t give enough information to really see the cracks that every company has.</li>
    <li>Employer-brand version of Snapchat filters.</li>
    <li>Most sources are internally produced and relatively subjective.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Rules to validate information:
  <ol>
    <li>More than three sources.</li>
    <li>Internal and external materials.</li>
    <li>Subjective and objective data.</li>
    <li>If something feels off, dive deeper. Don&rsquo;t ignore it.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>As an interviewee:
  <ul>
    <li>&ldquo;How can I position myself as the best candidate for the job?&rdquo;
    <ul>
      <li>The very nature of the question can lead us astray.</li>
      <li>We end up &ldquo;acting&rdquo; versus &ldquo;being&rdquo;.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a name="questions"></a>Questions to understand ways of working in the company:
  <ol>
    <li>What is the profile of the person who succeeds here?
    <ul>
      <li>Learn how the company defines success.</li>
      <li>Ask interviewer to tell you about a real person.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How does the company get work done? (chapter 6)</li>
    <li>What is the company&rsquo;s relationship to time?
    <ul>
      <li>Most important.</li>
      <li>Productivity equals full calendar?</li>
      <li>Is unlimited vacation really unlimited?</li>
      <li>Do you need to be at the office or in a meeting to be deemed productive?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>What is the reputation of the function/team you are joining?</li>
    <li>What are your day-to-day duties?
    <ul>
      <li>What will be the first three deliverables be once onboarding is complete?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How does the leader get productivity out of their team?
    <ul>
      <li>Most variance in satisfaction of an employee can be accounted for by their manager or leader.</li>
      <li>Study by Artz et al. found that technical competence mattered above else.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Where do people go once they leave this job/team/leader?
    <ul>
      <li>Most underrated skill as a leader is being a &ldquo;star maker&rdquo;.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>What happens here that didn&rsquo;t happen at the other companies you worked at previously?
    <ul>
      <li>Whether the culture has been solidified enough to turn into longstanding and unique practices.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>What are the nonnegotiables at the company?
    <ul>
      <li>How consistent are across interviews?</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-6"></a>Chapter 6 - Figuring Out If You Really Fit</h2>
<ul>
  <li>To find right fit, you should spend your first ninety days focused on understanding the reality of how the company truly works day-to-day and assessing that against your preferences.</li>
  <li>New talent is highly impressionable. Make sure they are surrounded by the &ldquo;models of your culture&rdquo; early and often.</li>
  <li>Fitting in is shifting away from your natural preference to be included or feel sense of belonging. This is a normal reaction to starting a new job.</li>
  <li>Most companies rarely fully understand or know how to articulate how work actually gets done.</li>
  <li>Three versions of a company:
  <ol>
    <li>The company we would be if we were at our best:
    <ul>
      <li>Recruiter version to sell the position.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>What is shown to talent on their first day:
    <ul>
      <li>Akin to being toured through a museum.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How it is for most people, every day.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>As talent, onboarding:
  <ul>
    <li>Is about determining right or wrong fit.</li>
    <li>Rules:
    <ol>
      <li>Avoid snap judgments: take the full 90 days.</li>
      <li>Keep a journal.</li>
      <li>Review what you have learned at day 10, 30, 60 and 90:
      <ul>
        <li>Patterns and themes.</li>
        <li>Share with your manager/mentor.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Let the facts lead you to your conclusions, not the other way around.</li>
      <li>Focus your assessment on the ways the company works.</li>
      <li>Make a decision to commit, or not:
      <ul>
        <li>Most important and difficult without a framework.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Create buffers to sustain right fit as the company grows/transforms.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a name="howwork"></a>How does the company get work done?
  <ol>
    <li>How does the company make decisions?
    <ul>
      <li>Tradeoffs made. Is everything a priority?</li>
      <li>Is there a clearly defined strategy that people can make decisions in alignment with?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How does the company solve problems?
    <ul>
      <li>What information is most valuable when determining the best solution?</li>
      <li>Best companies use approach depending on the size and complexity or company values.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How are ideas communicated?
    <ul>
      <li>Full sentences or pithy one-liners?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How does the company collaborate?
    <ul>
      <li>Most fundamental attribute of right fit.</li>
      <li>Area that diverges the most from team to team.</li>
      <li>Pay attention to:
      <ul>
        <li>Meeting culture.</li>
        <li>Primary tools used to communicate.</li>
        <li>Cadence of work.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How company assess performance?
    <ul>
      <li>Output, outcomes, strength of relationships, time in your seat or billed hours?</li>
      <li>Companies pay for one of:
      <ol>
        <li>Performance.</li>
        <li>Demonstrated expertise.</li>
        <li>Lived values/behaviours.</li>
        <li>Long-term commitment.</li>
      </ol></li>
      <li>To understand your own beliefs, look back at the classes you most enjoyed in school:
      <ul>
        <li>How did you get graded?</li>
        <li>Work alone or in groups?</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How does the company provide feedback?
    <ul>
      <li>Open, honest and consistent feedback is a rarity.</li>
      <li>We are fairly self-centered and idiosyncratic in our measurements, and thus our assessment is ultimately random and potentially damaging.</li>
      <li>Our education has trained us to ignore all the positives and go straight to the places to improve.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How does the company resolve conflict and break ties?
    <ul>
      <li>Are purpose, values or principles used?</li>
      <li>Full commitment or &ldquo;disagree and commit&rdquo;?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How company develops its talent?
    <ul>
      <li>Turning key events into lessons takes self-awareness, feedback, coaching, learning and testing out new behaviours, things that most companies fail to invest in.</li>
      <li>Who owns my career, the company or me?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How does information flow?
    <ul>
      <li>Tells where decisions get made.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How does the company socialize/gather?
    <ul>
      <li>What does the company celebrate?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>What is the company&rsquo;s relationship with time?
    <ul>
      <li>When on vacation, are I still available or unreachable?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How does the company view rest and recovery?
    <ul>
      <li>Do leaders take vacation quietly, or are they vocal about taking breaks?</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>No place will be a perfect match.</li>
  <li>As an executive leader, how you decide to work sets the floor (minimum expectation), not the ceiling.</li>
  <li>The Fit Assessment (page 126).</li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-4"></a>Part 4 - Buffers + Right Fit</h1><h2><a name="ch-7"></a>Chapter 7 - Inspirational Buffers and Enhancing Fit Over Time</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Great fit now doesn&rsquo;t guarantee that it will remain that way.</li>
  <li>Wrong fit is rarely sustainable for an extended period.</li>
  <li>Buffers to fit:
  <ul>
    <li>Actions to improve the overall experience over time.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Two categories:
  <ol>
    <li>Inspirational:
    <ul>
      <li>Those that connect us to something more meaningful.</li>
      <li>Increase better and more value-adding work.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Relational: center around people who we interact with.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>The later you marry, the less likely you are to divorce.</li>
  <li><a href="https://hbr.org/2013/04/does-money-really-affect-motiv">Correlation of pay to satisfaction is very weak</a>.</li>
  <li>Intrinsic motivations FTW!</li>
  <li>Inspirational buffers:
  <ol>
    <li>Connect to Purpose or Cause:
    <ul>
      <li>Company: why is the world better with us in it?</li>
      <li>Try to connect to the company purpose at least once a week.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Increase Meaningful Work, Decrease Busy Work:
    <ul>
      <li>Two ways:
      <ol>
        <li>Align nature of work:
        <ul>
          <li>To your passions.</li>
          <li>Learn new skills.</li>
          <li>Connect to a cause you care.</li>
        </ul></li>
        <li>Spend more time in high-value activities.</li>
      </ol></li>
      <li>Once people know you are passionate in something, they will give you plenty of opportunity to do it.</li>
      <li>Say &ldquo;no&rdquo; more. Volunteer more.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>If you are learning and growing:
    <ul>
      <li>Learning improves self-confidence, curb anxiety and depression.</li>
      <li>Companies that promote learning regularly outperform competitors.</li>
      <li>Five clusters of learning opportunities:
      <ol>
        <li>Challenging assignments.</li>
        <li>Developmental relationships (mentors, teachers, managers).</li>
        <li>Hardships or adverse situations (wrong fit).</li>
        <li>Coursework and training.</li>
        <li>Personal experiences (birth of child, living in a new country).</li>
      </ol></li>
      <li>Majority of learning come from 1 and 2. Least from 4.</li>
      <li>Learning takes work: reflection, making connections to previous events, practicing new behaviours.</li>
      <li>Diversity of experience matters.</li>
      <li>Hardship often brings out the most raw version of ourselves.</li>
      <li>Treat every day as a prototype (== small experiment).</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Find a consumer in need that you can relate to and can help.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>In any project, ask if the consumer would pay an extra 5% for the work.</li>
  <li>Make better use of your time: 41% activities are neither personally fulfilling nor add value.</li>
  <li>Procrastination:
  <ul>
    <li>More during stress.</li>
    <li>Losing time on the tasks at had due to our urgent need to &ldquo;manage negative emotions&rdquo;.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Working harder to fit in does not produce right fit; rather the opposite.</li>
  <li>Try to create a week calendar that is closer to your ideal in terms of time, types of meeting, and people you work alongside.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-8"></a>Chapter 8 - Relational Buffers and Enhancing Fit Over Time</h2>
<ul>
  <li>4 Buffers:
  <ol>
    <li>A supportive leader/manager:
    <ul>
      <li>Look at how you can shape your manager to the one that you need.</li>
      <li>A team makes the manager, not the other way around.</li>
      <li>Positive reinforcement.</li>
      <li>Individual feedback have an inverse relationship to seniority.
      <ul>
        <li>It should be the opposite as the stakes are higher!</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Managers understand if their teams are performing, but they know very little about the why.</li>
      <li>Researcher found that managers estimate their impact way higher than their reporters.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Meaningful mentor:
    <ul>
      <li>70% of talent who have a mentor are satisfied with their jobs.</li>
      <li>Mentors create connections, and connections are the seeds of commitment.</li>
      <li>3 types:
      <ol>
        <li>Storytellers: those who have been in the company for many years.</li>
        <li>Models: bleed the mission and values of the company.</li>
        <li>Masters of craft.
        <ul>
          <li>Rarely in the top leadership positions, very rarely used as mentors.</li>
        </ul></li>
      </ol></li>
      <li>Think what are you looking for in a mentor (career advise, connections, &hellip;)</li>
      <li>Agenda should be question based and focused on real areas where you are struggling or looking for wisdom.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Workplace BFF or Doppelganger:
    <ul>
      <li>Good social relationships are one of the most consistent predictors of a happy life.</li>
      <li>Doppelganger:
      <ul>
        <li>Somebody like you but that moves through the org with greater ease.</li>
        <li>Represent future possibilities.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Invest your time in the relationship.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Life outside work is magic:
    <ul>
      <li>If you don&rsquo;t say no, then your yes is meaningless. Peter Block.</li>
      <li>The happier we are at home, the more engaged and committed we will be at work.</li>
      <li>Don&rsquo;t let your outside work hours be filled with sensory pursuits.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h1><a name="p-5"></a>Part 5 - Company + Right Fit</h1><h2><a name="ch-9"></a>Chapter 9 - Crafting and Communicating How the Company Works</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Employee experience:
  <ul>
    <li>All the touch points an employee has with the company in a single year:</li>
    <li>Physical, human, digital and administrative.</li>
    <li>Excludes &ldquo;culture&rdquo;. Culture is an outcome.</li>
    <li>3 elements:
    <ol>
      <li>Work principles:
      <ul>
        <li>How it should feel to work in a team.</li>
        <li>What differentiates the company.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Work practices: chapter 4.</li>
      <li>Work platforms: the technology used to do work.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>With each new recruit, it gets harder to consistently teach or develop consistent unwritten practices.</li>
  <li>Creating <em>Right Fit</em> doesn&rsquo;t mean being the right place for everyone.</li>
  <li>To know how to the company should work in the future, study the company&rsquo;s most productive teams of today:
  <ul>
    <li>Make consistent what has already been innovated on.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Research: people make judgements within a fraction of a second upon seeing a person&rsquo;s face.</li>
  <li>Balance first impression is key: both who the company is today and what want to be tomorrow.</li>
  <li>Tips:
  <ol>
    <li>Make values the ground and work principles/practices/platforms the figure.</li>
    <li>Purpose and how it makes money overt.</li>
    <li>Show the real company in real ways.</li>
    <li>Create a network.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li><a name="realistic-job-preview"></a>Realistic job preview:
  <ol>
    <li>Nonnegotiables: set the base at a certain level.</li>
    <li>What we do:
    <ul>
      <li>How the product/service flows through the system.</li>
      <li>Focus on how the role adds value.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>How we work:
    <ul>
      <li>Be super clear about how work gets done.</li>
      <li>Prose-based work principles, practices and platforms.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>What capabilities we need.</li>
    <li>The three top deliverables for this position or this team:
    <ul>
      <li>In the next eighteen to twenty-four months.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-10"></a>Chapter 10 - Reimagining Fit - Recruiting and (Re)recruiting for Right Fit</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Onboarding:
  <ul>
    <li>A company will never have a more excited or engaged employee than the moment they walk into their first day.</li>
    <li>If a company just focuses on the new joiners, their culture will transform automatically over the next few years:
    <ul>
      <li>Turnover + growth.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Anything the company spends on onboarding will be far less expensive than the hidden cost of losing new employees within their first six months.</li>
    <li>Cultural immersion: what is expected, what is valued and how works get done.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Your early network will dictate much of your long-term success.</li>
  <li>Great managers are rare:
  <ul>
    <li>Gallup: companies fail to choose the right candidate 82% of time.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Team membership is as much of an art as team leadership:
  <ul>
    <li>Teach our teams &ldquo;teaming&rdquo;.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Performance as the collective act by individuals dedicated to a single mission:
  <ul>
    <li>Have one strategy:
    <ul>
      <li>Teams/individuals simply need to know their place in the strategy.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Outcomes, not activities.</li>
    <li>1-2-1 focus on ensuring everyone is growing faster than the company:
    <ul>
      <li>Moving key events to lessons of experience.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Pay well and distribute bonuses to the team.</li>
    <li>Find and celebrate the &ldquo;better practice&rdquo;:
    <ul>
      <li>Somewhere out in your company, there is a better practice for everything.</li>
      <li>Positive disobedient.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Ensure strategy is participated in, not just developed:
  <ul>
    <li>The life or death of strategy is determined in the number of day-to-day decisions that are made in service of it (or not).</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Unnecessary meetings:
  <ul>
    <li>Those that don&rsquo;t directly connect to purpose, how we work or sense of community.</li>
    <li>Asses the monetary cost of every meeting.</li>
    <li>Clear outcomes for each meeting.
    <ul>
      <li>What cannot be done in another way?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Set a limit for the size of meeting.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Transition from one role to another:
  <ul>
    <li>Companies usually ask to cover for both roles:
    <ul>
      <li>More stress in an already stressful situation.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Instead:
    <ul>
      <li>7 days off to rest.</li>
      <li>7 days for reflection, reconnection and reset.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>In times of transformation, think about how you work before you launch and design how it will work after.</li>
</ul>]]></description></item><item><title>Book notes: Never split the difference</title><link>https://danlebrero.com/2023/09/16/never-split-the-difference-summary/</link><guid>https://danlebrero.com/2023/09/16/never-split-the-difference-summary/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 16 Sep 2023 10:30:00 +0200</pubDate><description><![CDATA[<p>These are my notes on <a href="https://amzn.to/3yKCWKN">Never Split the Difference</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/fbinegotiator">Chris Voss</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/tahlraz">Tahl Raz</a></p><p>Kidnappers are just businessman trying to get the best price.</p><h1>Key Insights</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Apology and first name to seed warmth.</li>
  <li>Open-ended questions (calibrated questions):
  <ul>
    <li>Gives other illusion of control.</li>
    <li>How the other would solved your problems.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Negotiate more effectively by influencing System 1.</li>
  <li>Core concept: Tactical empathy:
  <ul>
    <li>Listening is the most active thing you can do.</li>
    <li>When people feel listened:
    <ol>
      <li>Listen to themselves more carefully.</li>
      <li>More open to evaluate and clarify their own thoughts and feelings.</li>
      <li>Less defensive.</li>
      <li>More willing to listen to others.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Engage negotiation with a mindset of discovery.</li>
  <li>Make it all about the other.</li>
  <li>Mirroring (isopraxism):
  <ul>
    <li>Sign of bonding.</li>
    <li>We fear what&rsquo;s different and drawn to what&rsquo;s similar.</li>
    <li>Repeat the last 3 words, or the critical 1 to 3 words.</li>
    <li>Downward inflection: I am listening and understand.</li>
    <li>Upward inflection: invite response.</li>
    <li>4 steps:
    <ol>
      <li>Use late-night FM DJ voice.</li>
      <li>Start with &ldquo;I&rsquo;m sorry&rdquo;.</li>
      <li>Mirror.</li>
      <li>Silence. 4 secs at least.</li>
      <li>Repeat.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Never ask &ldquo;What do you mean by that?&rdquo;:
  <ul>
    <li>Is more irritating than mirroring.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Labeling:
  <ul>
    <li>Validating someone&rsquo;s emotions by acknowledging them.</li>
    <li>Labeling negative emotions diffuses them.</li>
    <li>Labeling positive emotions reinforces them.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>&ldquo;No&rdquo; starts the negotiation.</li>
  <li>Clearly giving permission to say &ldquo;NO&rdquo; to your ideas preserve people need for autonomy.</li>
  <li>Helps people feel safe, secure, emotionally comfortable, and in control of their decision.</li>
  <li>Provoke a &ldquo;no&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>&ldquo;That&rsquo;s right&rdquo; (making progress) vs &ldquo;You&rsquo;re right&rdquo; (nothing changes).</li>
  <li>Deadlines are often arbitrary, almost always flexible, and hardly ever trigger the consequences we think they will.</li>
  <li>We are hardwired to reject unfairness.</li>
  <li>Prospect Theory (Kahneman and Tversky):
  <ul>
    <li>Certainty effect:
    <ul>
      <li>People are drawn to sure things over probabilities, even when probabilities is a better choice.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Loss aversion:
    <ul>
      <li>People take greater risk to avoid losses than to achieve gains.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>How to negotiate a better salary:
  <ol>
    <li>Be pleasantly persistent on non-salary terms.</li>
    <li>Define success and metrics for next rise.</li>
    <li>Ask: &ldquo;What does it take to be successful here?&rdquo;
    <ul>
      <li>Interviewer will give advise, watch if you follow and become your unofficial mentor.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Failure plants the seed of future success.</li>
  <li>&ldquo;How am I supposed to do that?&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>&ldquo;Yes&rdquo; is nothing without &ldquo;how&rdquo;.</li>
  <li><a href="#ch-9">You must understand your counterpart style for effective negotiation</a>.</li>
  <li><a href="#bargain">Ackerman bargaining</a>.</li>
  <li>When pressure is on, you don&rsquo;t raise to the occasion; you fall to your highest level of preparation.</li>
  <li>The first few minutes before a meeting, and the last few minutes (when everybody is leaving) often tell you more about the other side than anything in between.</li>
  <li><a href="https://info.blackswanltd.com/download-the-negotiation-one-sheet">Negotiation one sheet pdf</a>.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-1"></a>Chapter 1: The new rules</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Apology and first name to seed warmth.</li>
  <li>Open-ended questions (calibrated questions):
  <ul>
    <li>The other side can respond but there are no fixed answers.</li>
    <li>Buys you time.</li>
    <li>Gives other illusion of control.</li>
    <li>How the other would solved your problems.</li>
    <li>&ldquo;How I am supposed to do that?&rdquo;</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Kidnappers are just businessman trying to get the best price.</li>
  <li>Cognitive bias:
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://amzn.to/3CIAzL6">Thinking, fast and slow</a>.</li>
    <li>Irrational, more than <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases">150 different ones</a>.</li>
    <li>Come from System 1 thinking.</li>
    <li>System 1 steers and guides our rational thoughts (System 2).</li>
    <li>Negotiate more effectively by influencing System 1.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Core concept: Tactical empathy:
  <ul>
    <li>Listening is the most active thing you can do.</li>
    <li>When people feel listened:
    <ol>
      <li>Listen to themselves more carefully.</li>
      <li>More open to evaluate and clarify their own thoughts and feelings.</li>
      <li>Less defensive.</li>
      <li>More willing to listen to others.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Negotiation is the heart of collaboration:
  <ul>
    <li>Makes conflict meaningful and productive for all parties.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-2"></a>Chapter 2: Be a Mirror</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Engage negotiation with a mindset of discovery.</li>
  <li>Overuse of personal pronouns (we/they vs me/I):
  <ul>
    <li>The less important he makes himself, the more important he probably is.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Team of 4 or 5 to listen.</li>
  <li>Voices in your head:
  <ul>
    <li>When not talking, you are thinking about your arguments.</li>
    <li>When talking, making your arguments.</li>
    <li>The other is possibly doing the same.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Make it all about the other.</li>
  <li>Three voice tones:
  <ol>
    <li>Late-night FM DJ voice:
    <ul>
      <li>Deep, soft, slow and reassuring.</li>
      <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RJjnkxvbxaI">Listen here!</a>.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Positive/playful voice:
    <ul>
      <li>Default one.</li>
      <li>Easy going. Good natured person.</li>
      <li>Relax and smile while talking.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Assertive dominance voice:
    <ul>
      <li>Used very rarely.</li>
      <li>Probably push back.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Mirroring (isopraxism):
  <ul>
    <li>Sign of bonding.</li>
    <li>We fear what&rsquo;s different and drawn to what&rsquo;s similar.</li>
    <li>Repeat the last 3 words, or the critical 1 to 3 words.</li>
    <li>Downward inflection: I am listening and understand.</li>
    <li>Upward inflection: invite response.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>4 steps:
  <ol>
    <li>Use late-night FM DJ voice.</li>
    <li>Start with &ldquo;I&rsquo;m sorry&rdquo;.</li>
    <li>Mirror.</li>
    <li>Silence. 4 secs at least.</li>
    <li>Repeat.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Never ask &ldquo;What do you mean by that?&rdquo;:
  <ul>
    <li>Is more irritating than mirroring.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-3"></a>Chapter 3: Don&rsquo;t Feel Their Pain, Label It.</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Tactical empathy:
  <ul>
    <li>The ability to recognize the perspective of a counterpart, and the vocalization of that recognition.</li>
    <li>Emotional intelligence on steroids.</li>
    <li>Visualize yourself in the position they describe, and put in as much detail as you can.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Labeling:
  <ul>
    <li>Validating someone&rsquo;s emotions by acknowledging them.</li>
    <li>Give emotions a name.</li>
    <li>Steps:
    <ol>
      <li>Detect other person&rsquo;s emotional state.
      <ul>
        <li>Pay attention to changes people undergo when they respond to external events (your words).</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Label it:
      <ul>
        <li>It seems like &hellip;</li>
        <li>It sounds like &hellip;</li>
        <li>It looks like &hellip;</li>
        <li>NOT &ldquo;I am hearing that &hellip;&rdquo;</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Silence: be quiet and listen.</li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>Labeling negative emotions diffuses them:
    <ul>
      <li>When making a mistake, go straight to acknowledge it.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Labeling positive emotions reinforces them.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Accusation audit:
  <ul>
    <li>List every terrible thing your counterpart could say about you.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-4"></a>Chapter 4: Beware &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; - Master &ldquo;No&rdquo;</h2>
<ul>
  <li>&ldquo;No&rdquo; starts the negotiation.</li>
  <li>Clearly giving permission to say &ldquo;NO&rdquo; to your ideas preserve people need for autonomy:
  <ul>
    <li>Emotions calm.</li>
    <li>Give time.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>No != rejection:
  <ul>
    <li>I am not yet ready to agree.</li>
    <li>I do not understand.</li>
    <li>I want something else.</li>
    <li>I need more information.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>After &ldquo;no&rdquo;, pause, ask solution-based questions or label their effect:
  <ul>
    <li>What about this doesn&rsquo;t work for you?</li>
    <li>It seems like there&rsquo;s something here that bothers you.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Persuade them from their perspective, not ours:
  <ul>
    <li>Two primal urges:
    <ol>
      <li>Feel safe and secure.</li>
      <li>Feel in control.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>And early &ldquo;yes&rdquo; is often a counterfeit dodge.</li>
  <li>&ldquo;No&rdquo; skills:
  <ul>
    <li>Allows the real issue to be brought forth.</li>
    <li>Protects people from making ineffective decisions or to correct them.</li>
    <li>Slow things down so that people can freely embrace their decision.</li>
    <li>Helps people feel safe, secure, emotionally comfortable, and in control of their decision.</li>
    <li>Moves everyone&rsquo;s efforts forward.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>No &ldquo;no&rdquo; means no go.</li>
  <li>Email magic: provoke a &ldquo;no&rdquo;:
  <ul>
    <li>Have you given up on this project?</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Is not a bad time to talk?</li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-5"></a>Chapter 5: Trigger the two words that immediately transform any negotiation</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Behavioral Change Stairway Model (BCSM) stages:
  <ol>
    <li>Active listening.</li>
    <li>Empathy.</li>
    <li>Rapport.</li>
    <li>Influence.</li>
    <li>Behavioural change.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>&ldquo;That&rsquo;s right&rdquo;:
  <ul>
    <li>To trigger: summarize paraphrasing + labeling.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>&ldquo;You&rsquo;re right&rdquo;: nothing changes.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-6"></a>Chapter 6: Bend their reality</h1>
<ul>
  <li>No deal is better than a bad deal.</li>
  <li>Creative solutions are preceded by some degree of risk, annoyance, confusion, and conflict.
  <ul>
    <li>Compromise produce none of that.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Deadlines are often arbitrary, almost always flexible, and hardly ever trigger the consequences we think they will.
  <ul>
    <li>Deadlines are the bogeyman of negotiations.</li>
    <li>Don A. Moore: when negotiators tell about their deadline, they get better deals.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>People who had damaged the part of the brain where emotions are generated cannot make decisions.</li>
  <li>The F-word: fair.
  <ul>
    <li>We are hardwired to reject unfairness.</li>
    <li>Don&rsquo;t concede when accused of unfairness.
    <ul>
      <li>Ask how you&rsquo;re mistreating them.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Good use:
    <ul>
      <li>&ldquo;I want you to feel like you are being treated fairly at all times. So please stop me at any time if you feel I&rsquo;m being unfair, and we&rsquo;ll address it&rdquo;.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Prospect Theory (Kahneman and Tversky):
  <ul>
    <li>Certainty effect:
    <ul>
      <li>People are drawn to sure things over probabilities, even when probabilities is a better choice.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Loss aversion:
    <ul>
      <li>People take greater risk to avoid losses than to achieve gains.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>To get real leverage, you have to persuade that they have something concrete to lose if the deal fall through.</li>
    <li>Tactics:
    <ol>
      <li>Anchor their emotions:
      <ol>
        <li>Accusation audit.</li>
        <li>Play on their loss aversion.</li>
      </ol></li>
      <li>Let the other guy go first &hellip; most of the time:
      <ul>
        <li>Let the other side anchor monetary negotiations.</li>
        <li>Except if the other side is pro, as they may bend your reality with an extreme anchor.</li>
        <li>Except if the other side is a rookie, as you can bend their reality.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Establish a range:
      <ul>
        <li>Expect them to come in at the lower end.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Pivot to non-monetary terms.</li>
      <li>When you do talk numbers, use odd(weird) ones. Avoid rounded ones.
      <ul>
        <li>Example: 27,343.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Surprise with a gift:
      <ul>
        <li>It triggers reciprocity.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>How to negotiate a better salary:
  <ol>
    <li>Be pleasantly persistent on non-salary terms.</li>
    <li>Define success and metrics for next rise.</li>
    <li>Ask: &ldquo;What does it take to be successful here?&rdquo;
    <ul>
      <li>Interviewer will give advise, watch if you follow and become your unofficial mentor.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-7"></a>Chapter 7: Create the Illusion of Control</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Failure plants the seed of future success.</li>
  <li>Illusion of control with open-ended/calibrated questions:
  <ul>
    <li>Allows you to introduce an idea without sounding pushy.</li>
    <li>&ldquo;How am I supposed to do that?&rdquo;.
    <ul>
      <li>Ask for help! Not accusation or threat.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Calibrated: they have a direction where you want the conversation to go.</li>
    <li>Question must start with &ldquo;what&rdquo; or &ldquo;how&rdquo;.
    <ul>
      <li>What about this is important to you?</li>
      <li>How can I help to make this better for us?</li>
      <li>How would you like me to proceed?</li>
      <li>How can we solve this problem?</li>
      <li>What are we trying to accomplish here?</li>
      <li>What is the biggest challenge you face?</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Without self-control and emotional regulation it does not work.
  <ul>
    <li>Bite your tongue, do not counterattack, learn to change your state to something more positive.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-8"></a>Chapter 8: Guarantee Execution.</h2>
<ul>
  <li>&ldquo;Yes&rdquo; is nothing without &ldquo;how&rdquo;.</li>
  <li>Let your counterparts think they are defining success their way:
  <ol>
    <li>Questions:
    <ol>
      <li>How will we know we&rsquo;re on track?</li>
      <li>How will we address things if we find we&rsquo;re off track?</li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>Summarize until &ldquo;That&rsquo;s right&rdquo;.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Signs the other doesn&rsquo;t believe it is their idea:
  <ul>
    <li>&ldquo;You&rsquo;re right&rdquo;.</li>
    <li>&ldquo;I&rsquo;ll try&rdquo;.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>The other side is a team. Buy must come from all.</li>
  <li>Spotting liars:
  <ol>
    <li>Body language or tone of voice does not match words.</li>
    <li>Rule of three:
    <ul>
      <li>Get 3 times confirmation:
      <ul>
        <li>Summarize.</li>
        <li>Similar calibrated questions.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Pinocchio effect:
    <ul>
      <li>Liars tend to speak in more complex sentences.</li>
      <li>Liars avoid using &ldquo;I&rdquo;.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>How to get your counterparts bid against themselves:
  <ul>
    <li>You can express &ldquo;no&rdquo; four times before actually saying the word:
    <ol>
      <li>How am I supposed to do that?</li>
      <li>Your offer is very generous. I&rsquo;m sorry, that just doesn&rsquo;t work for me.</li>
      <li>I&rsquo;m sorry, but I&rsquo;m afraid I just can&rsquo;t do that.</li>
      <li>I&rsquo;m sorry, no.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-9"></a>Chapter 9: Bargain hard</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Negotiation styles:
  <ol>
    <li>Analyst:
    <ul>
      <li>Motto: as much time as it takes to get it right.</li>
      <li>Problem solvers, information aggregators.</li>
      <li>Hypersensitive to reciprocity.</li>
      <li>Avoid slowing emotion.</li>
      <li>Hate surprises. Loads of preparation.</li>
      <li>Skeptical by nature.</li>
      <li>Dont ask them too many questions.</li>
      <li>User clear data.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Accommodator:
    <ul>
      <li>Love building the relationship.
      <ul>
        <li>Great rapport may help little.</li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>Extremely friendly, optimistic, poor time managers.</li>
      <li>Can be difficult uncover their objections, hidden to avoid conflict.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Assertive:
    <ul>
      <li>Time is money.</li>
      <li>Done over perfect.</li>
      <li>Want to win.</li>
      <li>Don&rsquo;t listen until they feel heard and understood.</li>
      <li>Give an inch, take a mile.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
</ul>
<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th> </th>
      <th>Time </th>
      <th>Silence </th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Assertive </td>
      <td>Money </td>
      <td>More talking </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Analyst </td>
      <td>Preparation </td>
      <td>Thinking </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Accomodator </td>
      <td>Relationship </td>
      <td>Anger </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://info.blackswanltd.com/guide-to-3-negotiator-types">Guide to identify type</a>.
  <ul>
    <li>You must understand your counterpart style for effective negotiation.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Be ready for the counterparts extreme anchor.</li>
  <li>Punch back:
  <ul>
    <li>Avoid it!!!</li>
    <li>&ldquo;Strategic umbrage&rdquo;: threat without anger but with &ldquo;poise&rdquo;.</li>
    <li>&ldquo;Why would you do that?&rdquo; but in a way that the &ldquo;that&rdquo; favours you:
    <ul>
      <li>Why would you ever change your existing supplier?</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>&ldquo;I&rdquo; messages: &quot;I feel ___ when you ___ because ___&quot;.
</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a name="bargain"></a>Ackerman bargaining:
  <ol>
    <li>Set your target price.</li>
    <li>First offer at 65%.</li>
    <li>Other offers at 85, 95, 100%.</li>
    <li>Use lots of empathy and different ways of saying &ldquo;no&rdquo; to get the other side to counter before you increase your offer.</li>
    <li>For final amount, use non-rounded numbers.</li>
    <li>On the final number, throw a non-monetary item to show you&rsquo;re at your limit.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>When pressure is on, you don&rsquo;t raise to the occasion; you fall to your highest level of preparation.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-10"></a>Find the Black Swan</h1>
<ul>
  <li>What we know must guide us but not blind us to what we do not know.
  <ul>
    <li>Retain beginner&rsquo;s mind.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Black Swan == Unknown unknowns.
  <ul>
    <li>At least 3 on each negotiation.</li>
    <li>Change in mindset: open up your established pathways and embrace more intuitive and nuanced ways of listening.</li>
    <li>Not closely guarded information, but also completely innocuous. The value is misunderstood.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Leverage:
  <ul>
    <li>Positive: You have something the other want.</li>
    <li>Negative:
    <ul>
      <li>If you can threat, make the other suffer.</li>
      <li>Avoid or label it.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Normative: if you can show inconsistencies between their beliefs and their actions.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>When people act irrationally, is either:
  <ol>
    <li>Are ill-informed.</li>
    <li>They are constrained.</li>
    <li>They have other hidden interests.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>The first few minutes before a meeting, and the last few minutes (when everybody is leaving) often tell you more about the other side than anything in between.</li>
  <li><a href="https://info.blackswanltd.com/download-the-negotiation-one-sheet">Negotiation one sheet pdf</a>.</li>
</ul>]]></description></item><item><title>Book notes: Inspired: How to Create Tech Products Customers Love</title><link>https://danlebrero.com/2023/05/11/inspired-how-to-create-tech-products-customers-love-summary/</link><guid>https://danlebrero.com/2023/05/11/inspired-how-to-create-tech-products-customers-love-summary/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><description><![CDATA[<p>These are my notes on <a href="https://amzn.to/3MFmJNc">Inspired: How to Create Tech Products Customers Love</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/cagan">Marty Cagan</a>.</p><p>If you liked <a href="/2020/01/22/accelerate-high-performing-technology-orgs-summary/#content">Accelerate</a>, The DevOps Handbook, <a href="/2021/12/01/sonner-safer-happier-summary-patterns-business-agility/#content">Sooner, safer, happier</a> or other similar books, you will want to buy this book for your Product Manager.</p><h1>Key Insights</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Root cause of failed product efforts: Waterfall process from ideas to deploy.
  <ul>
    <li>Causes:
    <ul>
      <li>Source of new product ideas: sales or stakeholders.</li>
      <li>Assuming you can guess the cost and benefit.</li>
      <li>Getting excited about product roadmaps:
      <ul>
        <li>Truth:
        <ul>
          <li>Half to 3/4 of ideas are not going to work.</li>
          <li>It takes several iterations for an idea to deliver the business value.</li>
        </ul></li>
      </ul></li>
      <li>PM, design, engineering, agile, and customer validation come in late in the game.</li>
      <li>Project centric (== outputs).</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Principles:
  <ol>
    <li>Risk tackled up front.
    <ul>
      <li>Product discovery: output is validated product backlog:
      <ul>
        <li>Will the user buy this? Value risk.</li>
        <li>Can the user figure out how to use it? UX risk.</li>
        <li>Can engineers built it? Feasibility risk.</li>
        <li>Can stakeholders support it? Business viability risk.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Products are defined and designed collaboratively.</li>
    <li>Solve problems, not implement features.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>10-20 experiments per week.</li>
  <li>MVP: minimum viable <strong>prototype</strong>.</li>
  <li>Cross-functional long-lived teams.</li>
  <li>Missionaries, not mercenaries.</li>
  <li>The Product Manager:
  <ul>
    <li>Responsible and accountable for the success of the product.</li>
    <li>Decide what gets built.</li>
    <li>Not a 9-5 job.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Ensure senior engineers are participating and contributing to product discovery.</li>
  <li>Typical roadmaps are the root cause of most waste and failed efforts in product organizations.
  <ul>
    <li>We need to solve the underlying problem, not deliver a feature.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Outcome-based roadmaps (objective list) are good, as long as not all items have a deadline.</li>
  <li>High-integrity commitments:
  <ul>
    <li>Make commitment once value, UX, feasibility and business viability are clear.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Product vision must inspire, product strategy must focus.</li>
  <li><a href="#ch-25">Principles of Product Vision</a>:
  <ul>
    <li>Fall in love with the problem, not with the solution.</li>
    <li>Don&rsquo;t be afraid to disrupt yourselves because if you don&rsquo;t, someone else will.</li>
    <li>Be stubborn on vision but flexible on the details.</li>
    <li>Realize that any product vision is a leap of faith:
    <ul>
      <li>If you could truly validate a vision, then your vision is not ambitious enough.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#ch-26">Principles of Product Strategy</a>:
  <ul>
    <li>Focus on one target market or person at a time:
    <ul>
      <li>Product will likely be useful to others, but at least will be loved by some, and that&rsquo;s key.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Obsess over customers, not over competitors.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>If you are a PM and not good at evangelism, there is a strong chance that your product efforts will get derailed before they see the light of the day.</li>
  <li>Most product teams have a better understanding on how to accomplish quality, rather than speed.</li>
  <li>Key to effective product discovery is getting access to our customers without pushing quick experiments into production.</li>
  <li>Customer (and executives or stakeholders) cannot tell us what they want, because:
  <ol>
    <li>They don&rsquo;t know what is possible.</li>
    <li>Nobody knows what they want until they see it.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>UX is harder and more critical than engineering.</li>
  <li>Product discovery and validation only when there is significant risk.</li>
  <li>Customer discovery program:
  <ul>
    <li>Favourite leading indicator of future success.</li>
    <li>Aim for 6 reference customers:
    <ul>
      <li>Desperate for a solution, or a technologist.</li>
      <li>Willing to spend time with product team and testing prototypes.</li>
      <li>Not building features for all reference customers, but a single solution that works for all of them.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>If you cannot recruit even 4 or 5, you are probably chasing the wrong problem.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Opportunity Assessment Technique, answer:
  <ol>
    <li>What business objective is this work intended to address? (Objective - Should match an OKR).</li>
    <li>How will you know if you&rsquo;ve succeeded? (Key result - Should match an OKR).</li>
    <li>What problem will this solve for our customers? (Customer problem).</li>
    <li>What type of customer are we focused on? (Target market).</li>
  </ol>
  <ul>
    <li>It is responsibility of the PM to answer these questions.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.jpattonassociates.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/story_mapping.pdf">Jeff Patton&rsquo;s Story Map Summary</a>.</li>
  <li>Customer interviews:
  <ul>
    <li>Mindset: understand and learn. Not prove.</li>
    <li>At least 2-3 hours per week.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Prototypes: can serve as a spec on what to build.</li>
  <li>Testing Usability:
  <ul>
    <li>Objective: trying to figure out how your user thinks about the problem.</li>
    <li>Avoid leading. Act like a parrot.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Qualitative Value Testing Techniques:</li>
  <li>The single most important discovery activity.</li>
  <li>User willing to pay with money, reputation or time.</li>
  <li>Head of product to highlight big learnings at all-hands. Not more than 30 mins.</li>
  <li>Only a few companies are strong both at innovation and execution.</li>
</ul><h1>TOC</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#part-1">Part I: Lessons from Top Tech Companies</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-1">Chapter 1: Behind Every Great Product</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-3">Chapter 3: Startups: Getting to Product/Market Fit</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-4">Chapter 4: GrowthStage Companies: Scaling to Success</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-5">Chapter 5: Enterprise Companies: Consistent Product Innovation</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-6">Chapter 6: The Root Causes of Failed Product Efforts</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-7">Chapter 7: Beyond Lean and Agile</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-8">Chapter 8: Key Concepts</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#part-II">Part II: The Right People</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-9">Chapter 9: Principles of Strong Product Teams</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-10">Chapter 10: The Product Manager</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-11">Chapter 11: The Product Designer</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-13">Chapter 13: Product Marketing Managers</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-14">Chapter 14: The Supporting Roles</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-16">Chapter 16: The Role of Leadership</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-17">Chapter 17: The Head of Product Role</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-18">Chapter 18: The Head of Technology Role</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-19">Chapter 19: The Delivery Manager Role</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-20">Chapter 20: Principles of Structuring Product Teams</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#part-III">Part III: The Right Product</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-22">Chapter 22: The Problems with Product Roadmaps</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-23">Chapter 23: The Alternative to Roadmaps</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-24">Chapter 24: Product Vision and Product Strategy</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-25">Chapter 25: Principles of Product Vision</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-26">Chapter 26: Principles of Product Strategy</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-27">Chapter 27: Product Principles</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-28">Chapter 28: The OKR Technique</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-30">Chapter 30: Product Objectives @ Scale</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-31">Chapter 31: Product Evangelism</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#part-IV">Part IV: The Right Process</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-33">Chapter 33: Principles of Product Discovery</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-34">Chapter 34: Discovery Techniques Overview</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-34-1">Discovery framing techniques</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#ch-35">Chapter 35: Opportunity Assessment Technique</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-36">Chapter 36: Customer Letter Technique</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-37">Chapter 37: Startup Canvas Technique</a></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-38a">Discovery Planning Techniques</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#ch-38">Chapter 38: Story Map Technique</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-39">Chapter 39: Customer Discovery Program Technique</a></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-41a">Discovery Ideation Techniques</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#ch-41">Chapter 41: Customer Interviews</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-42">Chapter 42: Concierge Test Technique</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-43">Chapter 43: The Power of Customer Misbehavior</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-44">Chapter 44: Hack Days</a></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-45a">Discovery Prototyping Techniques</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#ch-45">Chapter 45: Principles of Prototypes</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-46">Chapter 46: Feasibility Prototype Technique</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-47">Chapter 47: User Prototype Technique</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-48">Chapter 48: LiveData Prototype Technique</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-49">Chapter 49: Hybrid Prototype Technique</a></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-50a">Discovery Testing Techniques</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#ch-50">Chapter 50: Testing Usability</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-51">Chapter 51: Testing Value</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-52">Chapter 52: Demand Testing Techniques</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-53">Chapter 53: Qualitative Value Testing Techniques</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-54">Chapter 54: Quantitative Value Testing Techniques</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-56">Chapter 56: Testing Business Viability</a></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-58a">Transformation Techniques</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#ch-58">Chapter 58: Discovery Sprint Technique</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-59">Chapter 59: Pilot Team Technique</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-60">Chapter 60: Weaning an Organization Off Roadmaps</a></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-61a">Process @ Scale</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#ch-61">Chapter 61: Managing Stakeholders</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ch-62">Chapter 62: Communicating Product Learnings</a></li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#part-V">Part V: The Right Culture</a>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#ch-64">Chapter 64: Good Product Team/Bad Product Team</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-65">Chapter 65: Top Reasons for Loss of Innovation</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-66">Chapter 66: Top Reasons for Loss of Velocity</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ch-67">Chapter 67: Establishing a Strong Product Culture</a></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="part-1"></a>Part I: Lessons from Top Tech Companies</h1><h2><a name="ch-1"></a>Chapter 1: Behind Every Great Product</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Book is for Product Managers (PM).</li>
  <li>PM is a full time job.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-3"></a>Chapter 3: Startups: Getting to Product/Market Fit</h2>
<ul>
  <li>One of the founders acts as the PM.</li>
  <li>Less 25 engineers in 1-5 product teams.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-4"></a>Chapter 4: GrowthStage Companies: Scaling to Success</h2>
<ul>
  <li>25 to hundreds of engineers.</li>
  <li>Product teams complains:
  <ol>
    <li>Cannot see the big picture.</li>
    <li>How they contribute to goals.</li>
    <li>What means to be empowered, autonomous.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Sales and marketing: go-to-market strategies not appropriate for new products.</li>
  <li>IT full of technical debt.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-5"></a>Chapter 5: Enterprise Companies: Consistent Product Innovation</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Symptoms:
  <ul>
    <li>Lack of innovation.</li>
    <li>Diminished morale.</li>
    <li>Slow product delivery.</li>
    <li>No clear vision.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-6"></a>Chapter 6: The Root Causes of Failed Product Efforts</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Root cause: Waterfall process from ideas to deploy.</li>
  <li>Causes:
  <ul>
    <li>Source of new product ideas: sales or stakeholders.</li>
    <li>Assuming you can guess the cost and benefit.</li>
    <li>Getting excited about product roadmaps:
    <ul>
      <li>Truth:
      <ul>
        <li>Half to 3/4 of ideas are not going to work.</li>
        <li>It takes several iterations for an idea to deliver the business value.</li>
      </ul></li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>PM, design, engineering, agile, and customer validation come in late in the game.</li>
    <li>Project centric (== outputs).</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-7"></a>Chapter 7: Beyond Lean and Agile</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Principles:
  <ol>
    <li>Risk tackled up front.</li>
    <li>Products are defined and designed collaboratively.</li>
    <li>Solve problems, not implement features.</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-8"></a>Chapter 8: Key Concepts</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Holistic Product == Functionality + tech + UX + monetization + user/customer acquisition + offline experience.</li>
  <li>Continuous Discovery and delivery.</li>
  <li>Product discovery: output is validated product backlog:
  <ol>
    <li>Will the user buy this? Value risk.</li>
    <li>Can the user figure out how to use it? UX risk.</li>
    <li>Can engineers built it? Feasibility risk.</li>
    <li>Can stakeholders support it? Business viability risk.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>10-20 experiments per week.</li>
  <li>MVP: minimum viable <strong>prototype</strong>.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="part-II"></a>Part II: The Right People</h1>
<ul>
  <li>It is all about the product team.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-9"></a>Chapter 9: Principles of Strong Product Teams</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Cross-functional long-lived teams.</li>
  <li>Missionaries, not mercenaries.</li>
  <li>Prefer collocated.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-10"></a>Chapter 10: The Product Manager</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Responsible and accountable for the success of the product.</li>
  <li>Decide what gets built.</li>
  <li>Key responsibilities:
  <ul>
    <li>Deep knowledge of:
    <ul>
      <li>the customer.</li>
      <li>the data.</li>
      <li>the business.</li>
      <li>the market and industry.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Traits:
  <ul>
    <li>Smart, creative, persistent.</li>
    <li>Passion for products and solving customer problems.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Not a 9-5 job.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-11"></a>Chapter 11: The Product Designer</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Responsibilities:
  <ol>
    <li>Product discovery: measured on the success of the product.</li>
    <li>Holistic UX, including email, marketing, sales process, &hellip;</li>
    <li>Prototypes.</li>
    <li>Continuous user testing.</li>
    <li>Interaction and visual design.</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-13"></a>Chapter 13: Product Marketing Managers</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Usually not a full-time, dedicated member.</li>
  <li>Business viability.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-14"></a>Chapter 14: The Supporting Roles</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Not a full-time decided member.</li>
  <li>User researchers:
  <ul>
    <li>Help to learn the most from user testing.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Data Analysts.</li>
  <li>Test automation engineers.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-16"></a>Chapter 16: The Role of Leadership</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Primary job: recruit, develop and retain strong talent.</li>
  <li>While growing, keep a holistic view of product.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-17"></a>Chapter 17: The Head of Product Role</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Most senior product role, peer to CTO.</li>
  <li>Competencies:
  <ol>
    <li>Develop a strong team of PM.</li>
    <li>Product vision and strategy:
    <ol>
      <li>Only when the CEO is not the product visionary.</li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>Execution.</li>
    <li>Product culture.</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-18"></a>Chapter 18: The Head of Technology Role</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Objective: remove tech barriers and broadening what is possible.</li>
  <li>Responsibilities, in order of importance:
  <ul>
    <li>Organization: people.</li>
    <li>Leadership: strategic direction.</li>
    <li>Delivery.</li>
    <li>Architecture.</li>
    <li>Discovery: ensure senior engineers are participating and contributing to product discovery.</li>
    <li>Evangelism.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-19"></a>Chapter 19: The Delivery Manager Role</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Project managers, and typically Scrum Masters.</li>
  <li>Remove impediments.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-20"></a>Chapter 20: Principles of Structuring Product Teams</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Principles:
  <ol>
    <li>Team structure should follow investment strategy.</li>
    <li>Minimize dependencies.</li>
    <li>Ownership and autonomy.</li>
    <li>Maximize leverage:
    <ul>
      <li>Shared services.</li>
      <li>But brings dependencies, reduces autonomy.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Follow production vision and strategy.</li>
    <li>3-12 people.</li>
    <li>Follow architecture (which should follow production vision).</li>
    <li>Align with user/customer:
    <ul>
      <li>Team to serve one type of user.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Align with business units.</li>
    <li>Structure is a moving target:
    <ul>
      <li>Review at least yearly.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h1><a name="part-III"></a>Part III: The Right Product</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Typical roadmaps are the root cause of most waste and failed efforts in product organizations.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-22"></a>Chapter 22: The Problems with Product Roadmaps</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Product discovery is the most important core competency of a product organization.</li>
  <li>Issue with roadmap is that is treated as a commitment.</li>
  <li>We need to solve the underlying problem, not deliver a feature.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-23"></a>Chapter 23: The Alternative to Roadmaps</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Valid roadmap purposes:
  <ol>
    <li>Ensure teams are working on the highest business value items.</li>
    <li>To track a date-based commitment, if there is any.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Product teams need business context (clarity in <a href="/2022/01/12/turn-the-ship-around-book-summary/#content">intent based leadership</a>).</li>
  <li>Two main components to provide business context:
  <ol>
    <li>Product vision and strategy.</li>
    <li>Business objectives (not product ideas).</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Outcome-based roadmaps (objective list) are good, as long as not all items have a deadline.</li>
  <li>Deadlines:
  <ul>
    <li>Minimize them.</li>
    <li>Issue is that the commitment is made too early (== not enough information).</li>
    <li>High-integrity commitments:
    <ul>
      <li>Make commitment once value, UX, feasibility and business viability are clear.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-24"></a>Chapter 24: Product Vision and Product Strategy</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Product vision must inspire, product strategy must focus.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-25"></a>Chapter 25: Principles of Product Vision</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Start with why:
  <ul>
    <li>Product vision articulate your purpose.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Fall in love with the problem, not with the solution.</li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t be afraid to think big.</li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t be afraid to disrupt yourselves because if you don&rsquo;t, someone else will.</li>
  <li>Needs to inspire.</li>
  <li>Determine and embrace relevant and meaningful trends.</li>
  <li>Skate to where the pack is heading, not to where it was.</li>
  <li>Be stubborn on vision but flexible on the details.</li>
  <li>Realize that any product vision is a leap of faith:
  <ul>
    <li>If you could truly validate a vision, then your vision is not ambitious enough.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Evangelize continuously and relentlessly.</li>
</ol><h2><a name="ch-26"></a>Chapter 26: Principles of Product Strategy</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Focus on one target market or person at a time:
  <ul>
    <li>Product will likely be useful to others, but at least will be loved by some, and that&rsquo;s key.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Needs to be aligned with business strategy.</li>
  <li>Needs to be aligned with sales and go-to-market strategy.</li>
  <li>Obsess over customers, not over competitors.</li>
  <li>Communicate the strategy across the org.</li>
</ol><h2><a name="ch-27"></a>Chapter 27: Product Principles</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Complement vision and strategy.</li>
  <li>Production principles: nature of the products you want to build.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-28"></a>Chapter 28: The OKR Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Two fundamental principles:
  <ol>
    <li>Tell people what to do, not how.</li>
    <li>Measure by result.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>OKR = Objectives and Key Results:
  <ul>
    <li>Management + focus + alignment.</li>
    <li>Objectives qualitative.</li>
    <li>Results quantitative. Outcomes.</li>
    <li>Typical cadence: org yearly, team quarterly.</li>
    <li>1-3 objectives, 1-3 key results.</li>
    <li>Track weekly.</li>
    <li>Team accountable.</li>
    <li>Org-wide consistent evaluation/scoring.</li>
    <li>Be transparent.</li>
    <li>High-integrity commitments are binary.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-30"></a>Chapter 30: Product Objectives @ Scale</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Large burden on leadership and management to ensure that the org is truly aligned, that each and every product team understands how they fit into the mix, and what they are there to contribute.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-31"></a>Chapter 31: Product Evangelism</h2>
<ul>
  <li>If you are a PM and not good at evangelism, there is a strong chance that your product efforts will get derailed before they see the light of the day.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="part-IV"></a>Part IV: The Right Process</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Product discovery:
  <ul>
    <li>Single solution that works for many customers, and not a series of specials.</li>
    <li>Learn fast + release with confidence (speed vs quality).</li>
    <li>In this book product == production ready.</li>
    <li>Most product teams have a better understanding on how to accomplish quality, rather than speed.</li>
    <li>Key to effective product discovery is getting access to our customers without pushing quick experiments into production.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-33"></a>Chapter 33: Principles of Product Discovery</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Customer (and executives or stakeholders) cannot tell us what they want, because:
  <ol>
    <li>They don&rsquo;t know what is possible.</li>
    <li>Nobody knows what they want until they see it.</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Most important thing is to establish compelling value.</li>
  <li>UX is harder and more critical than engineering.</li>
  <li>Functionality, design and technology are intertwined.</li>
  <li>Many ideas won&rsquo;t work, and the ones that do require several iterations.</li>
  <li>We must validate our ideas on real users and customers.</li>
  <li>Aim to validate ideas the fastest, cheapest way possible.</li>
  <li>Shared learning by the whole team.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
  <li>Aim for 10-20 iterations per week.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-34"></a>Chapter 34: Discovery Techniques Overview</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Discovery framing techniques:
  <ul>
    <li>To quickly identify the underlying issues that must be tackled during product discovery.</li>
    <li>Objective:
    <ol>
      <li>Agree on the problem.</li>
      <li>Identify big risk to be tackled ruing discovery work.</li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>Product discovery and validation only when there is significant risk.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Discovery planning techniques:
  <ul>
    <li>To scope out and plan the discovery efforts.</li>
    <li>Customer discovery program:
    <ul>
      <li>Loads of work.</li>
      <li>Favourite leading indicator of future success.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Discovery ideation techniques.</li>
  <li>Discovery prototyping techniques:
  <ul>
    <li><p>Different forms of prototypes, each suited to testing different things.</p>
    <blockquote>Plan to throw one away, you will anyhow. <cite>Fred Brooks</cite>
    </blockquote></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Discovery testing techniques:
  <ul>
    <li>Usual test order:
    <ol>
      <li>Value.</li>
      <li>Usability.</li>
      <li>Feasibility.</li>
      <li>Business Viability.</li>
    </ol></li>
    <li>Value and usability usually tested with the same users at the same time.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Transformation techniques:
  <ul>
    <li>Way of work.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ol><h1><a name="ch-34-1"></a>Discovery framing techniques</h1><h2><a name="ch-35"></a>Chapter 35: Opportunity Assessment Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Answer:
  <ol>
    <li>What business objective is this work intended to address? (Objective - Should match an OKR).</li>
    <li>How will you know if you&rsquo;ve succeeded? (Key result - Should match an OKR).</li>
    <li>What problem will this solve for our customers? (Customer problem).</li>
    <li>What type of customer are we focused on? (Target market).</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>It is responsibility of the PM to answer these questions.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-36"></a>Chapter 36: Customer Letter Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>For larger efforts.</li>
  <li>Write an imagined press release.</li>
  <li>Write an imagined letter from a happy customer to the CEO.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-37"></a>Chapter 37: Startup Canvas Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>When trying to figure out the new product:
  <ul>
    <li>Lot more risks.</li>
    <li><a href="https://miro.com/templates/startup-canvas/">Template</a>.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Typically, value is the most risky risk.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-38a"></a>Discovery Planning Techniques</h1><h2><a name="ch-38"></a>Chapter 38: Story Map Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Framing and planning technique, useful for ideation good for design and communication.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.jpattonassociates.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/story_mapping.pdf">Jeff Patton&rsquo;s summary</a>.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-39"></a>Chapter 39: Customer Discovery Program Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Simple best tool for marketing and sales is the happy reference customer:
  <ul>
    <li>Real (not family/friends).</li>
    <li>In production.</li>
    <li>Paying.</li>
    <li>Willing to tell others.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Discovery and developing a set of reference customers in parallel with discovery and developing the actual product.</li>
  <li>Substantial effort.</li>
  <li>Aim for 6 reference customers:
  <ul>
    <li>Same market.</li>
    <li>Recruit 8.</li>
    <li>Desperate for a solution, or a technologist.</li>
    <li>Willing to spend time with product team and testing prototypes.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Not building features for all reference customers, but a single solution that works for all of them.</li>
  <li>They do not pay in advance, it is a partner.</li>
  <li>If you cannot recruit even 4 or 5, you are probably chasing the wrong problem.</li>
  <li>Variations:
  <ul>
    <li>API/Platform products:
    <ul>
      <li>Reference apps instead of customers.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Customer-Enabling tools:
    <ul>
      <li>Well respected and influential internal users/employees.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Consumer products:
    <ul>
      <li>10-50 users.</li>
      <li>Supplement with much broad testing.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-41a"></a>Discovery Ideation Techniques</h1><h2><a name="ch-41"></a>Chapter 41: Customer Interviews</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Try to understand:
  <ol>
    <li>Are your customers who you think they are?</li>
    <li>Do they really have to problem you think they have?</li>
    <li>How does the customer solve this problem today?</li>
    <li>What would be required for them to switch?</li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Tips:
  <ul>
    <li>At least 2-3 hours per week.</li>
    <li>Mindset: understand and learn. Not prove.</li>
    <li>About 1 hour.</li>
    <li>On their native habitat.</li>
    <li>Be clear on the problem you think they have, and how you will either confirm or contradict that.</li>
    <li>PM (takes notes) + engineer (listens) + product designer (leads).</li>
    <li>Open-ended questions, learn what they are doing today.</li>
    <li>Debrief with colleagues.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-42"></a>Chapter 42: Concierge Test Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Do your customer work.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-43"></a>Chapter 43: The Power of Customer Misbehavior</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Encourage customers to use our product to solve problems other than what we planned for and officially support.</li>
  <li>Not a useful technique for all companies.</li>
  <li>Open API.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-44"></a>Chapter 44: Hack Days</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Undirected: any problem related to mission.</li>
  <li>Directed: a specific problem:
  <ul>
    <li>Facilitates the inclusion of engineers.</li>
    <li>Help building a team of missionaries.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-45a"></a>Discovery Prototyping Techniques</h2><h2><a name="ch-45"></a>Chapter 45: Principles of Prototypes</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Cheap learning.</li>
  <li>Think deeper about the problem.</li>
  <li>Build shared understanding.</li>
  <li>Right level of fidelity.</li>
  <li>Tackle on or more product risks.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
  <li>Can serve as a spec on what to build.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-46"></a>Chapter 46: Feasibility Prototype Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Just enough code to mitigate risk.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-47"></a>Chapter 47: User Prototype Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>It is not good for proving anything.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-48"></a>Chapter 48: LiveData Prototype Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>It is not okay for the PM to tell engineers that the prototype is good enough for production.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-49"></a>Chapter 49: Hybrid Prototype Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Wizard of Oz:
  <ul>
    <li>High fidelity FE and actual person manually performing the task.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-50a"></a>Discovery Testing Techniques</h1><h2><a name="ch-50"></a>Chapter 50: Testing Usability</h2>
<ul>
  <li>This is not rocket science.</li>
  <li>Key points:
  <ul>
    <li>Prefer high-fidelity user prototype.</li>
    <li>PM + Designer + Engineer.</li>
    <li>Prepare set of tasks to test.</li>
    <li>Ask for candid feedback, good or bad.</li>
    <li>Keep the users in &ldquo;use mode&rdquo; and out of &ldquo;critique&rdquo; mode.
    <ul>
      <li>What matters is whether users can easily do the tasks.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Keep quiet while the user is doing the task.
    <ul>
      <li>Avoid leading. Act like a parrot.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Objective: trying to figure out how your user thinks about the problem.</li>
    <li>Summarize the learnings.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-51"></a>Chapter 51: Testing Value</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Test demand, value qualitatively and quantitatively.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-52"></a>Chapter 52: Demand Testing Techniques</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Testing for demand is easy.</li>
  <li>Fake door demand testing:
  <ul>
    <li>Add button to new functionality but do not build anything.</li>
    <li>Check click-through rate.</li>
    <li>Ask in the fake page for volunteers to talk about the feature.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Same idea: landing page demand test but for whole product.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-53"></a>Chapter 53: Qualitative Value Testing Techniques</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Not for proving anything but for quick learnings and big insights.</li>
  <li>The single most important discovery activity.</li>
  <li>2-3 per week.</li>
  <li>Don&rsquo;t hire a firm to do this.</li>
  <li>Steps:
  <ol>
    <li>Customer interviews.</li>
    <li>Usability test.</li>
    <li>Value test, check if they are willing to pay:
    <ol>
      <li>Money: give you credit card details or sign a non-binding letter of intent to buy.</li>
      <li>Reputation: Recommend to friends, in social media, workmates.</li>
      <li>Time: work with you for a significant time.</li>
    </ol></li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-54"></a>Chapter 54: Quantitative Value Testing Techniques</h2>
<ul>
  <li>To collect evidence.</li>
  <li>Types:
  <ol>
    <li>Live-data prototype.</li>
    <li>A/B testing:
    <ul>
      <li>1% or fewer users.</li>
      <li>High volume traffic.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Invite-only testing:
    <ul>
      <li>For risk-adverse or low volume.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Use clients from the customer discovery program.</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-56"></a>Chapter 56: Testing Business Viability</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Stakeholders:
  <ul>
    <li>Marketing.</li>
    <li>Sales.</li>
    <li>Customer Success.</li>
    <li>Finance.</li>
    <li>Legal.</li>
    <li>Business development.</li>
    <li>Security.</li>
    <li>CEO/COO/GM.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-58a"></a>Transformation Techniques</h1><h2><a name="ch-58"></a>Chapter 58: Discovery Sprint Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>One week time-box of product discovery work to tackle a substantial risk.</li>
  <li>Sprint: how to solve big problems and test new ideas in just five days.</li>
  <li>Use when:
  <ol>
    <li>Something big/critical/difficult to tackle.</li>
    <li>When learning product discovery.</li>
    <li>When moving too slow.</li>
  </ol></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-59"></a>Chapter 59: Pilot Team Technique</h2>
<ul>
  <li>To avoid freaking out the laggards.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-60"></a>Chapter 60: Weaning an Organization Off Roadmaps</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Highlight the business outcome the feature is intended to help.
  <ul>
    <li>Celebrate if it does.</li>
    <li>In not; emphasize that the feature was delivered but the result was not.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h1><a name="ch-61a"></a>Process @ Scale</h1><h2><a name="ch-61"></a>Chapter 61: Managing Stakeholders</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Stakeholder: has vote power.</li>
  <li>PM responsibility:
  <ul>
    <li>Understand considerations and constraints of stakeholders.</li>
    <li>Commit to find solutions that also work for the stakeholders.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Success in stakeholder management == trust.
  <ul>
    <li>Trust comes from knowledge in customer, analytics, tech, industry and specially your business.</li>
    <li>Gain trust by openly sharing what we learn.</li>
  </ul></li>
  <li>Spend 1-2-1 time during discovery.</li>
  <li>Group settings is not the forum for designing strong products.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-62"></a>Chapter 62: Communicating Product Learnings</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Head of product to highlight big learnings at all-hands. Not more than 30 mins.</li>
</ul><h1><a name="part-V"></a>Part V: The Right Culture</h1><h2><a name="ch-64"></a>Chapter 64: Good Product Team/Bad Product Team</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Bad teams show the prototypes to engineers during sprint planning so they can estimate.</li>
  <li>Speed comes from the right techniques and not forced labor.</li>
  <li>Bad teams consider analytics and reporting a nice to have.</li>
  <li>Good teams obsess over their reference customers. Bad teams obsess over their competitors.</li>
  <li>Good teams celebrate impact. Bad teams celebrate when they finally release something.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-65"></a>Chapter 65: Top Reasons for Loss of Innovation</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Missing one or more of:
  <ul>
    <li>Customer-centric culture.</li>
    <li>Compelling product vision.</li>
    <li>Focused product strategy.</li>
    <li>Strong product managers.</li>
    <li>Stable product teams.</li>
    <li>Engineers in discovery.</li>
    <li>Corporate courage.</li>
    <li>Empowered product teams.</li>
    <li>Time to innovate.</li>
    <li>Product mindset.</li>
  </ul></li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-66"></a>Chapter 66: Top Reasons for Loss of Velocity</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Tech debt.</li>
  <li>Lack of strong PM.</li>
  <li>Lack of delivery management.</li>
  <li>Infrequent releases.</li>
  <li>Lack of product vision and strategy.</li>
  <li>Lack of co-located, durable product teams.</li>
  <li>Not including engineers early enough during product discovery.</li>
  <li>Not utilizing product design in discovery and instead having them try to do their work at the same time the engineers are trying to build.</li>
  <li>Changing priorities.</li>
  <li>A consensus culture.</li>
</ul><h2><a name="ch-67"></a>Chapter 67: Establishing a Strong Product Culture</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Two dimensions:
  <ol>
    <li>Consistently innovate:
    <ul>
      <li>Experiments.</li>
      <li>Open mind.</li>
      <li>Empowerment.</li>
      <li>Technology.</li>
      <li>Business and customer-savvy teams.</li>
      <li>Team diversity.</li>
      <li>Discovery techniques.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Consistent execution:
    <ul>
      <li>Urgency.</li>
      <li>High integrity commitments.</li>
      <li>Empowerment.</li>
      <li>Accountability.</li>
      <li>Collaboration.</li>
      <li>Results (vs output).</li>
      <li>Recognition.</li>
    </ul></li>
  </ol></li>
  <li>Most companies that are exceptionally strong at execution are pretty tough places to work.</li>
  <li>Only a few companies are strong both at innovation and execution.</li>
</ul>]]></description></item></channel></rss>